<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Dubious History</title>
 <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2021-11-14T19:48:09+01:00</updated>
 <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Marco Polo's ever-controversial travels</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/marco-polo"/>
   <updated>2021-06-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/marco-polo</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Marco Polo, the Venetian merchant who traveled across Asia at the end of the 13th century, is deeply ingrained in our history.  He became synonymous with traveling and adventure, countless brands and companies bear his name, and his story continues to inspire movies, books, and video games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He definitely wasn’t the first European who reached China, but his book surpassed all other records both in the scope and the popularity.  But right from the start, his book was met with large skepticism and it raised many controversies, some of which continue to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book was actually written by a romance writer Rustichello da Pis as a collection of Polo’s memories, which he relayed to him while they were allegedly imprisoned together during the Venetian-Genoese wars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is very little written about the life of Marco outside of travels.  All that we learn about his family are the names of his father Niccolò and uncle Maffeo, and that they sailed away before Marco’s birth and returned to Venice in 1269 when he was fifteen years old. [Preface, Chapter 9]&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:yule&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:yule&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;historical-record&quot;&gt;Historical record&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by stating the fact, that most scholars believe that Polo was a real person.  His name is mentioned in many contemporary Italian documents, genealogies, and even legal proceedings from which we can learn more about his family and life.  His last will was found, as well as wills of his two uncles, which provide some additional information too, most famously the notion of freeing a Tartar servant called Peter from his service. [Appendix 3]&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:yule:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:yule&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these documents, however, mention anything about his travels or China at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marco Polo was likely born in Venice, although there is no proof of his place of birth, around 1254 CE.  The theory that he was born on the island of Korčula in today’s Croatia remains highly controversial, however, he is still connected to Korčula, as it is considered the place where he was taken a prisoner by Genoese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first author who attempted to piece together some facts about his life was Venetian geographer Giovanni Battista Ramusio in the 16th century.  Though he himself most likely traveled a little, his &lt;em&gt;Navigation and Travels&lt;/em&gt; was an important resource documenting, discussing, and comparing journeys of famous explorers like Polo, Magellan, Niccolò de’ Conti, and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramusio’s book, based mostly on the Venetian oral tradition, is our sole source for the well-known story of Polo’s involvement in the Battle of Korčula which led to his imprisonment in Genoa where he met Rustichello.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is a mention of him in a chronicle written by another contemporary, Dominican friar Jacopo d’Acqui.  This chronicle, written during Polo’s life or very soon after, describes his involvement in the Battle of Layas (nowadays called Yumurtalık), which took place a few years earlier in 1294.  Henry Yule’s opinion on this is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This statement regarding the capture of Marco at the Battle of Ayas is one which cannot be true, for we know that he did not reach Venice till 1295. […] But though we cannot accept the statement that Polo was taken prisoner at Ayas, we may accept the passage as evidence from a contemporary source that he was &lt;em&gt;taken prisoner in some sea-fight with the Genoese&lt;/em&gt;, and thus admit it in corroboration of the Ramusian Tradition of a sea-fight at Curzola in 1298, which is perfectly consistent with all other facts in our posession. [Introduction]&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:yule:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:yule&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;d’Aqui’s report is also the origin of Polo’s famous deathbed quote that “he had not told one-half of what he had really seen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another piece of evidence comes from Polo’s contemporary author, Padovan scholar Pietro d’Abano.  According to one of his books, he knew Polo personally and he talked to him about an astronomical observation (curiously, not included in Polo’s book), which wasn’t observed in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/Marco/starsketch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A sketch of an astronomical phenomenon seen by Polo in South China, from Yule vol. I¹&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;A sketch of an astronomical phenomenon seen by Polo in South China, from Yule vol. I¹ &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;was-he-really-in-china&quot;&gt;Was he really in China?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the various manuscripts started to be more thoroughly analyzed in the 19th century, the consensus was that Polo’s book, although highly exaggerated, was probably based on truth.  As the contact and the language exchange with China broadened, more and more places were identified with known cities and provinces, despite their names often changed beyond recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some scholars argued long ago that Polo didn’t undergo the journey to the south-west of China (marked in dotted line on the map below), due to the lack of details compared to his other journey along the Grand Canal.  Historians such as K. D. Hullmann, Herbert Franke, Craig Clunas, and Frances Wood have all researched this question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the 1995 book by sinologist Dr. Frances Wood, &lt;em&gt;Did Marco Polo Go to China?&lt;/em&gt;, caused quite a stir by claiming that Polo never went farther east than the merchant outposts in the Black Sea and went as far as to claim that the whole persona of Marco Polo might be a fabrication.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:wood&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:wood&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main arguments of Wood’s book are that most of the information could be found in contemporary Persian sources, that Polo is not mentioned in any Chinese sources, numerous inaccuracies in descriptions, and the fact that Polo omits some practices and structures which one would expect in a description of China, like the Great Wall, tea-drinking, calligraphy, foot-binding, or the usage of chopsticks, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the more glaring inconsistencies is the description of the Battle of Xiangyang, in which he mentions that he, along with his father and uncle, were present at the siege.  However, it is believed that the siege had already ended before Marco Polo’s arrival in China.  The book even claims that Polos overturn the battle by introducing Chinese to the concept of trebuchet, which is according to Chinese sources attributed to a family of Muslim engineers.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:liang&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:liang&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in Venice, Wood argues, the story of the Polo family lacks sufficient corroboration.  There were several Polo families and Marco was a popular name.  There’s a Polo will of the right date but it mentions nothing about China or any travels into the Orient, nor that he bequeaths anything unique to his daughters.  The depiction of Peter as a “Tartar” doesn’t necessarily imply that Marco Polo brought Peter from his travels in the Far East as Tatar servants were a commonplace at that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As we don’t have the ‘original’ manuscript, all speculation as to how the text was compiled is just speculation,” Wood says. “Rustichello could have compiled travelers’ tales and existing texts but his involvement may also be a fabrication – we are talking about a time when the idea of authorship and copyright simply didn’t exist.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her strongest argument, however, is the total absence of his name in Chinese sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;History of Yuan&lt;/em&gt; mentions a certain Boluo, an adversary of Khan, being arrested in 1274.  The accusation was that Boluo had walked on the same side of the road as a female courtesan, in contravention of the order for men and women to walk on opposite sides of the road inside the city.  This Boluo was said to be a governor and superintendent of salt production in Yangzhou, but it was found out that it refers to a Mongol named Poulad in Persian sources and Bolad Akha in Mongol, not Marco Polo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francis Woodman Cleaves noted in 1970s that Polo’s account of the voyage of the princess Kököchin from China to Persia to marry the Īl-khān in 1293 has been confirmed by a passage in the 15th century Chinese work Yongle Encyclopedia, and by the Persian historian Rashid-al-Din Hamadani in his Jami’ al-tawarikh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, neither of these accounts mentions Polo or indeed any European as part of the bridal party, although the Yongle Encyclopedia confirms the names of three convoys, Oulatai, Apusca, and Coja, mentioned by Polo.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cleaves&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cleaves&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;probably&quot;&gt;…probably!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, many historians specializing in East Asia history criticized Wood’s work quite harshly.  Several authors pointed out poor scholarship, blatant errors, and argued against most of the points that were brought up.  Igor de Rachewiltz, translator of &lt;em&gt;The Secret History of the Mongols&lt;/em&gt;, and an authority on Mongol rule in China, answered Wood’s arguments several years ago.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:rachewiltz&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:rachewiltz&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Morris Rossabi, biographer of Khubilai Khan, also supports Marco’s veracity.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:rossabi&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:rossabi&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the Great Wall of China, while certainly already there, was far less impressive than the structure we know today, built several centuries after Polo’s visit.  Moreover, other European visitors to China during the Yuan dynasty, such as Giovanni de’ Marignolli, or Odoric of Pordenone, said nothing about the wall either.  Another 13th-century Muslim traveler Ibn Battuta, who asked about the wall when he visited China shortly after Marco, could find no one who had either seen it or knew of anyone who had seen it.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:battuta&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:battuta&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foot-binding was mentioned by Odoric, but no other travelers.  Also, tea-drinking wasn’t actually mentioned in European literature until Ramusio’s aforementioned &lt;em&gt;Navigations and Travels&lt;/em&gt; from 1550.  Also, while Polo mentions wine and other drinks, his omission of tea could be intentional, similarly to his description of Xichang in which he mentions a plethora of spices, but then adds that there are “other spices which never reach our countries, so we need say nothing about them”. [Book II, Chapter 47]&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:yule:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:yule&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A much more compelling argument of Wood’s book is the number of errors and inaccuracies in Polo’s description of e.g. Marco Polo Bridge, the city wall of Khanbaliq, and descriptions of Chinese ships.  However, his accounts do describe some Chinese nautical inventions which until then weren’t mentioned in European sources such as the watertight compartments or bulkhead partitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important fact to consider is that Polos spent most of their time with the Mongols, and Chinese culture might not be that apparent under the yoke.  It is unlikely that he would learn the Chinese language, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a 2012 study, German sinologist Hans Ulrich Vogel argues that the descriptions of currencies, salt production sites, and revenues were unprecedented in its time.  Not only does he detail the shape and size of the paper, but he also describes the use of seals and the various denominations of paper money.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:vogel&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:vogel&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wood accused Polo of confusing cowry money with Chinese ceramic-porcelain, but Vogel argues that Polo’s description was unique because he was the only writer to mention the use of the cowry as a currency in Yunnan during the Yuan.  Not only was Polo the sole non-Chinese author to mention this, but he also accurately pointed out that the cowries were not local, but imported from India.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:vogel2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:vogel2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the scholars, however, do agree that accounts of Polo’s travels and importance in China are full of inaccuracies, exaggerations, and, possibly, fabrications.  Nonetheless, some of Polo’s descriptions of the Chinese people and their country were remarkably accurate for its time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-be-dragons&quot;&gt;Here be dragons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In comparison to other contemporary reports from the Far East, Polo’s accounts are relatively sober when it comes to fantastical elements.  It even dispels some of the earlier myths, like the old Persian belief that asbestos is made from the hide of an animal called &lt;em&gt;samandar&lt;/em&gt; (which by extension led to the myth that salamanders can withstand fire).  Polo instead says that it is “a substance found in the earth”. [Book I, Chapter 42]&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:yule:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:yule&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The description of the ‘unicorn’ can be safely identified with Sumatran rhinoceros. [Book III, Chapter 9]&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:yule:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:yule&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, some stories continue to raise questions, such as his description of a two-legged ‘dragon’ in Southeast China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Here are found snakes and huge serpents, ten paces in length and ten spans in girth [15m, 240 cm]. At the fore part, near the head, they have two short legs, each with three claws, as well as eyes larger than a loaf and very glaring. The jaws are wide enough to swallow a man, the teeth are large and sharp, and their whole appearance is so formidable that neither man, nor any kind of animal can approach them without terror. Others are of smaller size, being eight, six, or five paces long. [Book II, Chapter 49]&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:yule:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:yule&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/Marco/drago2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;From French manuscript Livre des merveilles, 1410-1412.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;From French manuscript Livre des merveilles, 1410-1412. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we should note that dragons of various shapes and proportions were already featured in various legends and bestiaries of the time. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:dragons&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:dragons&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Just as the stories about the dog-headed people, which Polo connected with the Andaman Islands.  A very similar description of these dog-headed barbarians is featured in the legend of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gates_of_Alexander&quot;&gt;Gates of Alexander&lt;/a&gt;, which the book cites on several other occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Angamanain is a very large Island. The people are without a king and are Idolaters, and no better than wild beasts. And I assure you all the men of this Island of Angamanain have heads like dogs, and teeth and eyes likewise; in fact, in the face they are all just like big mastiff dogs! They have a quantity of spices; but they are a most cruel generation, and eat everybody that they can catch, if not of their own race.  They live on flesh and rice and milk, and have fruits different from any of ours. [Book III, Chapter 13]&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:yule:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:yule&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, Ibn Battuta, reported the people “whose mouths are like those of dogs” in roughly the same area as Polo - on islands between India and Sumatra.  This led to speculations that these descriptions refer to indigenous tribes such as Mentawai people who practice &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_tooth_sharpening&quot;&gt;teeth-sharpening&lt;/a&gt; to this day.  Here’s Battuta’s report for a comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fifteen days after leaving Sunaridwan we reached the country of the Barahnakar, whose mouths are like those of dogs. This tribe is a rabble, professing neither the religion of the Hindus nor any other. […] Their men are shaped like ourselves, except that their mouths are shaped like those of dogs; this is not the case with their womenfolk, however, who are endowed with surpassing beauty.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:battuta:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:battuta&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/Marco/dogheads.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ditto&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;ditto &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polo mentions yet another mythical creature in his description of Madagascar - an enormous bird from Persian legends called Rukh.  However, although this book is likely the first to mention this island in European or Asian literature, most of it is quite wrong, and the book makes it clear that the stories about it are based on secondhand accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For persons who had been there and had seen it told Messer Marco Polo that it was for all the world like an eagle, but one indeed of enormous size; so big in fact that its wings covered an extent of 30 paces [23 m], and its quills were 12 paces long, and thick in proportion. And it is so strong that it will seize an elephant in its talons and carry him high into the air, and drop him so that he is smashed to pieces. [Book III, Chapter 33]&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:yule:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:yule&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alaskan-coastline&quot;&gt;Alaskan coastline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1887, a set of 14 parchments were brought to America by an Italian teenaged immigrant named Marcian Rossi, who claimed that Marco Polo entrusted them to one of his ancestors.  The parchments include stories written by one of Marco’s daughters, Bella and Fantina, and most importantly a crudely drawn map that seems to depict the Alaskan coastline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also notes that they came across “people who speak the Tartar language, and […] go about dressed in sealskins, living on fish.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:alaska&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:alaska&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rossi donated this parchment, named &lt;em&gt;Map with Ship&lt;/em&gt;, to the Library of Congress in the 1930s, which even caught the attention of FBI’s J. Edgar Hoover who prompted further investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thorough study of all 14 documents was published in 2014 by a historian of cartography Benjamin B. Olshin.  Olshin has been researching these documents for 13 years and he was the first scholar to fully decode and translate the maps and to trace Rossi’s ancestry to Venice.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:olshin&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:olshin&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olshin himself notes that there are many questions about the authenticity of these documents.  The inscriptions, written in Italian, Latin, Arabic, and even Chinese suggest that it must have been made by someone knowledgeable in languages and cartography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand recent radiocarbon dating of this parchment revealed that it dates to the 15th or 16th centuries, meaning that it is a later copy of the original or at worst a forgery.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hessler&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hessler&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  The other parchments mention and depict the New World and travelers like Cortez and Columbus. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:myoldmaps&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:myoldmaps&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Those mentions are not out-of-place for the time they’re dated to, but the shape of the Alaskan coast, and the strait separating it from Asia wasn’t mapped until the 18th-century voyages of Vitus Bering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/Marco/map_with_ship.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Map With Ship parchment, depicting the Bering Strait, stored in Library of Congress.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;A Map With Ship parchment, depicting the Bering Strait, stored in Library of Congress. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reconstructing-the-route&quot;&gt;Reconstructing the route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the book is written more like an itinerary rather than a journal, it rarely explicitly states whether Polo actually visited the places it mentions.  Tracing the path between the cities in the order they’re mentioned quickly reveals that such a route would be highly impractical.  That suggests that a lot of stuff is compiled from previous sources, especially the description of Persian provinces, regions of today’s Mongolia, and inner China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As there are around 150 manuscripts in different languages and none of them can be considered the original, many Chinese and Mongol names were changed beyond recognition.  However, most of the place names correspond to their modern renditions remarkably well.  Like &lt;em&gt;Taianfu (=Taiyuan)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Chinginju (=Changzhou)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Yanju (=Yangzhou)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Saianfu (=Xiangyang)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Linju (=Linyi)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Yachi (=Yuxi)&lt;/em&gt;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some scholars, most notably famous 19th-century orientalist and geographer Henry Yule and more recently Amelia Carolina Sparavigna of the Polytechnic University of Turin, attempted to identify all places and even reconstruct the most likely path which Polo took based on historical roads and other contemporary itineraries.  Today, the absolute majority of names have been identified, but some are still a subject of controversy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/Marco/map2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Conjectural route based on the Yule-Cordier translation.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Conjectural route based on the Yule-Cordier translation. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This data, based on the Yule-Cordier edition, can be downloaded in KML format here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/i/Marco/places.kml&quot;&gt;Towns &amp;amp; cities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/i/Marco/route.kml&quot;&gt;Conjectural route&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:yule&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yule, H. &amp;amp; Cordier, H. &lt;em&gt;The Travels of Marco Polo, the 3rd edition annotated by Henri Cordier&lt;/em&gt;, 1920. &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/bookofsermarcopo01polo&quot;&gt;Volume I&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/bookofsermarcopo01polo&quot;&gt;Volume II&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Travels_of_Marco_Polo&quot;&gt;incomplete HTML version&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:yule&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:yule:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:yule:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:yule:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:yule:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:yule:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:yule:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:yule:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:yule:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:wood&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Wood, Frances. &lt;em&gt;Did Marco Polo Go to China?&lt;/em&gt;, 1995. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:wood&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:liang&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Liang, Jieming. &lt;em&gt;Chinese Siege Warfare: Mechanical Artillery &amp;amp; Siege Weapons of Antiquity&lt;/em&gt;, 2006. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:liang&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cleaves&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/2718743&quot;&gt;Cleaves, F. W. &lt;em&gt;A Chinese Source Bearing on Marco Polo’s Departure From China and a Persian Source on His Arrival in Persia&lt;/em&gt;, 1976.&lt;/a&gt; (jstor.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cleaves&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:rachewiltz&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://openresearch-repository.anu.edu.au/bitstream/1885/41883/1/Marcopolo.html&quot;&gt;Rachewiltz, I. &lt;em&gt;F. Wood’s Did Marco Polo Go To China? A Critical Appraisal&lt;/em&gt;, 2016&lt;/a&gt; (anu.edu.au) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:rachewiltz&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:rossabi&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://afe.easia.columbia.edu/mongols/pop/polo/mp_essay.htm&quot;&gt;Rossabi, M. &lt;em&gt;Did Marco Polo Really Go To China?&lt;/em&gt;, 2004&lt;/a&gt; (columbia.edu) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:rossabi&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:battuta&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/ibnbattutatravel00harg&quot;&gt;Gibb, H.A.R. &lt;em&gt;Ibn Battuta Travels In Asia And Africa 1325 To 1354&lt;/em&gt;, 1929.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:battuta&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:battuta:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:vogel&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2012/04/120416100439.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marco Polo was not a swindler: He really did go to China&lt;/em&gt;, 2012.&lt;/a&gt; (sciencedaily.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:vogel&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:vogel2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://reviews.history.ac.uk/review/1667&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marco Polo Was in China: New Evidence from Currencies, Salts and Revenues&lt;/em&gt;, 2012.&lt;/a&gt; (reviews.history.ac.uk) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:vogel2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:dragons&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.getty.edu/iris/separating-myth-from-legend-about-the-medieval-dragon/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Separating Myth from Legend about the Medieval Dragon&lt;/em&gt;, 2018.&lt;/a&gt; (getty.edu) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:dragons&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:alaska&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medievalists.net/2014/09/marco-polo-go-alaska/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Did Marco Polo go to Alaska?&lt;/em&gt;, 2014&lt;/a&gt; (medievalist.net) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:alaska&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:olshin&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Olshin, Benjamin B. &lt;em&gt;The Mysteries of the Marco Polo Maps&lt;/em&gt;, 2014. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:olshin&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hessler&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20120203012855/http://warpinghistory.blogspot.com/2008/12/sketching-unknown-phenomenologicalandco.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sketching the Unknown: A Phenomenological and Computational Study of the Rossi “Map With Ship”&lt;/em&gt;, 2008&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hessler&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:myoldmaps&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.myoldmaps.com/late-medieval-maps-1300/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marco Polo maps in the Rossi Collection, ca. 1350&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (myoldmaps.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:myoldmaps&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Kap-Dwa - a two-headed giant</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/artifacts/kap-dwa"/>
   <updated>2021-04-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/artifacts/kap-dwa-two-headed-giant</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kap-Dwa&lt;/em&gt; is allegedly a mummified body of a 12-foot [3.7 m] tall two-headed giant from Patagonia, making him potentially the only material proof of Patagonian giants we have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side-note&lt;/strong&gt;: Right from the start, we should note that although the Patagonian giants are well established in the historical record, there are no mentions of the two-headed variety, apart from those discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&quot;/patagonian-giants&quot;&gt;Patagonian Giants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/KapDwa/horizontal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual narrative, on which the majority of articles on &lt;em&gt;Kap-Dwa&lt;/em&gt; are based, comes from a story run by British magazine &lt;em&gt;Fortean Times&lt;/em&gt;, specializing in anomalous phenomena and mysteries, from 1998 to 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Two-headed Patagonian Giant”, said to have been over 12ft (3.7m) tall, was a famous fairground attraction allegedly brought to England in the 19th century. The story was that he had been captured by Spanish sailors in 1673 and bound to the mainmast. He broke loose and killed four of his captors, before being killed himself by a boarding pike plunged into his heart [FT112:15] &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fortean&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fortean&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the early 1900s, the stuffed giant was purchased by a Mr Bartram who toured the country on the Edwardian horror circuit, ending up in Weston-super-Mare in Somerset, where the curiosity passed through several hands and was exhibited at various locations. […] It was sold to a showman called “Lord” Thomas Howard in 1959, after which it left Weston.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fortean:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fortean&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some websites also mention that there are other versions of the story, or conflate them together, but we will get to each of them later.  So, let’s see what we can find in the depths of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;origins&quot;&gt;Origins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earliest record we could dig up mentions the two-headed Patagonian giant only circumstantially in an 1889 &lt;em&gt;Pittsburgh Dispatch&lt;/em&gt; column, which used him for a proposal of a ‘psychological puzzle’ about the workings of the giant’s mind.  The giant is not named.  More importantly, though, it provides us with the historically first version of the story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;He was captured 200 miles from the coast of Patagonia.  Both of his heads were lassoed at one and the same time by two Western cowboys.  […] The giant was subdued only when 160 shots from a Gatling gun had been poured into his body.  This remarkable product of animal kingdom has been examined by the wise men of the Smithsonian Institute and pronounced to be the Simon-pure, 18-carat article.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:pittsburgh&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:pittsburgh&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trace continues in an 1891 &lt;em&gt;The Philadephia Inquirer&lt;/em&gt; column about C.A. Bradenburgh’s dime museum in Philadelphia.  His alleged origins remain Patagonian and he is reported to be 11 feet tall.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:bradenburgh&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:bradenburgh&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side-note:&lt;/strong&gt; Among other requisites “the Turtle Boy, who is half boy and half turtle” is also advertised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/KapDwa/arch_museum.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The earliest confirmed location of two-headed Patagonian giant - C.A. Bradenburgh's Arch Museum on 9th and Arch Streets, Philadelphia, 1890s.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;The earliest confirmed location of two-headed Patagonian giant - C.A. Bradenburgh's Arch Museum on 9th and Arch Streets, Philadelphia, 1890s. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to an 1893 newspaper ad, the giant’s next stop was in M.C. Anderson’s &lt;em&gt;Wonderland Musee &amp;amp; Theatre&lt;/em&gt; in Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:wonderland&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:wonderland&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another newspaper reference leads us out of Pennsylvania for the first time.  The giant was exhibited in &lt;em&gt;Clark Street Museum&lt;/em&gt;, Chicago in 1899.  However, this time the advert says that he is of Maori origin [New Zealand]. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:clark&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:clark&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/KapDwa/wonderland_ad.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/KapDwa/clark_ad.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The Wilkes-Barre Record, 1893&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The Chicago Tribune, 1898&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-trip-to-england&quot;&gt;A trip to England&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, it seems to had made its way into England.  It was actually listed several times for sale in “want ads” in English print between 1989 and 1900.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:wantads&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:wantads&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One of the ads lists Bertram among its keywords, lending some credibility to FA’s story (although they spell it Bartram).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, just as the &lt;em&gt;Fortean Times&lt;/em&gt; say, it wound up in the Grand Pier in Weston-super-mare, England, which we can confirm with 1931 book by John Fothergill, an English innkeeper, and entrepreneur, who visited the pier and was fascinated by &lt;em&gt;Kap-Dwa&lt;/em&gt;.  He even set out to verify its authenticity by appointing physicist Guy Brown, an unnamed radiologist from Weston-super-mare hospital, and a local doctor, who allegedly inspected it and found “no perceptual evidence of its being a fake.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fothergill&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fothergill&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  The book doesn’t say whether this conclusion was based just on observation, or whether some more rigorous methods were used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much later, the giant was to be seen at Nottingham Goose Fair on 4th October 1959, as shown in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.macearchive.org/films/nottingham-goose-fair-october-1959&quot;&gt;this video around 08:10 mark&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:mace&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:mace&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  If we’re to believe &lt;em&gt;Fortean Times&lt;/em&gt;, it was owned by Thomas Howard during this time and it remained in England until at least 1971 (based on a photograph of the exhibit at Newcastle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/KapDwa/goose_fair.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/KapDwa/1970s_england.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1959, Goose Fair, Nottingham, England&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1971&lt;sup&gt;?&lt;/sup&gt;, England&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;back-in-the-usa&quot;&gt;Back in the USA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next mention is in an American newspaper from 1976.  This time, &lt;em&gt;Kap-Dwa&lt;/em&gt; was exhibited at various places in New Jersey and was said to be 2,000 years old.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:asbury&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:asbury&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:pennsauken&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:pennsauken&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  An article from a different newspaper from the same year repeats the 2,000 number and identifies the owner as a British woman named Chris Howard.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:courier&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:courier&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This once again seems to confirm the research conducted by &lt;em&gt;Fortean Times&lt;/em&gt; which reports that “Howard sold or transferred Kap Dwa to his brother Scott in New Jersey.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not clear where FA’s story about Spanish captors came from, but the Howard family apparently still favored the 2,000 years old narrative as late as 1977, indicating that the story emerged later.  &lt;em&gt;Fortean Times&lt;/em&gt; unfortunately, doesn’t provide any verifiable sources for their claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/KapDwa/70s_ad.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ads for Pennsauken mart from 1976—77.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Ads for Pennsauken mart from 1976—77. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exhibit now rests in a small curiosities and oddities shop called &lt;em&gt;Bob’s Side Show&lt;/em&gt; in Baltimore, owned by Robert Gerber.  He doesn’t mention how he obtained it.  According to his website:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The mummy was brought to England in the early 1800’s from Paraguay by Captain George Bickle who sailed out of Plymouth, England on the clipper ship Olive Branch.  It is said that the great P.T. Barnum tried in vain to buy Kap-Dwa on one of his trips to England. It was not until the mid 1950’s that Kap-Dwa left the Blackpool Museum to go on tour in the United States.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gerber&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gerber&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This account is evidently not very in line with the newspaper evidence presented earlier.  Also, although various ships named HMS &lt;em&gt;Olive Branch&lt;/em&gt; existed, there are no records of any captain George Bickle.  Berger was also quoted in a 1996 newspaper article saying that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We’ve had students from Hopkins [University], droves of them, and they all say he’s real.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gerber2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gerber2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there doesn’t seem to be any scientific report from Hopkins or any other universities or museums about this artifact.  This article also quotes a collector and sideshow historian Warren Raymond that “Nelson’s Supply House in South Boston cranked out Patagonian giants, charging $60 apiece.” confirming the advert mentioned earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the &lt;em&gt;Fortean Times&lt;/em&gt; published their aforementioned article two years after this news article was published, FA didn’t even acknowledge Gerber until four issues later.  So it seems that the story of Spanish sailors emerged after 1977 but before 1996.  By the way, they speculated that the American one could be an imitation.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fortean:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fortean&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, we do know that some replicas were made.  A 1939 article in &lt;em&gt;The San Francisco Examiner&lt;/em&gt; reprints an advertisement for a mummy they call &lt;em&gt;King Capuwar&lt;/em&gt;, 8 feet tall. “Made so Legs come off at the waist so as to ship in a box”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:examiner&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:examiner&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the photo shown in the article bears absolutely no resemblance to Berger’s mummy and the full-body which FA claims to be from the 60s matches Gerber’s mummy perfectly.  Moreover, there are no mentions of Kap-Dwa in English print after the 1970s and American newspaper reports starting in the 1970s suggest that it might be the same artifact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of their article, the &lt;em&gt;Fortean Times&lt;/em&gt; concludes with a statement that “showman Billy Hill had bought the giant from Howard in Blackpool” and that “he was last exhibited in Newcastle in 1999”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/KapDwa/heads.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mummy in Bob's Side Show, Baltimore&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Mummy in Bob's Side Show, Baltimore &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although the usual story correctly says that it was brought from England, the fact the mummy has its origins in American &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sideshow&quot;&gt;sideshows&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dime_museum&quot;&gt;dime museums&lt;/a&gt; is conveniently omitted.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fortean Times&lt;/em&gt; story about Spanish sailors or Berger’s story of captain George Bickle are not supported by any other sources.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The mentions of England apparently emerged only after it returned to the USA.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After the body left the USA, at least two other giants, most likely imitations, continued to be exhibited in the United States, namely &lt;em&gt;King Mac-A-Dula&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;King Capuwar&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:capuwar&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:capuwar&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Interestingly though, the name &lt;em&gt;Capuwar&lt;/em&gt; appears as early as 1892 and actually predates the name &lt;em&gt;Kap-Dwa&lt;/em&gt; in print.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:boston&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:boston&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although it had been put forward that the body was examined by various scientists, there is no published scientific analysis of &lt;em&gt;Kap-Dwa&lt;/em&gt;, despite the fact that it is known where he is currently located.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Given the context of the first appearance of the artifact, it is safe to assume that it is just an example of a &lt;em&gt;gaff taxidermy&lt;/em&gt; produced for entertainment and presentation purposes, similar to e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fiji_mermaid&quot;&gt;Fiji mermaids&lt;/a&gt; created from monkey and fish remains sewn together.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/&quot;&gt;newspapers.com&lt;/a&gt; sources are pay-walled, but you can get a free 7-day trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fortean&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20140331151313/http://www.forteantimes.com/strangedays/misc/74/the_twoheaded_giant.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The two-headed giant&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;em&gt;Fortean Times&lt;/em&gt; website (archived)&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fortean&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fortean:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fortean:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:pittsburgh&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/76233692&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pittsburgh Dispatch&lt;/em&gt;, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 03 Nov 1889, p. 7&lt;/a&gt; (newspapers.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:pittsburgh&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:bradenburgh&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/168413318/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Philadelphia Inquirer&lt;/em&gt;, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 27 Nov 1891, p. 7&lt;/a&gt; (newspapers.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:bradenburgh&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:wonderland&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/83185105/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Wilkes-Barre Record&lt;/em&gt;, Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania, 06 Dec 1893, p. 7&lt;/a&gt; (newspapers.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:wonderland&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:clark&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://newspapers.com/image/34180463/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Inter Ocean&lt;/em&gt;, Chicago, Illionis, 08 May 1898, p. 17&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://newspapers.com/image/349900114/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Chicago Tribune&lt;/em&gt;, Chicago, Illinois, 08 May 1898, p. 42&lt;/a&gt; (newspapers.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:clark&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:wantads&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Era&lt;/em&gt;, London, England, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/387838322&quot;&gt;24 Dec 1898, p. 25&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/387709485&quot;&gt;18 Mar 1899, p. 26&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/387719090&quot;&gt;12 May 1900, p. 28&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/387790491&quot;&gt;06 Oct 1900, p. 26&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/387833848&quot;&gt;24 Nov 1900, p. 25&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/387853475/&quot;&gt;22 Dec 1900, p. 26&lt;/a&gt; (newspapers.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:wantads&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fothergill&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/dli.ministry.14815/page/65/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Fothergill, John. &lt;em&gt;An innkeeper’s diary&lt;/em&gt;, 1931, p. 66—68&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fothergill&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:mace&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.macearchive.org/films/nottingham-goose-fair-october-1959&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nottingham Goose Fair October 1959&lt;/em&gt;, The Media Archive for Central England (MACE)&lt;/a&gt; (macearchive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:mace&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:asbury&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/145735699/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Asbury Park Press&lt;/em&gt;, Asbury Park, New Jersey, 26 Jun 1977, p. 4&lt;/a&gt; (newspapers.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:asbury&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:pennsauken&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/173595693&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Philadephia Inquirer&lt;/em&gt;, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 27 Oct 1977, p. 6&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/182681278/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Courier-Post&lt;/em&gt;, Camden, New Jersey, 06 Dec 1976, p. 14&lt;/a&gt; (newspapers.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:pennsauken&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:courier&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/222990150&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Courier-News&lt;/em&gt;, Bridgewater, New Jersey, 05 Sep 1978&lt;/a&gt; (newspapers.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:courier&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gerber&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theantiquemanltd.com/page1.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bob’s Side Show&lt;/em&gt; website (archived)&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gerber&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gerber2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newspapers.com/image/172228554/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Baltimore Sun&lt;/em&gt;, 26 Dec 1996, p. 1D &amp;amp; 8D.&lt;/a&gt; newspapers.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gerber2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:examiner&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/459201249&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The San Francisco Examiner&lt;/em&gt;, San Francisco, California, 03 Aug 1939, p. 56&lt;/a&gt; (newspapers.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:examiner&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:capuwar&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/533359003&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rutland Daily Herald&lt;/em&gt;, Rutland, Vermont, 23 Sep 1909, p. 5&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/478818835&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Courier-Post&lt;/em&gt;, Camden, New Jersey, 13 Aug 1915, p. 15&lt;/a&gt; (newspapers.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:capuwar&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:boston&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newspapers.com/image/430741152&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Boston Globe&lt;/em&gt;, Boston, Massachusetts, 13 Mar 1892, p. 10&lt;/a&gt; (newspapers.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:boston&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Patagonian Giants</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/patagonian-giants"/>
   <updated>2021-03-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/patagonian-giants</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many cultures and civilizations have stories about giants in their mythology or folklore.  The reports of their size greatly vary and characteristics range from vicious man-eating beasts to superior demigods.  But few of them have such a plethora of first-hand accounts in the historical literature as the Patagonia region, specifically the areas around the Strait of Magellan during the Age of Sail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/PatagonGiants/giants.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Un Matelot presentant a une Femme Patagonne un morceau de Biscuit pour son Enfant (Noach van der Meer, c. 1770)&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Un Matelot presentant a une Femme Patagonne un morceau de Biscuit pour son Enfant (Noach van der Meer, c. 1770) &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;historical-recrods&quot;&gt;Historical recrods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;16th-century&quot;&gt;16th century&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story usually starts with the 1519–22 expedition of Portuguese explorer Fernão de Magalhães better known as Magellan.  Out of more than 200 people who set sail, only 18 returned to tell the tale (Magellan himself died during the travels in 1521).  One of the men who returned was Antonio Pigafetta, whose records are our main source for the history of the expedition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding his accounts, none raised as much controversy as his description of giant inhabitants they encountered in Saint Julian inlet in today’s Argentina.  He immortalized them as the gigantic “Patagons” in his 1525 book, &lt;em&gt;Report on the First Voyage around the World&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We remained in that land for 13 days.  The proceeding on our way, we went as far as 34 and one-third degrees toward the Antarctic Pole, where we found people at a freshwater river, called Canibali, who eat human flesh.  One of them, in stature almost a giant, came to the flag-ship in order to assure [the safety of] the others, his friends.  He had a voice like a bull.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few paragraphs after, he writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Leaving that place, we finally reached 49 and one-half degree toward the Antarctic Pole. […] One day we suddenly saw a naked man of giant stature on the shore of the port, dancing, singing, and throwing dust on his head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When the giant was in the captain-general’s and our presence, he marveled greatly, and made signs with one finger raised upward, believing that we had come from the sky. He was so tall that we reached only to his waist, and he was well proportioned.  His face was large and painted red all over, while about his eyes he was painted yellow; and he had two hearts painted on the middle of his cheeks. His scanty hair was painted white. He was dressed in the skins of animals skilfully sewn together.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:pigafetta&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:pigafetta&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following pages describe many other encounters with various giants.  Magellan’s crew even captured two of them to bring back to Spain, but they became ill and died on the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pigafetta doesn’t provide a concrete estimate of their height, but another contemporary document does.  Three years before Pigafetta’s journal seen print, Maximillianus Transylvanus, the son of the Archbishop of Salzburg, interviewed three surviving members of the expedition.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:transylvanus&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:transylvanus&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  The English translation, which can be found in &lt;em&gt;The Philippine Islands, Vol. 1&lt;/em&gt; by Blair, Bourne &amp;amp; Robinson, says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These Indians were very tall, ten spans high [2.3 m, 7 ft. 7 in.], clad in skins of wild beasts, darker-complexioned than would have been expected in that part of the world.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:blair&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:blair&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Transylvanius’ number doesn’t seem too extraordinary from today’s perspective, Magellan’s expedition fixed Patagonia in the minds of Europeans as the &lt;em&gt;regio gigantum&lt;/em&gt; and soon, maps of the region featured illustrations of people nearly twice as tall as the explorers greeting them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/PatagonGiants/gigantum_regio.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Regio Gigantum from a 1562 map by Diego Gutiérrez&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Regio Gigantum from a 1562 map by Diego Gutiérrez &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be easy to dismiss the accounts of giants as a tall tale (&lt;em&gt;sorry&lt;/em&gt;), except that amount of reports had been only growing over time… Literally.  Starting with a brief mention from a Spanish expedition of García Jofre de Loaísa in 1525, which proposes astounding thirteen spans tall Patagonians [3 m, 10 ft.].&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:becco&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:becco&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One hundred years after Magellan, a detailed account of the voyages of Francis Drake was published by his nephew (of the same name).  Apparently not very fond of the “Spaniards’” stories, he reported about the Patagonians:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Magellane was not altogether deceived, in naming them Giants; for they generally differ from the common sort of men, both in stature, bignes, and strength of body, as also in the hideousness of their voice: but yet they are nothing so monstrous, or giant like as they were reported; there being some English men, as tall, as the highest of any that we could see, peradventure the Spaniards did not thinke that ever any English man would come thither to reprove them, and thereupon might presume to boldly lie; the name &lt;em&gt;Pentagones&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Five cubits&lt;/em&gt;, viz., 7 foote and halfe [2.3 m], describing the full height (if not somewhat more) of the highest of them.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:drake&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:drake&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the actual encounter happened, the book also mentions footprints whose “breadth was the length of one of our men’s feet of the largest size, which could be no other than the foot of a giant, so that we conjectured that the giants did possess some part of Brasilia on the north side of the river Plate.” [today’s Uruguay]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another member of the Francis Drake’s crew and his cousin, John Drake, was later captured by the Spanish and sent for the inquisition to provide a detailed account of the expedition.  In its transcript, Drake confirms a skirmish with giants in Saint Julian that resulted in the death of one native and two sailors.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:inquisition&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:inquisition&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:inquisition2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:inquisition2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently troubled by Drake’s raids, the Viceroy of Perú sent Pedro Sarmiento de Gamboa to secure the Strait of Magellan in 1579 to prevent the English from settling it first.  Throughout the book, he refers to various natives as giants.  And although not estimating the height, he says that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ten men, who had got out of the boat, attacked one of the natives and were scarcely able to hold him.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:sarmiento&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:sarmiento&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, they managed to kidnap one of the natives while being showered by arrows from his companions.  According to a footnote in an 1895 English translation, this giant was later brought to Spanish king Phillip II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last English expedition of the century to the Americas was led by Thomas Cavendish.  He reached the Strait of Magellan in 1587.  The first published report from this expedition says that they found footmarks “of a gigantic race, as the measure of one of their footmarks was eighteen inches [45,7 cm] long”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cavendish&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cavendish&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The height was specified by one of the members of the expedition, Anthonie Knivet.  Apart from estimating the height based on said footmarks, he mentions a freshly buried body:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Giants fifteeene or sixteene spans of height. I affirme, that at Port Desire I saw the footing of them, by the shoare side, that was aboute foure foote of one of our mens in length; and I saw two of them that were buried newly, the one of them was fourteene spannes long.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:knivet&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:knivet&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right before the turn of the century, two captains of the Dutch East Indies company reported about giants.  Sebald de Veert describes being attacked by “savages whom he thought to be ten or eleven feet high [3-3.3 m].”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:veert&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:veert&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  In the same year, Oliver Van Noort, had a &lt;em&gt;recontre&lt;/em&gt; with this gigantic race, whom he represents to be of high stature and of a terrible aspect.  It’s not clear whether these two accounts describe the same event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More interestingly, Noort seems to be the first one to note that not all tribes were this tall.  He specifically names a tribe “called &lt;em&gt;Tirimenen&lt;/em&gt;, dwelling in &lt;em&gt;Coin&lt;/em&gt;, which was of a gigantic stature, being ten or twelve feet high and continually at war with the other tribes”.  He describes all the other tribes as being of average height. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:noort&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:noort&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;17th-century&quot;&gt;17th century&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the sources from the 17th century don’t provide much factual information on giants, besides calling the natives “gigantic people”, “savages of a gigantic stature”, etc.  It should be noted, that some explorers who sailed through the Strait didn’t encounter these giants whatsoever or encountered people of ordinary height. (See the table below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notable exceptions are the first reports of skeletons from the expedition of Willem Corneliszoon Schouten: “graves with skeletons of very human beings, with bones 10 to 11 feet.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:schouten&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:schouten&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Hendrick Brouwer’s mention of “footsteps of men that measured eighteen inches [45.7m].”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:brouwer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:brouwer&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/PatagonGiants/skeletons.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;From Mirror of the Australian Navigation by Jacob le Maire, 1622&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;From Mirror of the Australian Navigation by Jacob le Maire, 1622 &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;18th-century&quot;&gt;18th century&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;French explorer Amédée-François Frézier, evidently fascinated by the stories of giants, wrote in 1714 that Don Pedro Molina and some other eye-witnesses told him about a tribe called &lt;em&gt;Caucahues&lt;/em&gt; which averaged to about nine or ten foot high.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:frezier&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:frezier&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 1764 a ship commanded by Commodore John Byron (grandfather of the famous poet) had a friendly encounter with a tribe of giants on Patagonia shore.  He estimated their height to be from eight to nine feet [2.5-2.8 m].&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:byron&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:byron&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to Noort and Frézier, he also emphasizes that there are several different tribes in the region, not all of them being this tall.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fitzroy&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fitzroy&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1767, Captain Samuel Wallis, apparently fed up with the conflicting reports about giants, sailed to Patagonia with a measuring rod.  There he measured some very tall people, for sure, but not giants.  The tallest man he measured was 6 feet 7 inches [2 m], with several others only an inch or two shorter.  But, he reported, most were between 5 feet 10 inches and six feet tall [~1.8 m].&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:wallis&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:wallis&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jesuit Thomas Falkner, who spent almost 40 years among the southern tribes, mentions a &lt;em&gt;Tehuelche&lt;/em&gt; chief “seven feet and some inches tall” [over 2.1 m] in his 1774 book.  He also notes that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Patagonians, or &lt;em&gt;Puelches&lt;/em&gt;, are a large bodied people ; but I have never heard of that gigantic race, which others have mentioned, though I have seen persons of all the different tribes of southern Indians.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:falkner&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:falkner&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that basically marks the end of the era of giants.  Following records from the 18th and 19th centuries all focus specifically on &lt;em&gt;Aónikenk&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Tehuelche&lt;/em&gt;) people and no measures exceed 2 meters.  There are no other mentions of &lt;em&gt;Caucahue&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Tirimenen&lt;/em&gt; people in other literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we know that &lt;a href=&quot;https://doorofperception.com/2016/10/the-lost-tribes-of-tierra-del-fuego/&quot;&gt;there were many extraordinary tribes&lt;/a&gt; in this part of the World which completely eradicated from history by diseases and genocides by European colonizers.  If any tribes of giants ever existed, they are among the victims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Source&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Magellan (1523)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:blair:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:blair&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ten spans [2.3 m, 7 ft. 6 in.]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;García Jofre de Loaísa (1525)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:becco:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:becco&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;thirteen spans [3 m, 9 ft. 9 in.]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Francis Drake (1577)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:drake:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:drake&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7 foote and halfe [2.3 m]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pedro Sarmiento de Gamboa (1579)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:sarmiento:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:sarmiento&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;big people / giants&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Anthonie Knivet (1591)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:knivet:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:knivet&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;corpse fourteen spans tall [3 m, 9 ft. 9 in.]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;fifteen to sixteen spans (based on footprints)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sebald de Veert (1599)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:veert:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:veert&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ten or eleven feet high [3-3.3 m]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Oliver van Noort (1599)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:noort:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:noort&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ten or twelve feet high [3-3.6 m]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Joris van Spilbergen (1614)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:spilbergen&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:spilbergen&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;a human being of very big stature&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Willem Schouten (1615)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:schouten:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:schouten&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;bones 10 to 11 feet [3-3.3 m]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Gonzalo García del Nodal (1618)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fitzroy:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fitzroy&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;taller, by the head, than the Europeans&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Jacques L’Hermite (1624) &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;./#hermite&quot;&gt;†&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;not larger than the inhabitants of Europe&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Dionisio de Rueda (1641) &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;./#rueda&quot;&gt;‡&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;gigantic people&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;John Narbrough (1670)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:narbrough&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:narbrough&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;people of average height/not taller that us&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Jean-Baptiste de Gennes (1696)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:froger&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:froger&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;not taller than six feet [1.8 m]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Harrington &amp;amp; Carman (1704)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:frezier:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:frezier&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;giants&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Pedro Molina y Valiente (1714)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:frezier:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:frezier&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;nine or ten foot [2.7-3m]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thomas Pascoe (1741)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:pascoe&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:pascoe&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;middling stature&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;John Byron (1764)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:byron:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:byron&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8 to 9 feet [2.5-2.8 m]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Charles de Brosses (1765)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:brosses&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:brosses&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;thirteen spans [3 m, 9 ft. 9 in.]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;corpse of fourteen spans [3.2 m, 10 ft. 5 in.]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Samuel Wallis (1767)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:wallis:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:wallis&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;six feet tall [2 m]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Louis de Bougainville (1676)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:bougainville&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:bougainville&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;between 5 feet 10 and 6 feet 2 [1.8-1.9 m]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thomas Falkner (1774)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:falkner:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:falkner&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7 feet and some inches tall [~2.1 m]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Antonio de Viedma (1783)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:viedma&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:viedma&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;between two varas and nine palms [~1.8 m, 6 ft.]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Alonso de Cordova (1785)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cordova&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cordova&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6 ft. 7 in. [2 m]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side-note:&lt;/strong&gt; It is important to take into account that between the 16th and 18th centuries the name “Patagonia” was given to all territory to the South of the Río de la Plata estuary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&quot;/artifacts/kap-dwa&quot;&gt;Kap-Dwa - a two-headed giant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patagoniamonsters.blogspot.com/2009/11/patagon-giants-part-1.html&quot;&gt;Austin Whitall - Patagonia Monsters: Patagonia Giants – Parts One&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://patagoniamonsters.blogspot.com/2009/11/patagon-giants-part-2.html&quot;&gt;Two&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;http://patagoniamonsters.blogspot.com/2009/11/patagon-giants-part-3-last-part.html&quot;&gt;Three&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fuegians&quot;&gt;Fuegians&lt;/a&gt; (wikipedia.org)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;hermite&quot;&gt;†&lt;/a&gt; Mentioned in Hawkesworth&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hawkesworth&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hawkesworth&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, p. xviii (1773).  We could not locate the original source.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;rueda&quot;&gt;‡&lt;/a&gt; Mentioned in Patagonian Monsters blog, but we could not locate the original source.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:pigafetta&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/magellansvoyagea01piga/page/46/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Pigafetta, Antonio. &lt;em&gt;Magellan’s Voyage: A Narrative Account of the First Circumnavigation&lt;/em&gt;, Antonio Pigafetta, 1552 (English translation, p. 47)&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:pigafetta&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:transylvanus&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/demoluccisinsuli00maxi/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Transylvanus, Maxmilianus. &lt;em&gt;De Moluccis Insulis&lt;/em&gt;, 1523&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:transylvanus&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:blair&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/13255&quot;&gt;Blair, Bourne, Robinson. &lt;em&gt;The Philippine Islands, 1483-1803 — Volume 01 of 55&lt;/em&gt;, 2004&lt;/a&gt; (gutenberg.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:blair&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:blair:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:becco&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/CronicasDeLosPatagones/page/n11/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Becco, Horatio J. &lt;em&gt;Crónicas de los Patagones&lt;/em&gt;, 2003, p. xiv&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:becco&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:becco:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:drake&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/worldencompassed16drak/page/n121/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Drake, Francis. &lt;em&gt;The World Encompassed by Sir Francis Drake&lt;/em&gt;, 1854, p. 60&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:drake&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:drake:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:inquisition&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://patlibros.org/djd/intro-eng.php?lan=eng&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deposition of John Drake to the Spanish Inquisition at Lima&lt;/em&gt;, Spanish transcription&lt;/a&gt; (patlibros.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:inquisition&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:inquisition2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/newlightondrakec34nuttuoft/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Nuttall, Zelia. &lt;em&gt;New light on Drake&lt;/em&gt;, 1914&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:inquisition2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:sarmiento&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/narrativesofvoya00sarmrich/page/136/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Sarmiento de Gamboa, Pedro. &lt;em&gt;Narratives of the voyages of Pedro Sarmiento de Gambóa to the straits of Magellan&lt;/em&gt;, 1579-1589 (English translation, p. 136)&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:sarmiento&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:sarmiento:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cavendish&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/ageneralhistory08unkngoog/page/n82/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Kerr, Robert. Harris’ &lt;em&gt;Voyage of Sir Thomas Candish Round the World, in 1586—1588&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;A general history and collection of voyages and travels&lt;/em&gt;, 1811, p. 70&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cavendish&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:knivet&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/32882019295362-hakluytusposthu/page/n293/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Purchas, Samuel. Knivet’s memoir in &lt;em&gt;Purchas his Pilgrimes, vol. XVI&lt;/em&gt;, 1905, p. 264&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:knivet&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:knivet:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:veert&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/ldpd_6424148_000/page/319/mode/2up&quot;&gt;de Reneville, Constantine. &lt;em&gt;A collection of voyages undertaken by the Dutch East-India Company for the improvement of trade and navigation&lt;/em&gt;, 1703, p. 319&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:veert&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:veert:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:noort&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/generalhistoryco10kerrrich/page/118/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Kerr, Robert. &lt;em&gt;A general history and collection of voyages and travels, arranged in systematic order: forming a complete history of the origin and progress of navigation, discovery, and commerce, by sea and land, from the earliest ages to the present time&lt;/em&gt;, 1824, p. 119&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:noort&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:noort:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:schouten&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/relacindiariade00schogoog/page/n35/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Schouten, W. C. &lt;em&gt;Relación diaria del viaje de Jacobo Le Maire y Guillermo Cornelio Schouten&lt;/em&gt;, 1620s&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:schouten&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:schouten:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:brouwer&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libros.uchile.cl/files/presses/1/monographs/431/submission/proof/6/&quot;&gt;Brouwer, Hendrick. &lt;em&gt;A voyage to the Kingdom of Chili in America&lt;/em&gt;, 1744, p. 388&lt;/a&gt; (uchile.cl) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:brouwer&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:frezier&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/voyagetosouthse00frzi/page/84/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Frézier, A. F. &lt;em&gt;A voyage to the South-Sea, and along the coasts of Chili and Peru, in the years 1712, 1713, and 1714&lt;/em&gt;, 1717&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:frezier&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:frezier:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:frezier:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:byron&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/A020088/page/n55/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Officer on Board the Said Ship the Dolph. &lt;em&gt;Voyage round the world, in his Majesty’s ship the Dolphin, commanded by the Honourable Commodore Byron&lt;/em&gt;, 1767&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:byron&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:byron:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fitzroy&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/narrativeofsurve21839fitz/page/104/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Fitzroy, Robert. &lt;em&gt;Narrative of the surveying voyages of His Majesty’s ships Adventure and Beagle between the years 1826 and 1836&lt;/em&gt;, 1839&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fitzroy&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fitzroy:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:wallis&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/accountofvoyages03hawk/page/788/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Hawkesworth, John. &lt;em&gt;An account of the voyages undertaken by the order of His present Majesty for making discoveries in the Southern Hemisphere, and successively performed by Commodore Byron, Captain Wallis, Captain Carteret, and Captain Cook, in the Dolphin, the Swallow, and the Endeavour&lt;/em&gt;, vol. iii, 1773&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:wallis&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:wallis:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:falkner&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/descriptionofpat01falk/page/n37/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Falkner, Thomas. &lt;em&gt;A description of Patagonia, and the adjoining parts of South America&lt;/em&gt;, 1774&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:falkner&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:falkner:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:spilbergen&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/eastwestindianmi00spiluoft/page/n121/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Van Spilbergen, J. &lt;em&gt;The East and West Indian mirror: being an account of Joris van Speilbergen’s voyage round the world (1614-1617)&lt;/em&gt;, 1906&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:spilbergen&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:narbrough&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/cihm_27895/page/n105/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Narbrough, John. &lt;em&gt;Sir John Narbrough’s voyage to the South-Sea&lt;/em&gt;, 1711&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:narbrough&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:froger&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/relationdunvoyag00frog_0/page/98/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Froger, François. &lt;em&gt;Relation d’un voyage fait en 1695. 1696. &amp;amp; 1697. aux côtes d’Afrique, détroit de Magellan, Brezil, Cayenne &amp;amp; isles Antilles, par une escadre des vaisseaux du roy, commandée par Monsieur de Gennes.&lt;/em&gt;, 1773, p. 98&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:froger&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:pascoe&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/a-true-and-impartial-journal-of-a-voyage-to-the-south-seas/page/125/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Pascoe, Thomas. &lt;em&gt;Voyage To The South Seas 1740—1744&lt;/em&gt;, 1745, p. 126&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:pascoe&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:brosses&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/bub_gal_ark_12148_bpt6k751404/page/n247/mode/2up&quot;&gt;de Brosses, Charles. &lt;em&gt;Histoire des navigations aux terres australes&lt;/em&gt;, 1756, p. 232&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:brosses&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:bougainville&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/voyageroundworld00boug/page/142/mode/2up&quot;&gt;de Bougainville, Luis. &lt;em&gt;A voyage round the world. Performed by order of His most Christian Majesty, in the years 1766, 1767, 1768, and 1769&lt;/em&gt;, 1772 (English translation, p. 142)&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:bougainville&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:viedma&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cervantesvirtual.com/obra/diario-de-un-viaje-a-la-costa-de-patagonia-para-reconocer-los-puntos-en-donde-establecer-poblaciones--0/&quot;&gt;de Viedma, Antonio. &lt;em&gt;Diario de un viaje a la costa de la Patagonia, para reconocer los puntos en donde establecer poblaciones&lt;/em&gt;, 1837&lt;/a&gt; (cervantesvirtual.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:viedma&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cordova&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/voyageofdiscove00varg/page/88/mode/2up&quot;&gt;de Vargas Ponce, José. &lt;em&gt;A voyage of discovery to the strait of Magellan: with an account of the manners and customs of the inhabitants; and of the natural productions of Patagonia&lt;/em&gt;, 1788, (English translation), p. 88&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cordova&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hawkesworth&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/anaccountvoyage01hawkgoog/page/n40/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Hawkesworth, John. &lt;em&gt;An account of the voyages undertaken by the order of His present Majesty for making discoveries in the Southern Hemisphere, and successively performed by Commodore Byron, Captain Wallis, Captain Carteret, and Captain Cook, in the Dolphin, the Swallow, and the Endeavour&lt;/em&gt;, vol. i, 1773&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hawkesworth&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dighton Rock</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/artifacts/dighton-rock"/>
   <updated>2021-03-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/artifacts/dighton-rock</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Dighton Rock, a crystalline sandstone boulder found in the riverbed of the Taunton River in current Berkley, Massachusetts, bears petroglyphs which are still controversial to this day.  This artifact is remarkable mainly for how long it is has been generating a range of very diverse speculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/DightonRock/DightonRock.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Crop from Seth Eastman at Dighton Rock by Horatio B. King, 1853.  Petroglyphs are traced with chalk.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Crop from Seth Eastman at Dighton Rock by Horatio B. King, 1853.  Petroglyphs are traced with chalk. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first reference to the carvings on the Dighton Rock dates back to 1680, shortly after the suppression of the rebellion of Wampanoag Indians, when recent Harvard graduate John Danforth spotted the rock in what was then the town of Dighton and made a drawing of its carvings.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:inscriptions&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:inscriptions&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A book &lt;em&gt;The Wonderful Works of God Commemorated&lt;/em&gt; by Cotton Mather from 1690 makes a reference to the rock:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Among the other Curiosities of New-England, one is that of a mighty Rock, on a perpendicular side whereof by a River, which at High Tide covers part of it, there are very deeply Engraved, no man alive knows How or When about half a score Lines, near Ten Foot Long, and a foot and half broad, filled with strange Characters: which would suggest as odd Thoughts about them that were here before us, as there are odd Shapes in that Elaborate Monument.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:mather&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:mather&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, because no organic pigment or other related artifacts have been found in the area, there’s no way of scientifically dating when the inscriptions were made.  But there don’t seem to be any doubts about its antiquity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/DightonRock/transcriptions.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A compilation of transcriptions from Envisioning Information by Edward Tufte, based on Annual report of the Bureau of Ethnology to the Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution 1880&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;A compilation of transcriptions from Envisioning Information by Edward Tufte, based on Annual report of the Bureau of Ethnology to the Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution 1880 &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;theories-of-origin&quot;&gt;Theories of origin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a few hundred years of speculation, the extensive petroglyphs on the rock have still raised controversy. The most widely held hypothesis attributes them to Native Americans.  However, it was attributed also to Norse Vikings, Portuguese, Phoenicians, Chinese, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1767, Ezra Stiles, then president of Yale University, declared in his &lt;em&gt;Election Sermon&lt;/em&gt; that the figures on the rock were of Phoenician origin.  Stiles writes that a copy of the inscription was sent to M. Gebelin of the Parisian academy of sciences, who, comparing them with the Punic paleography, judges them punic, and has interpreted them as denoting, that the ancient Carthaginians once visited these distant regions.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:stiles&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:stiles&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side-note:&lt;/em&gt; George Washington, while shown the Sewell’s transcription in Harvard College in 1789, allegedly scoffed at then-prevailing Phoenician theory. He remarked that he encountered many similar markings on his travels in Virginia.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:washington&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:washington&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The controversy was reignited when Danish writer Charles Christian Rafn published his &lt;em&gt;Antiquities Americanae&lt;/em&gt; in 1837, which contained more than 40 pages of analysis of the Dighton Rock. Rafn concluded the markings on the rock were Norse.  His translation says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thorfinn and his 151 companions took possession of this land.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:rafn&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:rafn&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1912, Edmund B. Delabarre announced his discovery of date “1511” and the name of “Miguel Corte-Real,” a Portuguese explorer who had left Portugal in 1502 and never returned.  Fifty years after, Manuel Da Silva made a study of the rock and came upon two other clues, the Portuguese royal coat-of-arms and the Portuguese Cross of the Order of Christ. He published his findings in his &lt;em&gt;Portuguese Pilgrims and Dighton Rock&lt;/em&gt; in 1971. Delabarre proposed that he had been heard from, in the inscription on the rock that read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;MIGUEL CORTEREAL – V. DEI HIC DUX IND – 1511 &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:delabarre&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:delabarre&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/DightonRock/cortereal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Detail of the replica displayed at the Museu da Marinha, Lisbon, Portugal, conveniently ignoring all previous inscriptions which don't support the argument.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Detail of the replica displayed at the Museu da Marinha, Lisbon, Portugal, conveniently ignoring all previous inscriptions which don't support the argument. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recent proponents of the Portuguese theory include Manuel Luciano da Silva and Geroge F. W. Young&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:young&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:young&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  Notable historian of Portuguese discoveries, Luís de Albuquerque, discarded the theory in his &lt;em&gt;Navegadores, Viajantes e Aventureiros Portugueses (1987)&lt;/em&gt;.  More recently, popular literature writer Douglas Hunter provides thorough analysis, debunking the Corte-Real origin hypothesis.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hunter&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hunter&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most recent theories came in 2002. Gavin Menzies, in his book &lt;em&gt;1421: The Year China Discovered America&lt;/em&gt;, proposed that the inscriptions we made by Chinese explorers who had arrived and claimed the Americas for themselves at that time.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:menzies&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:menzies&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, that the historians of Dighton Rock Museum hold that it’s made by native Americans.  The museum recently acquired a high-resolution 3D scan of the object, giving them access to the smallest details and angles.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:berkland&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:berkland&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hunter:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hunter&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best description of the Rorschach test-like effect the rock has on people was fittingly summarized by E. B. Delabarre himself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is easy to imagine as present on the rock almost any desired letter of the alphabet, especially of crude of early forms; and that, starting with almost any favored story, he can discover for it, if he looks for them eagerly enough, illustrative images to fit its various features, and initial letters or even entire words or names.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:delabarre2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:delabarre2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:inscriptions&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/annualreportofbu1018881889smit&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Annual report of the Bureau of Ethnology to the Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution&lt;/em&gt;, 1880&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:inscriptions&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:mather&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://quod.lib.umich.edu/e/evans/N00431.0001.001/1:3?rgn=div1;view=toc&quot;&gt;Mather, Cotton. &lt;em&gt;The wonderful works of God Commemorated&lt;/em&gt;, 1690&lt;/a&gt; (umich.edu) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:mather&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:stiles&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalcommons.unl.edu/etas/41/&quot;&gt;Stiles, Ezra. &lt;em&gt;Election Sermon&lt;/em&gt;, 1783&lt;/a&gt; (unl.edu) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:stiles&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:washington&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=th1TuDKZ4kc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dighton Rock Inscription in History&lt;/em&gt;, Harvard University&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Better source needed.&lt;/strong&gt; (youtube.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:washington&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:rafn&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rafn, Charles Christian. &lt;em&gt;Antiquities Americanae&lt;/em&gt;, 1837 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:rafn&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:delabarre&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/dightonrockstudy00dela/page/n11/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Delabarre, Edmund Burke. &lt;em&gt;Dighton rock; a study of the written rocks of New England&lt;/em&gt;, 1928&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:delabarre&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:young&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Young, George F. W. &lt;em&gt;Miguel Corte-Real and the Dighton Writing-Rock&lt;/em&gt;, 1970 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:young&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hunter&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dwhauthor.wordpress.com/2018/02/19/the-place-of-stone-introduction/&quot;&gt;Hunter, Douglas. &lt;em&gt;The Place of Stone&lt;/em&gt;, 2017&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Better source needed.&lt;/strong&gt; (dwhauthor.wordpress.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hunter&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hunter:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:menzies&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Menzies, Gavin. &lt;em&gt;1421: The Year China Discovered America&lt;/em&gt;, 2002 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:menzies&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:berkland&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2017/09/harvard-art-museums-tour-lands-at-dighton-rock/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Harvard Art Museums tour takes visitors to Dighton Rock&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (harvard.edu) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:berkland&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:delabarre2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/recenthistoryofd20delauoft/page/310/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Delabarre, Edmund Burke. &lt;em&gt;Recent History of Dighton Rock&lt;/em&gt;, 1919&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:delabarre2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Phoenicians in America</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/phoenicians-in-america"/>
   <updated>2021-03-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/phoenicians-in-america</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The theory of Phoenician discovery of America suggests that the earliest Old World contact with the Americas was not with Columbus or even Norse settlers, but with the Phoenicians (or, alternatively, other Semitic peoples).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no wonder that there are so many controversies surrounding these enigmatic people which we still know little about, ranging from the extent of their sea travels to their religion and alleged child sacrifices.  Ironically, although their alphabet became one of the most widely used writing systems in the West, very few Phoenician manuscripts have survived in the original or in translation due either to their destruction during Macedonian and Roman aggression or for having been written on easily perishable material like papyrus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People generally consider this particular theory to be fringe because quite a few artifacts speaking in its favor are now considered to be forgeries.  However, there are still people who vehemently support it and there’s much more evidence and controversy than one might think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;archaeological-evidence&quot;&gt;Archaeological evidence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-paraíba-inscription&quot;&gt;The Paraíba Inscription&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1872, the National Museum of Brazil received a letter signed by a man named Joaquim Alves da Costa, which contained a transcription of the inscriptions found on a stone at “&lt;em&gt;Pouso-Alto on the shores of the Parahyba&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The director of the museum Ladislau de Souza Mello Netto first accepted the inscription as genuine, but by 1873, philologist Ernest Renan convinced him that it was a forgery.  According to his translation, the inscription tells the story of “Sidonian Canaanites”, who set sail around Africa and wound up on the shores of Brazil during the nineteenth year of the reign of King Hiram, some 500 years BC.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:netto&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:netto&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/Phoenicians/paraiba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inscriptions sent along with the letter.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Inscriptions sent along with the letter. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We are children of Canaan from Sidon from the Eastern kingdom of merchants and are cast,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I pray now, where there is (?gold amids a/a far off?) land of mountains and offered a chosen one to the Most High gods&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;And Goddesses in year 19 of Hiram’s reign, I pray (still) strong&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;from the valley of Ezion-geber at the Red Sea there by journeyed with 10 ships&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;we were at sea together assuredly two years around the land of Ham separated&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;by the hand of Baal and no (longer) remained among our companions, now we have come here 12&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;men and three women at this land devoted I make, even whom men of wealth bow the knee,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;a pledge to the Most High Gods and Goddesses (with) sure hope.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netto also reports that all efforts of locating the original author of the inscription were in vain, which led him to believe that it was a hoax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side-note:&lt;/strong&gt; The skeptical website &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.badarchaeology.com/out-of-place-artefacts/petroglyphs-inscriptions-and-reliefs/the-paraiba-parahyba-stone/&quot;&gt;BadArcheology.com&lt;/a&gt; claims that there was a real person Joachim Alves da Costa Freitas, who lived close to Pouso Alto in Minas Gerais province during the 1870s.  Sadly, the link seemingly proving this leads to now-defunct Yahoo Groups and it doesn’t seem to be archived anywhere.  If you know how to verify such information in some official records, please &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;let us know!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hypothesis was brought up again in 1967 by Cyrus Herzel Gordon, an expert in Semitic languages and head of the Department of Mediterranean Studies at Brandeis University, well-known for his translations of the ancient Cretan “Linear A”.  He provided a slightly different translation and concluded that “it is obvious that the text is genuine since it didn’t copy any Semitic writing that would have been widely accessible at the time.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gordon&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gordon&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another contemporary expert on Semitic languages, Frank Moore Cross, disagreed, supporting Renan’s opinion that the letterforms cover a range of ten centuries and that they could be made with knowledge of that time (see e.g. Jordan Moabite Stone from 1870&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:boloji&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:boloji&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is Dr. Gordon’s translation (or rather, interpretation) of the text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are Sidonian Canaanites from the city of the Mercantile King. We were cast up on this distant shore, a land of mountains. We sacrificed a youth to the celestial gods and goddesses in the nineteenth year of our mighty King Hiram and embarked from Ezion-geber into the Red Sea. We voyaged with ten ships and were at sea together for two years around Ham [Africa]. Then we were separated by the hand of Baal and were no longer with our companions. So we have come here, twelve men and three women, into New Shore. Am I, the Admiral, a man who would flee? Nay! May the celestial gods and goddesses favour us well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s conclude with a wonderful summary from Austin Whittall’s Patagonian Monsters blog: “So, we have a letter with a transcription of inscriptions found on a stone, that was never actually seen by scientists, it was posted from an unknown place on an ambiguous river by a person who could not be found later. Its text was, according to some scholars badly written and therefore a hoax, but, according to others, genuine.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:whittall&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:whittall&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Make of that what you will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bat-creek-inscription&quot;&gt;Bat Creek inscription&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bat Creek stone is an inscribed stone collected as part of a Native American burial mound excavation in Loudon County, Tennessee, in 1889.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inscriptions were initially described as Cherokee, but aformentioned Dr. Gordon correctly identified them as Hebrew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in 2004, Robert C. Mainfort and Mary L. Kwas noticed the glaring similarities with an inscription that was circulating in a Freemason book, indicating that the stone it’s a religiously-motivated nineteenth-century forgery.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:kwas&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:kwas&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  The inscription in question, an 1860s artist’s impression of how the Biblical phrase QDSh LYHWH, or “Holy to Yahweh,” would have looked in Paleo-Hebrew letters, is reproduced below along with the Bat Creek stone:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Phoenicians/macoy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;macoy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Phoenicians/batcreek.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;batcreek&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;General History, Cyclopedia, and Dictionary of Freemasonry, 1870&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bat Creek Stone inscription, found in 1889&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;los-lunas-decalogue-stone&quot;&gt;Los Lunas Decalogue Stone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This inscribed stone is located on a 400-foot high mesa in Hidden Mountain, near Los Lunas, New Mexico.  It is written in Paleo-Hebrew using the north Canaanite script of the early first millennium BC and it appears to be a version of Ten Commandments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the stone’s discovery in the 1930s, several different translations were proposed.  But it was a translation of Robert Pfeiffer of Harvard’s Semitic Museum from 1949 that created the greatest interest among scholars and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many ascribe the first mention of the stone in print to the late Prof. Frank C. Hibben, an archaeologist from the University of Mexico, in 1933, though no record exists of his having published anything on the subject.  It was first reported by Prof. James D. Tabor of the Dept. of Religious Studies, University of North Carolina - Charlotte, who interviewed Hibben in 1996.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:tabor&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:tabor&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hibben reports that he first saw the text in 1933. At the time it was covered with lichen and patination and was hardly visible. He was taken to the site by a guide who had seen it as a boy, back in the 1880s.”  Hibben’s assessment of its age in the 1930s, based on the growth of mosses and lichens on it, was that the incised characters were at least a hundred years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stone is blanched (from being cleaned by Boy Scouts in the 1950s, Hibben told Tabor), making dating through the patina, the surface layer of the rock, impossible. The first line has been scratched out by a vandal in 2006, but the rest of the inscription is completely legible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Atlee Phillips, curator of Archeology at the Maxwell Museum of Anthropology and professor of anthropology at the University of New Mexico, finds it much more likely that the inscription is the work of con-artists instead of the evidence of an ancient civilization.  The smoking gun for Phillips is the usage of the “caret”, the upside-down V symbol placed under a piece of text where something has been missed out.  Though sometimes found in ancient Latin and Greek texts, it is not known in Hebrew until the Middle Ages.  To make matters worse, it is above a dot that seems to be a full stop (or period); full stops did not exist in ancient Hebrew. Moreover, there are Greek letters of a slightly later date mixed in with Hebrew forms. &lt;sup&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;citation needed&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, even before 1880, and certainly before 1933 when Hibben first described the stone, enough had been learned about Paleo-Hebrew to account for a contemporary forgery.  See e.g. &lt;em&gt;A Discourse Concerning Sanchoniathon’s Phoenician History&lt;/em&gt; by Henry Dodwell from 1691.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, let’s not discount the presence of Jewish refugees in the earliest waves of Spanish colonists and settlers in the 16th or 17th century in today’s New Mexico - one of the farthest outposts in the empire of New Spain. It was an excellent place to avoid the horrors of the Inquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;baal-stone&quot;&gt;Baal Stone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The triangular stone, first documented by archaeologist James P. Whittall II, was popularized in the book &lt;em&gt;America B.C.&lt;/em&gt; by Barry Fell.  According to Fell, the inscription is in the Iberian Punic script and says “To Baal of the Canaanites, this in Dedication”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fell&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fell&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was found on a site called America’s Stonehenge in Salem, New Hampshire, previously called Mystery Hill by its owner William Goodwin who believed it was built by Culdee monks from Ireland.  The place was later sold to Bob Stone whose son still owns the site and the stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side-note:&lt;/em&gt; One of the photos circulating the internet which apparently shows the artifact is definitely a replica.  Although the inscriptions are more or less equal to the ones depicted in Fell’s book, it’s clearly a different stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Phoenicians/baal1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;baal1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Phoenicians/baal2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;baal2&quot; /&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/i/Phoenicians/baal3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;baal3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another claim was presented (relatively) recently at the History Channel TV show &lt;em&gt;America Unearthed&lt;/em&gt; by Scott Wolter and a son of the current owner of the site.  They hint at the possibility of the Phoenician link with the site by showing that the summer solstice sunrise alignment of American’s Stonehenge can be extended all the way to the Stonehenge and continues straight into the city of Beirut, Lebanon.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:stonehenge&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:stonehenge&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from referring to Lebanon as “the ancient home of the ancient Phoenicians”, they don’t explain what’s the connection with England’s Stonehenge.  They also fail to mention that while the place we call Beirut today was most likely settled, it doesn’t seem to play any big role in historical records compared to cities like Byblos or Sidon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, the summer solstice sunrise alignment of America’s Stonehenge does point roughly in the direction of Stonehenge but remember that the exact course of this line is obviously very sensitive on the initial degree.  Lines that start more or less parallel can diverge by several kilometers by the time they reach England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Another side-note:&lt;/em&gt; Just a few days before finishing this article, a QAnon supporter allegedly vandalized the megalithic monument with the infamous WWG1WGA slogan and his Twitter handle.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:qanon&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:qanon&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plymouth State University archaeologist David Starbuck notes the 19th-century quarrying marks on many of the stones and said the site has been altered so many times over the decades—particularly by the owner and researcher William Goodwin starting in 1936—that there will never be a way to settle the argument over its genesis.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:starbuck&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:starbuck&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sherbrooke-stones&quot;&gt;Sherbrooke stones&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to a 1975 newspaper article, A Laval University Prof. Thomas Lee found three stones in Quebec province’s Eastern Townships which could indicate that North America was visited by North Africans 500 years before the birth of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof. Thomas Lee said the stones were discovered “sometime early in this century” but the Egyptian inscriptions were written in a Libyan script not deciphered until last year.  He said the earliest mention of the stones he has seen is in a letter dated Dec. 26, 1910, but he “got the impression the stones were not in the museum at that time.” A spokesman for the museum said it has had the stones since at least 1910.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:winnipeg&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:winnipeg&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said one stone is inscribed: “Expedition that crossed in the service of Lord Hiram to conquer territory.” The other of the pair discovered together bears the inscription: “Record by Hata, who attained this limit on the river, moored his ship and engraved this rock.”  The stone which was found alone reads: “Hanno, son of Tamu, reached this mountain landmark.”,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:winnipeg:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:winnipeg&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Probably alluding to the famous Hanno the Navigator himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;see-also-dighton-rock&quot;&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&quot;/artifacts/dighton-rock&quot;&gt;Dighton Rock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coins&quot;&gt;Coins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;roman-coins&quot;&gt;Roman coins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reports of Roman coins in America go back to the 16th century.  The earliest account is of Marineo Siculo, who reported in 1533 that a coin bearing the image of Augustus was found in the gold mines of Panama.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:siculo&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:siculo&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  In the 19th century, two more finds were reported to be found at two different but neighboring locations in Tennessee.  William C. Atwater was the first to discuss this material in 1818 but remained very skeptical.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:atwater&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:atwater&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  His contemporary Haywood, a proponent of the idea that Romans, Hebrews, etc. played a role in forming Native American culture, was not so skeptical; he published a list of objects suggestive of transoceanic contact, including 4 Roman coins all discovered around a town in Arkansas.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:haywood&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:haywood&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  The first mention of a Hebrew coin is from a letter sent to editors of &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt; in 1860.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:schoolcraft&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:schoolcraft&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1970s-phoenician-coins&quot;&gt;1970s Phoenician coins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 20th century, discoveries started to mount up rapidly.  Starting in 1913, when Macedonian tetradrachma was found while digging a house foundation in Montana.  The first mention of a coin suggesting direct Phoenician contact comes from the non-peer-reviewed (and now defunct) &lt;em&gt;Anthropological Journal of Canada&lt;/em&gt; in a paper by Joseph B. Mahan and Douglas C. Braithwaite in 1975.  They describe the discovery of a “Syracusan coin” by a boy in Phenix City, Alabama, who wanted to trade it for candy.  He said he found it near his home at the edge of the city.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:mahan&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:mahan&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coin was later sent to Preston E. Blackwell, from the University of Georgia, who sent it to the Fogg Museum in Boston for identification.  Museum officials identified the coin as a Syracuse coin dating from 490 BC.  According to the Blackwell, the coin was later stolen from his wallet when he was hospitalized.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:mahan:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:mahan&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next publication to discuss the coins was a 1977 cover story by Norman Totten titled &lt;em&gt;Carthaginian coins found in Arkansas and Alabama&lt;/em&gt;.  Totten had been sent a coin similar to the one described by Mahan and Braithwaite by professor Barry Fell.  Totten concluded that the coin was genuine and that based “on the obverse style alone, one might date this coin to about 350” BC.  Fell got the coin from an amateur archaeologist Gloria Farley from Eastern Oklahoma Historical Society, who in turn got it from a man who claimed he found it with a metal detector buried six inches deep in a field near Cauthron, Arkansas. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:totten&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:totten&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark A. McMenamin from Mount Holyoke College, a previous proponent of their authenticity, provided exhaustive recapitulation of all evidence “Fell’s” coins and concluded that all of these were most likely modern forgeries.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:mcmenamin&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:mcmenamin&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;finding-patterns&quot;&gt;Finding patterns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to date, some 40 out-of-place coins are documented in the scientific literature (most of them being Roman coins).  The striking increase in coin discoveries comes after WWII, most of them are reported in the 60s and 70s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting aspect is that the dates minted on coins are spread across much of Greek and Roman history ranging from 490 BC to 800 AD, which would imply prolonged contact for hundreds of years if we would accept all evidence as authentic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, Jeremiah F. Epstein from the University of Chicago, who provided an exhaustive assessment of all evidence available in the 1980s, concludes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The significance of the occasional discovery of a Roman, Greek or Hebrew coin in America is hard to asses, largely because such discoveries are comparatively rare and seldom adequately documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When one examines the dates of the coin discoveries, the distribution of the finds, and the times when the coins were minted, the most plausible interpretation is that the coins were lost recently. In fact, most of them appear to have been lost since WWIII.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The biggest stumbling block in the way of giving these coins pre-Columbian status is that none have been found in documented prehistoric contexts.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:epstein&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:epstein&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about those 15th to 19th-century finds?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The long period of time between the first report, in 1533, and the, in 1818, should arouse suspicion. If they were valid, one would imagine that ancient coins would have shown up in increasing numbers as America became settled.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:epstein:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:epstein&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That however didn’t happen until after the last world war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;historical-evidence&quot;&gt;Historical evidence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ptolemys-geography&quot;&gt;Ptolemy’s &lt;em&gt;Geography&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, Lucio Russo has speculated about a probable arrival of Phoenicians in the Americas in his philological analyses regarding Fortunate Isles, &lt;em&gt;a.k.a.&lt;/em&gt; Islands of the Blessed.  This mythical winterless paradise from Greek mythology would deserve their own analysis, but for the sake of Russo’s argument, we will only look at Ptolemy’s &lt;em&gt;Geography&lt;/em&gt;, which provides information about geographical longitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his book, Ptolemy gives the coordinates of the Fortunate Isles but at the same time, he shrinks the size of the world by one-third compared to the size measured by Eratosthenes.  He argues that the underestimate of size is caused by incorrect identification of Fortunate Isles with the Caribbean and by attributing those coordinates to the Antilles, the world gets back to the right size and also certain other puzzling deformations in Ptolemy’s world map disappear.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:russo&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:russo&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russo also argues that the Antilles coordinates must have been known to Ptolemy’s source, Hipparchus. Hipparchus lived in Rhodes and may have gotten this information from Phoenicians sailors since they had full control of the western Mediterranean in those times.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:russo2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:russo2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;diodoros-of-sicily&quot;&gt;Diodoros of Sicily&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diodoros’ &lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt; is remarkable for many reasons. This 40-volume book (of which only 15 books survive intact) is considered one of the earliest attempts at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_history&quot;&gt;Universal history&lt;/a&gt; and also it is notably more detached from ‘Hellenocentric’ world-view&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:usher&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:usher&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  It’s also a major source of our knowledge about Alexander the Great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, some passages are a bit controversial.  For fans of Alternative History, he’s mainly notable for his mentions of Atlanteans, but it also contains this peculiar passage story about Phoenicians:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But now that we have discussed what relates to the islands which lie within the Pillars of Hercules, we shall give an account of those which are in the ocean. For there lies out in the deep off Libya an island of considerable size, and situated as it is in the ocean it is distant from Libya a voyage of a number of days to the west.  Its land is fruitful, much of it being mountainous and not a little being a level plain of surpassing beauty. Through it flow navigable rivers which are used for irrigation, and the island contains many parks planted with trees of every variety and gardens in great multitudes which are traversed by streams of sweet water;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;on it also are private villas of costly construction, and throughout the gardens banqueting houses have been constructed in a setting of flowers, and in them the inhabitants pass their time during the summer season, since the land supplies in abundance everything which contributes to enjoyment and luxury.  […] the climate of this island is so altogether mild that it produces in abundance the fruits of the trees and the other seasonal fruits for the larger part of the year, so that it would appear that the island, because of its exceptional felicity, were a dwelling-place of a race of gods and not of men.(V-19)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:diodoros&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:diodoros&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In ancient times this island remained undiscovered because of its distance from the entire inhabited world j but it was discovered at a later period for the following reason.  The Phoenicians, who from ancient times on made voyages continually for purposes of trade, planted many colonies throughout Libya and not a few as well in the western parts of Europe.  And since their ventures turned out according to their expectations, they amassed great wealth and essayed to voyage beyond the Pillars of Heracles into the sea which men call the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] The Phoenicians, then, while exploring the coast outside the Pillars for the reasons we have stated and while sailing along the shore of Libya, were driven by strong winds a great distance out into the ocean. And after being storm-tossed for many days they were carried ashore on the island we mentioned above, and when they had observed its felicity and nature they caused it to be known to all men.(V-20)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:diodoros:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:diodoros&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, we are told that Tyrrhenians wanted to make a colony there, but Carthaginians prevented it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] partly out of concern lest many inhabitants of Carthage should remove there because of the excellence of the island, and partly in order to have ready in it a place in which to seek refuge against an incalculable turn of fortune, in case some total disaster should overtake Carthage.  For it was their thought that, since they were masters of the sea, they would thus be able to move, households and all, to an island which was unknown to their conquerors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could this be another reference to Fortunate Islands?  And would that mean Canary Islands, Azores, or Americas?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:netto&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bdor.sibi.ufrj.br/handle/doc/20&quot;&gt;Netto, Ladislau. &lt;em&gt;Lettre a Monsieur Ernest Renan a propos de l’inscrioption Phenicienne apocryphe soumise en 1872 a l’Institut historique, geographique et ethnograpicque du Bresil&lt;/em&gt;, 1885&lt;/a&gt; (ufrj.br) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:netto&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gordon&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/43078826&quot;&gt;Gordon, Cyrus H. &lt;em&gt;The Canaanite Text from Brazil&lt;/em&gt;, 1968&lt;/a&gt; (jstor.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gordon&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:boloji&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.boloji.com/articles/14383/phoenicians-in-the-americas&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phoenicians in the Americas - Is the Paraiba Stone of Brazil Genuine?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (boloji.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:boloji&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:whittall&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patagoniamonsters.blogspot.com/2011/03/phoenician-inscriptions-from-paraiba.html&quot;&gt;Whittall, Austin. &lt;em&gt;The “Phoenician” inscriptions from Paraiba, Brazil&lt;/em&gt;, 2011&lt;/a&gt; (blogspot.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:whittall&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:kwas&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Kwas, Mary L., Mainfort, Robert C. &lt;em&gt;The Bat Creek Stone Revisited&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;American Antiquity&lt;/em&gt;, v. 69, n. 4, 2004. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:kwas&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:tabor&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/19981202230505/http://www.unitedisrael.org/loslunas.html&quot;&gt;Tabor, James D. &lt;em&gt;An Ancient Hebrew Inscription in New Mexico&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:tabor&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fell&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/americabcancient00fell&quot;&gt;Fell, Barry. &lt;em&gt;America B.C.&lt;/em&gt;, 1978&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fell&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:stonehenge&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;America Unearthed&lt;/em&gt; TV Show, Season 01, Episode 06 - Stonehenge in America, 2012 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:stonehenge&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:qanon&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2021/mar/04/americas-stonehenge-qanon-carving-mark-russo&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Man arrested for allegedly carving QAnon slogan at ‘America’s Stonehenge’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (theguardian.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:qanon&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:starbuck&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Starbuck, David R. &lt;em&gt;The Archaeology of New Hampshire: Exploring 10,000 Years in the Granite State&lt;/em&gt;, 2006 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:starbuck&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:winnipeg&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20191217073811/http://uhem-mesut.com/medu/en0052.php&quot;&gt;Lee, Thomas. &lt;em&gt;Africans Visited North America 2,500 Years Ago - Archeologist&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Winnipeg Free Press&lt;/em&gt;, 1976&lt;/a&gt; (uhem-mesut.com, archived) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:winnipeg&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:winnipeg:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:siculo&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://liburutegibiltegi.bizkaia.eus/handle/20.500.11938/69370&quot;&gt;Siculo, Marineo. &lt;em&gt;De las cosas memorables de España&lt;/em&gt;, 1530&lt;/a&gt; (bizkaia.eus) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:siculo&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:atwater&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.loc.gov/resource/lhbtn.12883/?sp=19&quot;&gt;Atwater, Caleb. &lt;em&gt;Archæologia americana: transactions and collections of the American Antiquarian Society&lt;/em&gt;, p. 19, 1820&lt;/a&gt; (loc.gov) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:atwater&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:haywood&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/naturalaborigina00hayw/page/174/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Haywood, John. &lt;em&gt;The Natural and Aboriginal History of Tennessee&lt;/em&gt;, p. 174, 1823&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:haywood&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:schoolcraft&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/1860/08/06/archives/the-hebrew-stone-in-ohio-letter-from-mr-henry-r-schoolcraft.html&quot;&gt;Schoolcraft, Henry R. &lt;em&gt;The “Hebrew stone” in Ohio.; Letter from Mr. Henry R. Schoolcraft, sent to *The New York Times&lt;/em&gt; in 1860&lt;/a&gt; (nytimes.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:schoolcraft&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:mahan&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Mahan, J., Braithwaite, D. &lt;em&gt;Discovery of Ancient Coins in the United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Anthropological Journal of Canada&lt;/em&gt;, v. 12, n. 2, p. 15-18, 1975 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:mahan&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:mahan:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:totten&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Totten, Norman. &lt;em&gt;Carthaginian Coins found in Arkansas and Alabama&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;ESOP IV&lt;/em&gt;, v. 88, 1977 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:totten&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:mcmenamin&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;McMenamin, Mark A. &lt;em&gt;Phoenicians, Fakes and Barry Fell: Solving the Mystery of Carthaginian Coins Found in America&lt;/em&gt;, 2000 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:mcmenamin&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:epstein&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/202398&quot;&gt;Epstein, Jeremiah F. &lt;em&gt;Pre-Columbian Old World Coins in America: An Examination of the Evidence&lt;/em&gt;, 1980&lt;/a&gt; (uchicago.edu) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:epstein&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:epstein:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:russo&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://msp.org/memocs/2018/6-3/p02.xhtml&quot;&gt;Russo, Lucio. &lt;em&gt;Far-reaching Hellenistic geographical knowledge hidden in Ptolemy’s data&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mathematics and Mechanics of Complex System&lt;/em&gt;, v. 6, n. 3, 2018&lt;/a&gt; (msp.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:russo&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:russo2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Russo, Lucio. &lt;em&gt;L’ America dimenticata. I rapporti tra le civiltà e un errore di Tolomeo&lt;/em&gt;, 2013 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:russo2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:usher&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/historiansofgree00ushe/page/234/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Usher, Stephen. &lt;em&gt;The Historians of Greece and Rome&lt;/em&gt;, 1970&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:usher&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:diodoros&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/DiodorosOfSicily034.598/Diodoros%20of%20Sicily%2003%20%284.59-8%29/page/n147/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Diodoros of Sicily. &lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt;, 1st-century BC, English translation, 1933&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:diodoros&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:diodoros:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Pîrî Reis Map of 1513</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/piri-reis-map-of-1513"/>
   <updated>2021-02-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/piri-reis-map-of-1513</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The map drawn by an admiral of Ottoman Empire Muhyi-iddin Pîrî re‘is dated to 1513 CE is well known in the fringe literature, mainly for its alleged depiction of the Antarctica coastline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was featured on the &lt;em&gt;Ancient Aliens&lt;/em&gt; and it’s often brought up by Graham Hancock&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hancock&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hancock&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, among others, as proof of ancient civilization or technology we’re not yet aware of, as the first modern mapping of Antarctica wasn’t done until the 19th century.  The argument is that Pîrî himself must have drawn from older, more ancient maps, which ties it into the general notion of ancient civilization theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an undeniable fact, that the precision of this map is astounding for its time.  Made only 20 years after the Discovery, it is the most precise depiction of the Brazilian coastline from this period.  Try to compare with other contemporary maps like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waldseem%C3%BCller_map&quot;&gt;Waldseemüller map&lt;/a&gt; from 1507 or even three decades older &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thedigitalgallery.org/images/255&quot;&gt;Sebastian Müster map&lt;/a&gt;.  However, there are numerous misconceptions about this map that need to be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/overlay.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Overlay on a modern map&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Overlay on a modern map &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite Pîrî being a well-known and studied figure in Turkish history, the discovery of the map came surprisingly late.  It was discovered by the Director of National Museums, Halil Etem Edhem only in 1929 when the Topkapı Palace in Istanbul was repurposed into a museum.  It’s believed to be just a fraction of a bigger map, although no other parts had been found.  Apart from numerous illustrations of ships, animals, and even mythical creatures, and more than a hundred of place-names (mostly corresponding with other contemporary portolan maps), it also features many inscriptions written mainly in Ottoman Turkish.  There are about thirty of them and English translations are available online.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:translation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:translation&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By far the largest inscription, placed over South America inland, says the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These coasts are named the shores of Antilia. They were discovered in the year 896 of the Arab calendar [1491 CE]. But it is reported thus, that a Genoese infidel, his name was Columbus, discovered these places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lower part of the same text elaborates more on the source material:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No one now living has seen a map like this. I have composed and constructed it using about twenty maps and mappaemundi; these are the maps which were composed in the time of Alexander of the Two Horns, and which show the inhabited portion of the earth. The Arabs call these maps ja’fariya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have used eight ja’fariya maps, an Arab map of India and four recent Portuguese maps - these maps show the sea of Sind, India and China according to mathematical principles - and also a map of the western regions drawn by Columbus. The final farm was arrived at by reducing all these maps to the same scale. Therefore the present map is as accurate for the Seven Seas as the maps of our own countries used by sailors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the previously mentioned video of Graham Hancock “explaining” the map doesn’t mention Columbus at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;antarctica&quot;&gt;Antarctica&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to the lowest part of the map, often doubtlessly identified with Antarctica coastline, there are two inscriptions which say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And in this country it seems that there are white-haired monsters in this shape, and also six-horned oxen. The Portuguese infidels have written it in their maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This country is a waste. Everything is in ruin and it is said that large snakes are found here. For this reason the Portuguese infidels did not land on these shores and these are also said to be very hot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will leave it to the reader to decide how likely it is that these lands refer to Antarctica. In any case, Pîrî clearly credits these parts of the map to Portuguese, not to some lost ancient maps as it’s often claimed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that the map actually depicts the Antarctica coastline seems to originate with captain Arlington Humphrey Mallery in c. 1956.  Apart from being a captain, he was an amateur archaeologist who believed that North America had been extensively colonized by Celts, Vikings, and other Old World peoples, who possessed accurate maps lost to later ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mallery’s accounts apparently inspired Charles Hapgood, famous mainly for his now-discredited Polar shift theory, who argued that Pîrî’s map and others are proof of a lost ancient civilization.  Hapgood’s book show his correspondence with USAF Lt. Colonel Harold Z. Ohlmeyer, who agreed with Hapgood that &lt;em&gt;“this is the most logical and in all probability the correct interpretation of the map”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“lower part of the map agrees very remarkably with the results of the seismic profile made across the top of the ice-cap by the Swedish-British Antarctic Expedition of 1949”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“we have no idea how the data on this map can be reconciled with the supposed state of geographical knowledge in 1513.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hapgood&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hapgood&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/hapgood.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hapgood's interpretation&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Hapgood's interpretation &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are several problems with Hapgood’s hypotheses.  The map does not show Drake’s Passage or the Pacific Ocean. Also, what Hapgood identifies as the Andes mountains are not located along a coastline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theory was later revived by Erich von Däniken in his &lt;em&gt;Chariots of the Gods?&lt;/em&gt;, where he basically just reiterated Hapgood’s claims within his own context of Ancient Aliens hypothesis.  He says that &lt;em&gt;“the only explanation is that it must have been made by extraterrestrials, either at an early date when Antarctica was indeed free from ice or because their technology revealed the underlying surface.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:daniken&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:daniken&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another proponent of this view is above mentioned Graham Hancock, who also adds that one of the islands depicts the “Bimini Road”, which Hapgood identified as Cuba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/bimini_road.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An island which according to Hancock depicts Bimini Road&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;An island which according to Hancock depicts Bimini Road &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, serious scholarship holds that there is no reason to believe that the map is the product of genuine knowledge of the Antarctic coast.  The general belief is that it actually depicts the South American coastline, just heavily distorted.  This distortion could be caused by an error, motivated by the weird shape of the parchment, or even for political reasons.  This well-constructed argument is proposed by Diego Cuoghi on his website, where he doesn’t rely only on the correlation of geography, but also on historical arguments and comparison with other historical maps.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cuoghi&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cuoghi&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/piri_brazil.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Correlation with SA coastline according to Diago Cuoghi&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Correlation with SA coastline according to Diago Cuoghi &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speculation alert:&lt;/strong&gt; Could this identification with Tierra del Fuego explain the “shores that are said to be very hot”?  Yes, Magellan officially coined the name in 1525, but maybe some relation with fire was already present before?  He apparently knew about the strait before he set out, as “he saw it, in the Treasury of the King of Portugal, on a map drawn by Martin de Bohemia” (Pigafetta).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we should not toss out the possibility that although the map does state the year of its creation, some portions could be drawn later.  As Cuoghi notes, we know that the chart of Pedro Reinel, kept in the same Library of Topkapı, was probably retouched after the discovery of the Strait of Magellan, so it wouldn’t be unprecedented.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cuoghi:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cuoghi&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cryptozoology&quot;&gt;Cryptozoology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting subject that is often overlooked is the illustrations of animals and fantastical creatures.  Apart from the above-mentioned large snakes, white-haired monsters mentioned in the inscriptions, the map also features a unicorn, a monkey dancing with what looks to be a dog-headed man, and a headless creature reminiscent of &lt;em&gt;blemmyes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/dancing_beasts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/blemmye.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;“In the mountains of this territory were creatures like this and human beings came out on the seacoast. The gold mines are endless.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;“These monsters are seven spans long. The space between their eyes is one span, but they are harmless souls.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These fantastic creatures had been occasionally depicted in medieval &lt;em&gt;mappae mundi&lt;/em&gt; and many of them were associated with either Africa or Asia.  De La Cosa’s map (1500) also shows &lt;em&gt;blemmye&lt;/em&gt; and a dog-headed man in the Far East, in the approximate location of China, probably in a reference to the reports of Marco Polo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Pîrî Reis, they are also found on the chart of Guillaume Le Testu (1555) and associated with the New World on the map of Sebastian Cabot (1544) and that of Guiana by de Bry (1599).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:masseti&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:masseti&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hancock&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qt2GYyGTXTs&quot;&gt;Graham Hancock’s summary of the argument on &lt;em&gt;The Mysterious Origins of Man&lt;/em&gt; TV program.&lt;/a&gt; (youtube.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hancock&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:translation&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://turkeyinmaps.com/piri.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Piri Reis Map of 1513 (translations)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (turkeyinmaps.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:translation&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hapgood&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hapgood, Charles H. &lt;em&gt;Maps of the Ancient Sea Kings&lt;/em&gt;, 1966 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hapgood&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:daniken&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;von Däniken, Erich. &lt;em&gt;Chariots of the Gods?&lt;/em&gt;, 1968 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:daniken&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cuoghi&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diegocuoghi.com/Piri_Reis/PiriReis_eng.htm&quot;&gt;Cuoghi, Diego. &lt;em&gt;The Mysteries of the Piri Reis Map&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (diegocuoghi.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cuoghi&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cuoghi:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:masseti&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sciencepress.mnhn.fr/en/periodiques/anthropozoologica/51/1/les-representations-zoomorphiques-de-la-carte-de-piri-reis-1513&quot;&gt;Masseti, Marco &amp;amp; Veracini, Cecilia. &lt;em&gt;The zoomorphic representations of the Pîrî Reis map (1513)&lt;/em&gt;, 2016&lt;/a&gt; (mnhn.fr) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:masseti&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Atlantis - myths about the myth</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/atlantis"/>
   <updated>2021-01-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/atlantis</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The myth of Atlantis probably doesn’t require much introduction.  The mythical lost civilization and its island have generated speculations in countless books since Plato first mentioned it in the 5th century BC, even capturing the attention of famous thinkers like Isaac Newton or Francis Bacon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It branched into many different beliefs about its true location, linking Atlantis with Crete, Sardinia, America, Antarctica, Iberian Peninsula, Mauritania, and many, many other places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several years of relative dormancy in the imagination of the broader public, it has begun to make something of a comeback in recent years, partly driven by recent discoveries about the Younger Dryas period and ancient settlements like Göbekli Tepe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the most skeptical-minded articles focus on debunking the idea itself or some specific claims, we’re just trying to trace the most repeated claims to their source and show how the perception of the myth evolved through time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of building an argument, the goal is to gather &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; sources, make as few active claims as possible, and let the reader form his own opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;origin---platos-timaeus-and-critias&quot;&gt;Origin - Plato’s &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Critias&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a speaker in Plato’s &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, a character called Critias states that he heard the Atlantis tale from his grandfather Critias the elder, who heard it from Solon.  Solon, a famous Greek statesman who lived two centuries before, allegedly acquired the story in Egypt and “brought it back with him” to Athens, with intentions to adapt it into an epic poem later, which he left unfinished. (&lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, p. 17)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:timaeus&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:timaeus&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;CRITIAS: [It’s a story that] Solon, the wisest of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seven_Sages_of_Greece&quot;&gt;wise seven&lt;/a&gt;, once declared. Solon, who, you must know, was, as he says in several places in his poems, a kinsman and a close friend of my great-grandfather Dropides, told my grandfather Critias (so the Critias in his turn, used to repeat the story to me in his old age), that there are great and splendid ancient exploits of our city which have been forgotten from lapse of time and decay of population, and, in particular, one, the greatest of all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right away, we have a problem.  There are several contradicting interpretations of the genealogy described by Plato.  However, it’s certain that at the time the dialogue was written, Solon must have been dead for at least 150 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Atlantis/proclus.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Atlantis/burnet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interpretation of Proclus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gen_proclus&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gen_proclus&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interpretation of classicist John Burnet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gen_burnet&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gen_burnet&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regard to Atlantis, here are some main takeaways from &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt; (p. 17 - 23):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Athens was inhabited 9,000 ago by Athenians, it was a country “foremost both in war and all besides” before its destruction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Atlantis was an island with its own kings ruling over many other islands as well as mainland colonies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Located “before Pillars of Heracles” in Atlantic ocean, “larger than Libya and Asia together”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Atlanteans were wealthy and powerful and set to subjugate all other nations. Athenians revolted and “vanquished the invaders”, even freeing some of their colonies in the process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But later, great earth-quakes, and floods sunk the Atlantis (and drown all Athenian warriors as well).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Plato’s later work, &lt;em&gt;Critias&lt;/em&gt;, things get a bit more interesting (pages 116 - end):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Island of Atlantis was Poseidon’s “lot”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He carved the mountain into a palace and enclosed it with three circular moats.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Poseidon’s temple was in the inner ring and “forbidden to enter”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Poseidon took a liking to an orphaned girl.  She gave him ten sons, who later ruled 10 parts of Atlantis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rich fauna and flora, including plentiful elephants and many fruits and flowers (including ones exuding “gums”), which Atlanteans utilized for their sustenance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gold-red metal called Orichalcum was mined in many parts of Atlantis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apart from the capital city, “mountains contained numerous villages with a wealthy population”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the First king of Atlantis, Atlas, had a twin brother who ruled the region now known as Gadeira (Cádiz). (Note: Later, Strabo and Diodoros attribute foundation of this city to Phoenicians, which even archaeology nowadays seem to confirm)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering that Plato invented Atlantis for the sake of a political allegory, it can seem quite intriguing that so much detail is provided regarding things like geography, natural resources, agricultural practices, etc. before turning focus to society itself.  On the other hand, we can’t simply ignore that the same amount of detail is provided also for Athens in the same period, which the archeology evidence simply doesn’t support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that’s pretty much it.  As you can see, there are absolutely no implications of advanced technology or superior esoteric knowledge.  From all descriptions (apart from the dating and mythology, of course), they’re portrayed as pretty believable, though remarkably wealthy and powerful, Bronze Age civilization.  They armed themselves with spears and shields, they conquered barbaric lands and they waged war against Athenians, which they eventually lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bonus-solon-in-egypt&quot;&gt;BONUS: Solon in Egypt?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting all claims about Atlantis aside, even the claim that Solon actually traveled to Egypt in the first place was contested.  The first mention of this, apart from Plato’s story, of course, comes from Herodotus’ &lt;em&gt;The Histories&lt;/em&gt; (c. 440 BC), some 200 years after Solon’s passing and &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; Platon’s &lt;em&gt;Timeas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Critias&lt;/em&gt; was already well known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there are many inconsistencies in Herodotus’ accounts of Solon’s travel, and another story about his travel to Lydia is widely believed to be unhistorical.  However, the idea that Solon could visit Egypt roughly in the specified time doesn’t seem so unbelievable to be too controversial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interpretations-throughout-the-history&quot;&gt;Interpretations throughout the history&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, shouldn’t the story end here?  For many it does.  However, the debate about Atlantis is almost as old as the myth itself.  So how was the story perceived in ancient times?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;strabo-and-aristotle&quot;&gt;Strabo (and Aristotle?)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantis&quot;&gt;wikipedia page on Atlantis&lt;/a&gt; claims, that even Aristotle believed that Plato, his teacher, had invented the island to teach philosophy.  As a source, a 1967 article from &lt;em&gt;Galaxy Science Fiction&lt;/em&gt; magazine, is provided. Itself completely unsourced. (Note: Without taking any sides, it’s always important to be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; careful with accepting claims you read on Wikipedia and where they come from.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what’s the real story?  As always, it’s complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument comes from Strabo’s &lt;em&gt;Geography&lt;/em&gt;.  Strabo (c.60 BC- C.20 BC) endorses Poseidonius’ (c. 135 BC-c.50 BC) view that Atlantis might be more than mere fiction and dismisses the argument that “Its inventor caused it to disappear, just as did the Poet the wall of the Acheans.” (Implying &lt;strong&gt;Solon&lt;/strong&gt; avoided the historical consequences of his fiction by sinking Atlantis, just as Homer did by making Poseidon and Apollo sweep away with a flood the wall built by the Achaeans. (Strabo 2.3.6&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:strabo&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:strabo&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does Aristotle come in?  Well, in chapter 13.1.36 in a passage completely unrelated to Atlantis, this quote is referenced again, this time attributed to Aristotle.  This led some to conclude that the first appearance of a quote does indeed reflect Aristotle’s opinion on Atlantis.  This is disputed in the generally well-received book &lt;em&gt;Aristotle and Atlantis&lt;/em&gt; by T. C. Franke&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:franke&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:franke&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;commentary-on-platos-timaeus-by-proclus&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Commentary on Plato’s Timaeus&lt;/em&gt; by Proclus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosopher Crantor (c. 3rd century BC), a student of Plato’s student Xenocrates, is often cited as an example of a writer who thought of the story as a historical fact.  His work, a commentary on &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, is however lost and all our information come from commentary on his work from the 5th century by Neoplatonist Proclus (more than 600 years after the life of Crantor) In regard to Atlantis story, he reports&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:proclus&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:proclus&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With respect for the whole of this narration about the Atlantics, some say, that it is a mere history, which was the opinion of Crantor, the first interpreter of Plato, who says, that Plato was derided by those of his time, as not being the inventor of the Republic, but transcribing what the Egyptians had written on this subject; and that he so far regards what is said by these deriders as to refer to the Egyptians this history about the Athenians and Atlantics, and to believe that the Athenians once lived conformably to this polity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[He] adds, that this is testified by the prophets of the Egyptians, who assert that these particulars [which are narrated by Plato] are written on pillars which are still preserved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re putting ‘He’ in brackets because some translations say it was Crantor, who confirms the story (see 1820 English translation in Sources) but the Greek original uses ambiguous ‘He’, which leaves room for speculations that it was Plato himself who verified the story with Egyptians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever you lean towards, all we can safely state is that according to 5th CE century Greek Neoplatonist philosopher, Plato, facing ridicule, made attempts to verify the story with Egyptians, and either Plato or Crantor confirmed its veracity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, we hope that it’s evident that based on this text is absolutely no justification for conclusions such as Otto Muck’s “Crantor came to Sais and saw there in the temple of Neith the column, completely covered with hieroglyphs, on which the history of Atlantis was recorded. Scholars translated it for him, and he testified that their account fully agreed with Plato’s account of Atlantis”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:muck&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:muck&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;library-of-history-by-diodoros-of-sicily&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt; by Diodoros of Sicily&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diodoros’ &lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt; is remarkable for many reasons. This 40-volume book (of which only 15 books survive intact) is considered one of the earliest attempts at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_history&quot;&gt;Universal history&lt;/a&gt; and also it is notably more detached from ‘Hellenocentric’ world-view&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:usher&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:usher&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  It’s also a major source of our knowledge about Alexander the Great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we need to keep in mind that Diodoros still relied on Greek tradition and historians and he was almost certainly familiar with Plato’s work.  What’s interesting though, is that he doesn’t seem to even acknowledge Plato’s story and even disagrees on many details (notably mythical genealogy of Atlas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Diodoros, many generations before the Trojan War, the Atlanteans, the most civilized people of their time, became subject to the Libyan Amazons (author emphasizes that this a different tribe, not the more famous one, living along river Thermodon).  He places these Amazons’ land on an island in Lake Tritonis.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:diodoros&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:diodoros&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This island mentioned was of great size and full of fruit-bearing trees of every kind, from which the natives secured their food.  It also contained multitude of flocks, goats, sheeps, […]. But grain the nation used not at all because the use of this fruit of the earth had not yet been discovered among them.  The Amazons, then, the account continues, being a race superior in valour and eager for war, first of all subdued all the cities on the island except one called Menê, which was considered to be sacred[…] (III. 53. 3-6)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their city was called Cherronesus [Penninsula] after its shape.  Now, enter Atlantians:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…]the most civilized men among the inhabitants of those regions, who dwelt in a prosperous country and possessed great cities; it was among them, we are told, that mythology places the birth of the gods. (III. 54)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their first king had been Uranus, a god who had elevated them from the bestial state and had taught them agriculture (Book III, 56, 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, the Amazons attacked and conquered a major Atlantian city called Cernê and Atlantians became subjected and that’s the last time their history was mentioned.  This is what Diodoros said of Atlantians.  Not a word about its conquest of neighboring nations or about the time and circumstances of the cataclysm that should have destroyed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, where does &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; version of the story come from?  Diodoros is very clear about that.  Before beginning the story of Amazons and Atlantians, he credits “Dionysius, who composed a narrative about Argonauts and Dionysus, and also about many other things which took place in the most ancient times.” (III. 52)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side-note:&lt;/strong&gt; Dionysus’ version of Argonauts is also quite different from the ‘classic’ version you probably know)  This Dionysius Scytobrachion, often identified with Dionysus of Miletus, is believed to live in the 2nd century BC in Alexandria, Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;see-also-phoenicians-in-america&quot;&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/phoenicians-in-america&quot;&gt;Phoenicians in America&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-world&quot;&gt;New World&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some later Christian scholars who seem to interpret Atlantis as real were Eusebius, Philo, and Kosmas Indikopleustés (who by the way scorned the view of spherical Earth calling it “pagan lies”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big resurrection of the idea came with the Age of Discovery.  The Spanish historian Francisco López de Gómara (c. 1511-c. 1566) seems to be the first to believe that Plato’s Atlantis was referring to America.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gomara&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gomara&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exception to this sentiment provides Jesuit Father Athanasius Kircher (1601-1680), who pictures Atlantis as a separate landmass between Europe and America in an illustration to his book &lt;em&gt;Mundus Subterraneus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:kircher&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:kircher&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/Atlantis/Kircher.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Map of Atlantis from Mundus Subterraneus&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Map of Atlantis from Mundus Subterraneus &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Francis Bacon (1561-1626)  his unfinished utopian novel &lt;em&gt;The New Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:bacon&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:bacon&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  He talks about an island called Bensalem, whose people, ancestors to bigger island New Atlantis located even further west, were of a high moral character, modesty, Christian faith, and scientific inquiry.  Some then-futuristic technologies like flying machines, submarines, weather control, etc. are described.  However, this book is clearly a Christian utopian novel and nothing suggests it was ever intended to be taken literally, however it might play some role in cementing the idea of Atlantis as a utopian, advanced society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another growing theory was Mayanism, which connected Atlantis with Mayan and other indigenous American cultures.  Early proponents of this belief were Charles Étienne Brasseur de Bourbourg (1814-1874) and Augustus Le Plongeon (1825-1908) who seems to be the first to theorize that Atlantis was ancestral to ancient Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-age&quot;&gt;New Age&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the 19th century, the theory shifted into more fringe territory and it was molded to fit various Christian, New Age, and even Nazi beliefs.  Also, only now do most of the supernatural claims start to appear.  Major figures were Ignatius L. Donnelly, Helena Blavatsky, and Edgar Cayce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignatius L. Donnelly (1831-1901) is probably the reason why this myth became so widely known.  He was probably inspired by Mayanism, but he saw Atlantis as an actually lost continent in the Atlantic sea, which disappeared in a flood.  He also originated quite a few original claims, which are still perpetuated today.  To name a few, Atlantis was the region where man first rose from barbarians [sic] to civilization.  From there the civilization was distributed to all ancient civilizations around the world.  Gods of Greeks, Phoenicians, Hindus, etc. were simply kings, queens, and heroes of Atlantis.  From all colonies, the religions of Egypt and Peru were the closest representations of the original religion of Atlanteans.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:donnelly&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:donnelly&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This video summarizes all 13 hypotheses that Donnelly is trying to prove: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aP9xOcZ9AN4&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Book Review: Atlantis: The Antediluvian World, by Ignatius L. Donnelly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (youtube.com)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helena Blavatsky (1831-1891), a Russian mystic and founder of the Theosophical Society.  Despite claiming that she was given access to “secret wisdom” in Tibet, she repeated many claims of Donelly, mainly concerning and further elaborating on the idea of “progenitor race” (first very briefly proposed in &lt;em&gt;Isis Unveiled&lt;/em&gt;).  In her next book, &lt;em&gt;The Secret Doctrine&lt;/em&gt;, she tells much more about Atlantis.  Tibetan masters revealed to her that Atlantians were only a fourth of seven “root races”, following i.a. Hyperboreans and Lemurians.  The fifth “root race” is the “Aryan race” and the sixth and seventh have yet to be.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:blavatsky&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:blavatsky&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  By the way, this unscientific race theory could be one of the contributing factors to forming of Nazi ideology.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:nazis&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:nazis&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  But, of course, Blavatsky was in no way responsible for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Blavatsky attributed her knowledge to “sacred wisdom” bestowed upon her by Ascended Masters, Edgar Cayce (1877-1945) wasn’t even trying to hide the fact that the knowledge of Atlantis came to him through his psychic abilities.  But it can be demonstrated that he must have been familiar with the works of Donnelly, Blavatsky, and probably other theosophists.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cayce&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cayce&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  In regard to Atlantis, he originates a plethora of claims. Atlanteans migrated to Egypt after the disaster and that their &lt;em&gt;History of Records&lt;/em&gt; is still hidden under the Sphinx (likely inspired by Paul Chrisitan’s &lt;em&gt;Histoire De La Magie&lt;/em&gt;) and also “in another [place] in the Aryan or Yucatan land”.  He also made many claims concerning crystal technology, the capability of flying and moving through the water, telepathy, etc.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cayce2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cayce2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (probably inspired by Bacon)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;modern-times&quot;&gt;Modern times&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 20th century, the Continental drift hypothesis started to gain acceptance, which offered new possible explanations for Atlantis believers.  More recently, the myth was once again revived by new discoveries about catastrophic events during the Younger Dryas period.  This is still fresh stuff, so it naturally captures the minds of ancient history enthusiasts who often see it as a solution to all the flood myths of ancient cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of the proponents of this “scientific stream” don’t seem to acknowledge the supposed esoteric and advanced technology proposed by New Age authors, some ideas persist.  Mainly connection to native Americans, Egyptians, and other early civilizations - basically the idea of progenitor race, but stripped of all the Aryan connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there’s very little doubt, that catastrophic events like Megafloods and meteor strikes did happen in a relatively short period and might greatly influence the human population of that time, that itself doesn’t imply that some great civilization was destroyed by it.  Moreover, archaeological evidence of any bronze culture in the neolithic is still lacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most prominent scientific hypotheses, which don’t directly relate to Atlantis but somehow tie into the “progenitor civilization” theory, are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Younger_Dryas_impact_hypothesis&quot;&gt;YD impact hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;  and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sphinx_water_erosion_hypothesis&quot;&gt;Sphinx water erosion hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;.  Graham Hancock also mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orion_correlation_theory&quot;&gt;Orion correlation theory&lt;/a&gt; in the BBC documentary &lt;em&gt;Atlantis Reborn Again&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest “candidate”, propagated mainly by the youtube channel Bright Insight, is the Richat Structure in Mauretania.  Claims of this video are thoroughly analyzed by an actual historian in two videos from another youtube channel, World of Antiquity.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:woa1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:woa1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:woa2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:woa2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be also noted, that some academics propose that the destruction of Atlantis was inspired by the explosion of a volcano on Santorini (c. 1600 BC).  Louis Guillaume Figuier (1819-1984) was the first to suggest a link between the Theran explosion and Plato’s Atlantis.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:figuier&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:figuier&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Supporters of this theory note that Minoans were a significant naval power and they could be seen as ancestors of Greeks by Egyptians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many other locations were proposed: Bermuda Triangle (Charles Berlitz), Doñana National Park (Bruce Blackburn), Great Meteor Seamount, Azores, Black Sea, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to these efforts, writer L. Sprague de Camp fittingly noted in his book “Lost Continents,” “You cannot change all the details of Plato’s story and still claim to have Plato’s story. That is like saying the legendary King Arthur is ‘really’ Cleopatra; all you have to do is to change Cleopatra’s sex, nationality, time period, temperament, moral character, and other details, and the resemblance becomes obvious.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:timaeus&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.499834/page/n31/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Plato, &lt;em&gt;Timaeus And Critias&lt;/em&gt;, 6th century BC, English translation, 1929&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:timaeus&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gen_proclus&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/timaeusofplato00platiala/page/64/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Archer-hind, R. D. &lt;em&gt;The Timaeus of Plato&lt;/em&gt;,  1888&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gen_proclus&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gen_burnet&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/burnetsgreekphil00burnuoft/page/350/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Burnet, John. &lt;em&gt;Greek Philosophy I&lt;/em&gt;, 1914&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gen_burnet&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:strabo&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/Strabo08Geography17AndIndex/Strabo%2001%20Geography%201-2/page/n425/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Strabo. &lt;em&gt;Geography&lt;/em&gt;, 1st century AD, English translation, 1917&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:strabo&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:franke&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Franke, Thorwald C. &lt;em&gt;Aristotle and Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;, English translation, 2012 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:franke&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:proclus&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/proclusontimaeus01procuoft/page/64&quot;&gt;Proclus, &lt;em&gt;Commentary on Plato’s Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, 4th century AD, English translation, 1820&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:proclus&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:muck&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Muck, Otto. &lt;em&gt;The Secret of Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;, English translation, 1981 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:muck&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:usher&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/historiansofgree00ushe/page/234/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Usher, Stephen. &lt;em&gt;The Historians of Greece and Rome&lt;/em&gt;, p. 235, 1970&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:usher&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:diodoros&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/DiodorosOfSicily034.598/Diodoros%20of%20Sicily%2002%20%282.35-4.58%29/page/n253/mode/1up&quot;&gt;Diodoros of Sicily, &lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt;, 1st century BC, English translation, 1933&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:diodoros&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gomara&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.cz/books?pg=PA337&amp;amp;ei=J5C_T4nHF6SN6QGGn_nOCg&amp;amp;id=VHoKAQAAIAAJ&quot;&gt;de Gómara, Francisco López. &lt;em&gt;Historia general de las Indias&lt;/em&gt;, 1552&lt;/a&gt; (Google Books) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gomara&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:kircher&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/mundussubterrane02kirc/page/n123/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Kircher, Athanasius. &lt;em&gt;Mundus Subterraneus&lt;/em&gt;, 1678&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:kircher&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:bacon&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bacon, Francis. &lt;em&gt;The New Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;, Francis Bacon, 1627. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:bacon&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:donnelly&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/atlantisantedilu00donnuoft/page/x/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Donnelly, Ingatius L. &lt;em&gt;Atlantis: the antediluvian world&lt;/em&gt;, 1882&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:donnelly&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:blavatsky&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/secretdoctrine01unkngoog/page/n10/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Blavatsky, Helena. &lt;em&gt;The Secret Doctrine&lt;/em&gt;, 1917&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:blavatsky&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:nazis&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.haaretz.com/jewish/holocaust-remembrance-day/.premium-the-dark-link-between-nazis-and-atlantis-1.6870036&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dark Link Between the Nazis and the Legend of Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (haaretz.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:nazis&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cayce&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Johnson, Paul K. &lt;em&gt;Edgar Cayce in Context: The Readings, Truth and Fiction&lt;/em&gt;, 1998 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cayce&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cayce2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bibliotecapleyades.net/esp_cayce_3.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edgar Cayce’s Atlantis Readings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (bibliotecapleyades.net) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cayce2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:woa1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BqhMGVLUSB0&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;THE LOST CITY OF ATLANTIS: What researchers get WRONG about Plato’s famous legend&lt;/em&gt;, World of Antiquity, 2019&lt;/a&gt; (youtube.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:woa1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:woa2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;ATLANTIS: The TRUTH about the Richat Hypothesis&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;ATLANTIS: The TRUTH about the Richat Hypothesis&lt;/em&gt;, World of Antiquity, 2019&lt;/a&gt; (youtube.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:woa2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:figuier&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k22526x&quot;&gt;Figuier, Louis. &lt;em&gt;La Terre et les Mers&lt;/em&gt;, 1872&lt;/a&gt; (bnf.fr) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:figuier&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
