<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Dubious History</title>
 <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2021-03-21T19:03:35+01:00</updated>
 <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Dighton Rock</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/artifacts/dighton-rock"/>
   <updated>2021-03-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/artifacts/dighton-rock</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Dighton Rock, crystaline sandstone boulder found in the riverbed of the Taunton River in current Berkley, Massachsetts, bears petroglyphs which are still controversial to this day.  This artefact is remarkable mainly for how long it is has been generating range of very diverse speculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/DightonRock/DightonRock.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Crop from Seth Eastman at Dighton Rock by Horatio B. King, 1853.  Petroglyphs are traced with chalk.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Crop from Seth Eastman at Dighton Rock by Horatio B. King, 1853.  Petroglyphs are traced with chalk. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first reference to the carvings on the Dighton Rock dates back to 1680, shortly after the suppression of rebellion of Wampanoag Indians, when recent Harvard graduate John Danforth spotted the rock in what was then the town of Dighton and made a drawing of its carvings.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:inscriptions&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:inscriptions&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A book &lt;em&gt;The Wonderful Works of God Commemorated&lt;/em&gt; by Cotton Mather from 1690 makes a reference to the rock:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Among the other Curiosities of New-England, one is that of a mighty Rock, on a perpendicular side whereof by a River, which at High Tide covers part of it, there are very deeply Engraved, no man alive knows How or When about half a score Lines, near Ten Foot Long, and a foot and half broad, filled with strange Characters: which would suggest as odd Thoughts about them that were here before us, as there are odd Shapes in that Elaborate Monument.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:mather&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:mather&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, because no organic pigment or no other related artefacts have been found in the area, there’s no way of scientifically dating when the inscriptions were made.  But there don’t seem to be any doubts about it’s antiquity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/DightonRock/transcriptions.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A compilation of transcriptions from Envisioning Information by Edward Tufte, based on Annual report of the Bureau of Ethnology to the Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution 1880&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;A compilation of transcriptions from Envisioning Information by Edward Tufte, based on Annual report of the Bureau of Ethnology to the Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution 1880 &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;theories-of-origin&quot;&gt;Theories of origin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a few hundred years of speculation, the extensive petroglyphs on the rock have still raise controversy. The most widely held hypothesis attributes them to Native Americans.  However, it was attributed also to Norse Vikings, Portuguese, Phoenicians, Chinese and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1767, Ezra Stiles, then president of Yale University, declared in his &lt;em&gt;Election Sermon&lt;/em&gt; that the figures on the rock were of Phoenician origin.  Stiles writes that a copy of inscription was sent to M. Gebelin of the Parisian academy of sciences, who comparing them with the Punic paleography, judges them punic, and has interpreted them as denoting, that the ancient Carthaginians once visited these distant regions.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:stiles&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:stiles&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side-note:&lt;/em&gt; George Washington opined - while shown the Sewell’s transcription in Harvard College in 1789 - scoffed at the then-prevailing Phoenician thoery. He concluded that the markings most likely made by American Indians.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:washington&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:washington&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The controversy was reignited when Danish writer Charles Christian Rafn published his &lt;em&gt;Antiquities Americanae&lt;/em&gt; in 1837, which contained more than 40 pages of analysis of the Dighton Rock. Rafn concluded the markings on the rock were Norse.  His translation says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thorfinn and his 151 companions took possession of this land.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:rafn&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:rafn&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1912, Edmund B. Delabarre announced his discovery of date “1511” and the name of “Miguel Corte-Real,” a Portuguese explorer who had left Portugal in 1502 and never returned.  Fifty years after, Manuel Da Silva made a study of the rock and came upon two other clues, the Portuguese royal coat-of-arms and the Portuguese Cross of the Order of Christ. He published his findings in his &lt;em&gt;Portuguese Pilgrims and Dighton Rock&lt;/em&gt; in 1971. Delabarre proposed that he had been heard from, in the inscription on the rock that read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;MIGUEL CORTEREAL – V. DEI HIC DUX IND – 1511 &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:delabarre&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:delabarre&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;= &lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/DightonRock/cortereal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Detail of the replica displayed at the Museu da Marinha, Lisbon, Portugal, conveniently ignoring all previous inscriptions which don't support the argument.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Detail of the replica displayed at the Museu da Marinha, Lisbon, Portugal, conveniently ignoring all previous inscriptions which don’t support the argument. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 =&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recent proponents of the Portuguese theory include Manuel Luciano da Silva and Geroge F. W. Young&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:young&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:young&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  Notable historian of Portuguese discoveries, Luís de Albuquerque, discarded the theory in his &lt;em&gt;Navegadores, Viajantes e Aventureiros Portugueses (1987)&lt;/em&gt;.  More recently, popular literature writer Douglas Hunter provides thorough analysis, debunking the Corte-Real origin myth.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hunter&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hunter&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most recent theories came in 2002. Gavin Menzies, in his book &lt;em&gt;1421: The Year China Discovered America&lt;/em&gt;, proposed that the inscriptions we made by Chinese explorers who had arrived and claimed the Americas for themselves at that time.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:menzies&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:menzies&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, that the historians of Dighton Rock Museum hold that it’s made by native Americans.  The museum recently acquired high-resolution 3D scan of the object, giving them access to the smallest details and angles.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:berkland&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:berkland&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hunter:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hunter&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best description of the Rorschach test-like effect the rock has on people was fittingly summarized by E. B. Delabarre himself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is easy to imagine as present on the rock almost any desired letter of the alphabet, especially of crude of early forms; and that, starting with almost any favored story, he can discover for it, if he looks for them eagerly enough, illustrative images to fit its various features, and initial letters or even entire words or names.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:delabarre2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:delabarre2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:inscriptions&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/annualreportofbu1018881889smit&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Annual report of the Bureau of Ethnology to the Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution&lt;/em&gt;, 1880&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:inscriptions&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:mather&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://quod.lib.umich.edu/e/evans/N00431.0001.001/1:3?rgn=div1;view=toc&quot;&gt;Mather, Cotton. &lt;em&gt;The wonderful works of God Commemorated&lt;/em&gt;, 1690&lt;/a&gt; (umich.edu) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:mather&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:stiles&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalcommons.unl.edu/etas/41/&quot;&gt;Stiles, Ezra. &lt;em&gt;Election Sermon&lt;/em&gt;, 1783&lt;/a&gt; (unl.edu) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:stiles&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:washington&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=th1TuDKZ4kc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dighton Rock Inscription in History&lt;/em&gt;, Harvard University&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Better source needed.&lt;/strong&gt; (youtube.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:washington&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:rafn&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rafn, Charles Christian. &lt;em&gt;Antiquities Americanae&lt;/em&gt;, 1837 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:rafn&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:delabarre&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/dightonrockstudy00dela/page/n11/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Delabarre, Edmund Burke. &lt;em&gt;Dighton rock; a study of the written rocks of New England&lt;/em&gt;, 1928&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:delabarre&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:young&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Young, George F. W. &lt;em&gt;Miguel Corte-Real and the Dighton Writing-Rock&lt;/em&gt;, 1970 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:young&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hunter&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dwhauthor.wordpress.com/2018/02/19/the-place-of-stone-introduction/&quot;&gt;Hunter, Douglas. &lt;em&gt;The Place of Stone&lt;/em&gt;, 2017&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Better source needed.&lt;/strong&gt; (dwhauthor.wordpress.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hunter&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hunter:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:menzies&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Menzies, Gavin. &lt;em&gt;1421: The Year China Discovered America&lt;/em&gt;, 2002 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:menzies&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:berkland&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2017/09/harvard-art-museums-tour-lands-at-dighton-rock/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Harvard Art Museums tour takes visitors to Dighton Rock&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (harvard.edu) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:berkland&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:delabarre2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/recenthistoryofd20delauoft/page/310/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Delabarre, Edmund Burke. &lt;em&gt;Recent History of Dighton Rock&lt;/em&gt;, 1919&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:delabarre2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Phoenicians in America</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/phoenicians-in-america"/>
   <updated>2021-03-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/phoenicians-in-america</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The theory of Phoenician discovery of the America suggests that the earliest Old World contact with the Americas was not with Columbus or even Norse settlers, but with the Phoenicians (or, alternatively, other Semitic peoples).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no wonder that there’s so many controversies surrounding this enigmatic people, which we still know little about, ranging from the extent of their sea travels to their religion and alleged child sacrifices.  Ironically, though their alphabet became one of the most widely used writing system in the West, very few Phoenician manuscripts have survived in the original or in translation due either to their destruction during Macedonian and Roman aggression or for having been written on perishable material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People generally consider this particular theory to be fringe, because quite a few artifacts speaking in it’s favor are now considered to be forgeries.  However, there are still people who vehemently support it and it’s much more controversial then one might think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;archaeological-evidence&quot;&gt;Archaeological evidence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-paraíba-inscription&quot;&gt;The Paraíba Inscription&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1872, National Museum of Brazil received a letter signed by a man named Joaquim Alves da Costa, which contained transcription of the inscriptions found on a stone at “&lt;em&gt;Pouso-Alto on the shores of the Parahyba&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The director of the museum Ladislau de souza Mello Netto first accepted the inscription as geniune, but by 1873, philologist Ernest Renan convinced him that it was a forgery.  According to his translation the inscription tells story of “Sidonian Canaanites”, who set sail around Africa and wound up on the shores of Brazil during the nineteenth year of the reign of King Hiram, some 500 years BC.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:netto&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:netto&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/Phoenicians/paraiba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Inscriptions sent along with the letter.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Inscriptions sent along with the letter. &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netto also reports that all efforts of locating the original author of the inscription were in vain, which led him to believe that it was a hoax.  The skeptical website &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.badarchaeology.com/out-of-place-artefacts/petroglyphs-inscriptions-and-reliefs/the-paraiba-parahyba-stone/&quot;&gt;BadArcheology.com&lt;/a&gt; claims that there was a real person Joachim Alves da Costa Freitas, who lived close to Pouso Alto in Minas Gerais province during the 1870s.  Sadly, the link seemingly proving this leads to now-defunct Yahoo Groups and it doesn’t seem to be archived anywhere.  If you know how to verify such information in some official records, please &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;let us know!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hypothesis was brought up again in 1967 by Cyrus Herzel Gordon, expert in Semitic languages and head of the Department of Mediterranean Studies at Brandeis University, well-known for his translations of the ancient Cretan “Linear A”.  He provided a slightly different translation and concluded that “it is obvious that the text is genuine, since it didn’t copy any Semitic writing that would have been widely accessible at the time.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gordon&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gordon&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another contemporary expert on Semitic languages, Frank Moore Cross, disagreed, supporting Renan’s opinion that the letter forms cover a range of ten centuries and that they could be made with knowledge of that time (see e.g. Jordan Moabite Stone from 1870&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:boloji&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:boloji&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is Dr. Gordon’s translation of the text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are Sidonian Canaanites from the city of the Mercantile King. We were cast up on this distant shore, a land of mountains. We sacrificed a youth to the celestial gods and goddesses in the nineteenth year of our mighty King Hiram and embarked from Ezion-geber into the Red Sea. We voyaged with ten ships and were at sea together for two years around Africa [Ham]. Then we were separated by the hand of Baal and were no longer with our companions. So we have come here, twelve men and three women, into New Shore. Am I, the Admiral, a man who would flee? Nay! May the celestial gods and goddesses favour us well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s conclude with a wonderful summary from Austin Whittall on his Patagonian Monsters blog: “So, we have a letter with a transcription of inscriptions found on a stone, that was never actually seen by scientists, it was posted from an unknown place on an ambiguous river by a person who could not be found later. It’s text was, according to some scholars badly written and therefore a hoax, but, according to others, genuine.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:whittall&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:whittall&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Make of that what you will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bat-creek-inscription&quot;&gt;Bat Creek inscription&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bat Creek stone is an inscribed stone collected as part of a Native American burial mound excavation in Loudon County, Tennessee, in 1889.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inscriptions were initially described as Cherokee, but Gordon correctly identified them as Hebrew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However in 2004, similarities to an inscription that was circulating in a Freemason book were discovered by Robert C. Mainfort and Mary L. Kwas indicating that it’s religiously motivated nineteenth century forgery.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:kwas&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:kwas&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  The inscription in question, an 1860s artist’s impression of how the Biblical phrase QDSh LYHWH, or “Holy to Yahweh,” would have looked in Paleo-Hebrew letters, is reproduced below along with the Bat Creek stone itself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Phoenicians/macoy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;macoy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Phoenicians/batcreek.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;batcreek&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;General History, Cyclopedia, and Dictionary of Freemasonry, 1870&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bat Creek Stone inscription, found in 1889&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;los-lunas-decalogue-stone&quot;&gt;Los Lunas Decalogue Stone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This inscribed stone is located on a 400 foot high mesa in Hidden Mountain, near Los Lunas, New Mexico.  It is written in Paleo-Hebrew using north Canaanite script of the early first millenium BC and it appears to be a version of Decalogue (better known as Ten Commandments).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the stone’s discovery in the 1930s, several different translations were proposed.  But it was translation of Robert Pfeiffer of Harvard’s Semitic Museum from 1949 that created the greatest interest among scholars and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many ascribe the first mention of the stone in print to the late Prof. Frank C. Hibben, archaeologist from University of Mexico, in 1933, though no record exists of his having published anything on the subject.  It was first reported by Prof. James D. Tabor of the Dept. of Religious Studies, University of North Carolina - Charlotte, who interviewed Hibben in 1996.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:tabor&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:tabor&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hibben reports that he first saw the text in 1933. At the time it was covered with lichen and patination and was hardly visible. He was taken to the site by a guide who had seen it as a boy, back in the 1880s.”  Hibben’s assessment of its age in the 1930s, based on the growth of mosses and lichens on it, was that the incised characters were at least a hundred years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stone is blanched (from being cleaned by Boy Scouts in the 1950s, Hibben told Tabor), making dating through the patina, the surface layer of the rock, impossible. The first line has been scratched out by a vandal in 2006, but the rest of the inscription is completely legible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Atlee Phillips, curator of Archeology at the Maxwell Museum of Anthropology and professor of anthropology at the University of New Mexico, finds it much more likely that the inscription is the work of con artists than evidence of an ancient civilization. The smoking gun for Phillips is the “caret”, the upside-down V symbol placed under a piece of text where something has been missed out.  Sometimes found in ancient Latin and Greek texts, it is not known in Hebrew until the Middle Ages.  To make matters worse, it is above a dot that seems to be a full stop (or period); full stops did not exist in ancient Hebrew. Moreover, there are Greek letters of a slightly later date mixed in with Hebrew forms.&lt;sup&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;citation needed&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, even before 1880, and certainly before 1933 when Hibben first described the stone, enough had been learned about Paleo-Hebrew to account for a contemporary forgery.  See e.g. &lt;em&gt;A Discourse Concerning Sanchoniathon’s Phoenician History&lt;/em&gt; by Henry Dodwell from 1691.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, let’s not discount the presence of refugee Jews in the earliest waves of Spanish colonists and settlers in the 16th or 17th century in today’s New Mexico one of the farthest outposts in the empire of New Spain. It was an excellent place to avoid the horrors of the Inquisition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;baal-stone&quot;&gt;Baal Stone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The triangular stone, first documented by archaeologist James P. Whittall II, was popularized in book &lt;em&gt;America B.C.&lt;/em&gt; by Barry Fell.  According to Fell, the inscription is in Iberian Punic script and says “To Baal of the Canaanites, this in Dedication”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fell&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fell&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was found on a site called America’s Stonehenge in Salem, New Hampshire, previously called Mystery Hill by its owner William Goodwin who believed it was built by Culdee monks from Ireland.  The place was later sold to Bob Stone whose son still owns the site and the stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side-note:&lt;/em&gt; One of the photos circulating the internet which apparently shows the artifact is definitely a replica.  Although the inscriptions are more or less equal to the ones depicted in Fell’s book, it’s clearly a different stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Phoenicians/baal1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;baal1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Phoenicians/baal2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;baal2&quot; /&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/i/Phoenicians/baal3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;baal3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another claim was presented (relatively) recently at History Channel TV show &lt;em&gt;America Unearthed&lt;/em&gt; by Scott Wolter and a son of current owner of the site.  They hint at the posibility of Phoenician link with the site by showing that Summer Solstice sunrise alignment of American’s stonehenge can be extended all the way to the Stonehenge and continues straight into city of Beirut, Lebanon.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:stonehenge&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:stonehenge&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from referring to Lebanon as “ancient home of the ancient Phoenicians”, they don’t explain what’s the connection with England’s Stonehenge.  They also fail to mention that while the place we call Beirut today was most likely settled, it doesn’t seem to play any big role in historical records compared to cities like Byblos or Sidon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, the summer solstice sunrise alignment of America’s Stonehenge does point roughly in the direction of Stonehenge, but remember that the exact course of this line is obviously very sensitive on the initial degree.  Lines which start pretty much parallel can diverge by several kilometers by the time they reach England.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Another side-note:&lt;/em&gt; Just few days before finishing this article, a QAnon supporter allegedly vandalized the megalithic monument with infamous WWG1WGA slogan and his twitter handle.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:qanon&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:qanon&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plymouth State University archaeologist David Starbuck notes the 19th century quarrying marks on many of the stones and said the site has been altered so many times over the decades—particularly by owner and researcher William Goodwin starting in 1936—that there will never be a way to settle the argument over its genesis.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:starbuck&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:starbuck&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sherbrooke-stones&quot;&gt;Sherbrooke stones&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to 1975 newspaper article, A Laval University Prof. Thomas Lee found three stones in Quebec province’s Eastern Townships which could indicate that North America was visited by North Africans 500 years before the birth of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof. Thomas Lee said the stones were discovered “sometime early in this century” but the Egyptian inscriptions were written in a Libyan script not deciphered until last year.  He said the earliest mention of the stones he has seen is in a letter dated Dec. 26, 1910, but he “got the impression the stones were not in the museum at that time.” A spokesman for the museum said it has had the stones since at least 1910.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:winnipeg&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:winnipeg&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said one stone is inscribed: “Expedition that crossed in the service of Lord Hiram to conquer territory.” The other of the pair discovered together bears the inscription: “Record by Hata, who attained this limit on the river, moored his ship and engraved this rock.”  The stone which was found alone reads: “Hanno, son of Tamu, reached this mountain landmark.”,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:winnipeg:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:winnipeg&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Probably alluding to famous Hanno the Navigator himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;see-also-dighton-rock&quot;&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&quot;/artifacts/dighton-rock&quot;&gt;Dighton Rock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coins&quot;&gt;Coins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;roman-coins&quot;&gt;Roman coins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reports of Romanian coins in America go back to the 16th century.  The earliest account is of Marineo Siculo, who reported in 1533 that a coin bearing the image of Augustus was found in the gold mines of Panama.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:siculo&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:siculo&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  In the 19th century, two more finds were reported to be found at two different but neighboring locations in Tennessee.  William C. Atwater was the first to discuss this material in 1818, but remained very skeptical.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:atwater&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:atwater&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  His contemporary Haywood, proponent of idea that Romans, Hebrews, etc. played a role in forming Native American culture, was not so skeptical; he published list of objects suggestive of transoceanic contact, including 4 Roman coins all discovered around a town in Arkansas.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:haywood&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:haywood&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  The first mention of a Hebrew coin is from letter sent to editors of &lt;em&gt;The New York Times&lt;/em&gt; in 1860.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:schoolcraft&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:schoolcraft&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1970s-phoenician-coins&quot;&gt;1970s Phoenician coins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 20th century, discoveries started to mount up rapidly.  Starting in 1913, when Macedonian tetradrachma was found while digging a house foundation in Montana.  First mention of coin suggesting direct Phoenician contact comes from the non-peer reviewed (and now defunct) &lt;em&gt;Anthropological Journal of Canada&lt;/em&gt; in a paper by Joseph B. Mahan and Douglas C. Braithwaite in 1975.  They describe the discovery of a “Syracusean coin” by a boy in Phenix City, Alabama, who wanted to trade it for candy.  He said he found it near his home at the edge of the city.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:mahan&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:mahan&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coin was later sent to Preston E. Blackwell, from University of Georgia, who sent it to Fogg Museum in Boston for identification.  Museum officials identified the coin as a Syracuse coin dating from 490 BC.  According the Blackwell, the coin was later stolen from his wallet when he was hospitalized.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:mahan:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:mahan&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next publication to discuss the coins was a 1977 cover story by Norman Totten titled &lt;em&gt;Carthagian coins found in Arkansas and Alabama&lt;/em&gt;.  Totten had been sent a coin similar to the one described by Mahan and Braithwaite by professor Barry Fell.  Totten concluded that the coin was genuine and that based “on the obverse style alone, one might date this coin to about 350” BC.  Fell got the coin from an amateur archaeologist Gloria Farley from Eastern Oklahoma Historical Society, who in turn got it from a man who claimed he found it with a metal detector buried six inches deep in a field near Cauthron, Arkansas. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:totten&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:totten&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark A. McMenamin from Mount Holyoke College, previous proponent of their authenticity, provided exhaustive recapitulation of all evidence “Fell’s” coins and concluded that all of these were most likely modern forgeries.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:mcmenamin&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:mcmenamin&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;finding-patterns&quot;&gt;Finding patterns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to date, some 40 out-of-place coins are documented in a scientific literature (most of them being Roman coins).  The striking increase in coin discoveries comes after WWII, most of them are reported in 60s and 70s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting aspect is that the dates minted on coins are spread across much of Greek and Roman history ranging from 490 BC to 800 AD, which would imply prolonged contact for hundreds of years if we would accept all evidence as true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Jeremian F. Epstein from University of Chicago, who made an exhaustive assessment of all evidence available in 1980s, concludes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The significance of the occasional discovery of a Roman, Greek or Hebrew coin in America is hard to asses, largely because such discoveries are comparatively rare and seldom adequately documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When one examines the dates of the coin discoveries, the distribution of the finds, and the times when the coins were minted, the most plausible interpretation is that the coins were lost recently. In fact, most of them appear to have been lost since WWIII.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The biggest stumbling block in the way of giving these coins pre-Columbian status is that none have been found in documented prehistoric contexts.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:epstein&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:epstein&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about those 15th- to 19th-century finds?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The long period of time between the first report, in 1533, and the, in 1818, should arouse suspicion. If they were valid, one would imagine that ancient coins would have shown up in increasing numbers as America became settled.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:epstein:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:epstein&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That however didn’t happen until after the last world war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;historical-evidence&quot;&gt;Historical evidence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ptolemys-geography&quot;&gt;Ptolemy’s &lt;em&gt;Geography&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, Lucio Russo has speculated about a probable arrival of Phoenicians in the Americas in his philological analyses regarding Fortunate Isles, &lt;em&gt;a.k.a.&lt;/em&gt; Islands of the Blessed.  This mythical winterless paradise from Greek mythology would deserve their own analysis, but for the sake of Russo’s argument we will only look at Ptolemy’s &lt;em&gt;Geography&lt;/em&gt;, which provides information about geographical longitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his book Ptolemy gives the coordinates of the Fortunate Isles but at the same time he shrinks the size of the world by one third compared to the size measured by Eratosthenes.  He argues that the underestimate of size is caused by incorrect identification of Fortunate Isles with Carribean and by attributing those coordinates to the Antilles, the world gets back to the right size and also certain other puzzling deformations in Ptolemy’s world map disappear.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:russo&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:russo&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russo also argues that the Antilles coordinates must have been known to Ptolemy’s source, Hipparchus. Hipparchus lived in Rhodes and may have gotten this information from Phoenicians sailors, since they had full control of the western Mediterranean in those times.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:russo2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:russo2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;diodoros-of-sicily&quot;&gt;Diodoros of Sicily&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diodoros’ &lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt; is remarkable for many reasons. This 40-volume book (of which only 15 books survive intact) is considered one of the earliest attempts at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_history&quot;&gt;Universal history&lt;/a&gt; and also it is notably more detached from ‘Hellenocentric’ world-view&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:usher&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:usher&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  It’s also a major source of our knowledge about Alexander the Great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, some passages are a bit controversial.  For fans of Alternative History, he’s mainly notable for his mentions of Atlanteans, but it also contains this peculiar passage story about Phoenicians:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But now that we have discussed what relates to the islands which lie within the Pillars of Hercules, we shall give an account of those which are in the ocean. For there lies out in the deep off Libya an island of considerable size, and situated as it is in the ocean it is distant from Libya a voyage of a number of days to the west.  Its land is fruitful, much of it being mountainous and not a little being a level plain of surpassing beauty. Through it flow navigable rivers which are used for irrigation, and the island contains many parks planted with trees of every variety and gardens in great multitudes which are traversed by streams of sweet water;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;on it also are private villas of costly construction, and throughout the gardens banqueting houses have been constructed in a setting of flowers, and in them the inhabitants pass their time during the summer season, since the land supplies in abundance everything which contributes to enjoyment and luxury.  […] the climate of this island is so altogether mild that it produces in abundance the fruits of the trees and the other seasonal fruits for the larger part of the year, so that it would appear that the island, because of its exceptional felicity, were a dwelling-place of a race of gods and not of men.(V-19)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:diodoros&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:diodoros&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In ancient times this island remained undiscovered because of its distance from the entire inhabited world j but it was discovered at a later period for the following reason.  The Phoenicians, who from ancient times on made voyages continually for purposes of trade, planted many colonies throughout Libya and not a few as well in the western parts of Europe.  And since their ventures turned out according to their expectations, they amassed great wealth and essayed to voyage beyond the Pillars of Heracles into the sea which men call the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] The Phoenicians, then, while exploring the coast outside the Pillars for the reasons we have stated and while sailing along the shore of Libya, were driven by strong winds a great distance out into the ocean. And after being storm-tossed for many days they were carried ashore on the island we mentioned above, and when they had observed its felicity and nature they caused it to be known to all men.(V-20)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:diodoros:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:diodoros&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we are said that Tyrrhenians wanted to make a colony there, but Carthaginians prevented it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] partly out of concern lest many inhabitants of Carthage should remove there because of the excellence of the island, and partly in order to have ready in it a place in which to seek refuge against an incalculable turn of fortune, in case some total disaster should overtake Carthage.  For it was their thought that, since they were masters of the sea, they would thus be able to move, households and all, to an island which was unknown to their conquerors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could this be another reference to Fortunate Islands?  And would that mean Canary Islands, Azores, or Americas?  So far we haven’t found any mentions of this passage in scholarly sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:netto&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bdor.sibi.ufrj.br/handle/doc/20&quot;&gt;Netto, Ladislau. &lt;em&gt;Lettre a Monsieur Ernest Renan a propos de l’inscrioption Phenicienne apocryphe soumise en 1872 a l’Institut historique, geographique et ethnograpicque du Bresil&lt;/em&gt;, 1885&lt;/a&gt; (ufrj.br) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:netto&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gordon&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/43078826&quot;&gt;Gordon, Cyrus H. &lt;em&gt;The Canaanite Text from Brazil&lt;/em&gt;, 1968&lt;/a&gt; (jstor.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gordon&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:boloji&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.boloji.com/articles/14383/phoenicians-in-the-americas&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phoenicians in the Americas - Is the Paraiba Stone of Brazil Genuine?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (boloji.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:boloji&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:whittall&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patagoniamonsters.blogspot.com/2011/03/phoenician-inscriptions-from-paraiba.html&quot;&gt;Whittall, Austin. &lt;em&gt;The “Phoenician” inscriptions from Paraiba, Brazil&lt;/em&gt;, 2011&lt;/a&gt; (blogspot.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:whittall&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:kwas&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Kwas, Mary L., Mainfort, Robert C. &lt;em&gt;The Bat Creek Stone Revisited&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;American Antiquity&lt;/em&gt;, v. 69, n. 4, 2004. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:kwas&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:tabor&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/19981202230505/http://www.unitedisrael.org/loslunas.html&quot;&gt;Tabor, James D. &lt;em&gt;An Ancient Hebrew Inscription in New Mexico&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:tabor&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fell&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/americabcancient00fell&quot;&gt;Fell, Barry. &lt;em&gt;America B.C.&lt;/em&gt;, 1978&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fell&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:stonehenge&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;America Unearthed&lt;/em&gt; TV Show, Season 01, Episode 06 - Stonehenge in America, 2012 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:stonehenge&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:qanon&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2021/mar/04/americas-stonehenge-qanon-carving-mark-russo&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Man arrested for allegedly carving QAnon slogan at ‘America’s Stonehenge’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (theguardian.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:qanon&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:starbuck&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Starbuck, David R. &lt;em&gt;The Archaeology of New Hampshire: Exploring 10,000 Years in the Granite State&lt;/em&gt;, 2006 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:starbuck&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:winnipeg&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20191217073811/http://uhem-mesut.com/medu/en0052.php&quot;&gt;Lee, Thomas. &lt;em&gt;Africans Visited North America 2,500 Years Ago - Archeologist&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Winnipeg Free Press&lt;/em&gt;, 1976&lt;/a&gt; (uhem-mesut.com, archived) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:winnipeg&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:winnipeg:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:siculo&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://liburutegibiltegi.bizkaia.eus/handle/20.500.11938/69370&quot;&gt;Siculo, Marineo. &lt;em&gt;De las cosas memorables de España&lt;/em&gt;, 1530&lt;/a&gt; (bizkaia.eus) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:siculo&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:atwater&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.loc.gov/resource/lhbtn.12883/?sp=19&quot;&gt;Atwater, Caleb. &lt;em&gt;Archæologia americana: transactions and collections of the American Antiquarian Society&lt;/em&gt;, p. 19, 1820&lt;/a&gt; (loc.gov) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:atwater&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:haywood&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/naturalaborigina00hayw/page/174/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Haywood, John. &lt;em&gt;The Natural and Aboriginal History of Tennessee&lt;/em&gt;, p. 174, 1823&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:haywood&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:schoolcraft&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/1860/08/06/archives/the-hebrew-stone-in-ohio-letter-from-mr-henry-r-schoolcraft.html&quot;&gt;Schoolcraft, Henry R. &lt;em&gt;The “Hebrew stone” in Ohio.; Letter from Mr. Henry R. Schoolcraft, sent to *The New York Times&lt;/em&gt; in 1860&lt;/a&gt; (nytimes.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:schoolcraft&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:mahan&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Mahan, J., Braithwaite, D. &lt;em&gt;Discovery of Ancient Coins in the United States&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Anthropological Journal of Canada&lt;/em&gt;, v. 12, n. 2, p. 15-18, 1975 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:mahan&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:mahan:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:totten&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Totten, Norman. &lt;em&gt;Carthaginian Coins found in Arkansas and Alabama&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;ESOP IV&lt;/em&gt;, v. 88, 1977 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:totten&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:mcmenamin&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;McMenamin, Mark A. &lt;em&gt;Phoenicians, Fakes and Barry Fell: Solving the Mystery of Carthaginian Coins Found in America&lt;/em&gt;, 2000 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:mcmenamin&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:epstein&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/202398&quot;&gt;Epstein, Jeremiah F. &lt;em&gt;Pre-Columbian Old World Coins in America: An Examination of the Evidence&lt;/em&gt;, 1980&lt;/a&gt; (uchicago.edu) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:epstein&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:epstein:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:russo&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://msp.org/memocs/2018/6-3/p02.xhtml&quot;&gt;Russo, Lucio. &lt;em&gt;Far-reaching Hellenistic geographical knowledge hidden in Ptolemy’s data&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mathematics and Mechanics of Complex System&lt;/em&gt;, v. 6, n. 3, 2018&lt;/a&gt; (msp.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:russo&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:russo2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Russo, Lucio. &lt;em&gt;L’ America dimenticata. I rapporti tra le civiltà e un errore di Tolomeo&lt;/em&gt;, 2013 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:russo2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:usher&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/historiansofgree00ushe/page/234/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Usher, Stephen. &lt;em&gt;The Historians of Greece and Rome&lt;/em&gt;, 1970&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:usher&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:diodoros&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/DiodorosOfSicily034.598/Diodoros%20of%20Sicily%2003%20%284.59-8%29/page/n147/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Diodoros of Sicily. &lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt;, 1st-century BC, English translation, 1933&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:diodoros&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:diodoros:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Pîrî Reis Map of 1513</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/piri-reis-map-of-1513"/>
   <updated>2021-02-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/piri-reis-map-of-1513</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The map drawn by an admiral of Ottoman Empire Muhyi-iddin Pîrî &lt;em&gt;re‘is&lt;/em&gt; dated to 1513 CE is well known in the fringe literature, mainly for it’s alleged depiction of Antarctica coastline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was featured on the &lt;em&gt;Ancient Aliens&lt;/em&gt; and it’s often brought up by Graham Hancock&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hancock&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hancock&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, among others, as a proof of ancient civilization or technology we’re not yet aware of, as the first modern mapping of Antarctica wasn’t done until 19th century.  The argument is that Pîrî himself must have drawn from older, more ancient maps, which ties it into the general notion of ancient civilization theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an undeniable fact, that the precision of this map is astounding for its time.  Made only 20 years after the Discovery, it is the most precise depiction of Brazilian coastline from this period.  Try to compare with other contemporary maps like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waldseem%C3%BCller_map&quot;&gt;Waldseemüller map&lt;/a&gt; from 1507 or even three decades older &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thedigitalgallery.org/images/255&quot;&gt;Sebastian Müster map&lt;/a&gt;.  However, there are numerous misconceptions about this map which need be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/overlay.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Overlay on a modern map&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Overlay on a modern map &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite Pîrî being a well-known and studied figure in Turkish history, the discovery of the map came surprisingly late.  It was discovered by the Director of National Museums, Halil Etem Edhem only in 1929, when the Topkapı Palace in Istanbul was repurposed into a museum.  It’s believed to be just a fraction of a bigger map.  Apart from numerous illustrations of ships, animals and even mythical creatures, and more than a hundred of place-names (mostly corresponding with other contemporary portolan maps), it also features many inscriptions written mainly in Ottoman Turkish.  There are about thirty of them and English translations are available online.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:translation&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:translation&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By far the largest inscription, placed over the South America inland, says following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These coasts are named the shores of Antilia. They were discovered in the year 896 of the Arab calendar [1491 CE]. But it is reported thus, that a Genoese infidel, his name was Columbus, who discovered these places. For instance, a book fell into the hands of the said Columbus, and he found it said in this book that at the end of the Western Sea [Atlantic] that is, on its western side, there were coasts and islands and all kinds of metals and also precious stones. Columbus, having studied this book thoroughly, explained these matters one by one to the greats of Genoa [Italy] and said: “Come, give me two ships, let me go and find these places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The above-mentioned Columbus saw that no help was forthcoming from the Genoese, he sped forth, went to the Bey of Spain [king], and told his tale in detail. They too answered like the Genoese. In brief Columbus petitioned these people for a long time, finally the Bey of Spain gave him two ships[…]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This passage is very interesting in context of our generally accepted notion that Columbus was simply trying to find an alternative route to Asia.  According to Pîrî, there was a book which taught Columbus about the undiscovered shores.  However, this could also refer to Pierre d’Ailly’s &lt;em&gt;Imago Mundi&lt;/em&gt;, which was in Columbus’s possession and which inspired his estimates of the size of the world, implying that he still likely intended to find east coast of Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lower part of the same text elaborates more on the source material:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No one now living has seen a map like this. I have composed and constructed it using about twenty maps and mappaemundi; these are the maps which were composed in the time of Alexander of the Two Horns, and which show the inhabited portion of the earth. The Arabs call these maps ja’fariya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have used eight ja’fariya maps, an Arab map of India and four recent Portuguese maps - these maps show the sea of Sind, India and China according to mathematical principles - and also a map of the western regions drawn by Columbus. The final farm was arrived at by reducing all these maps to the same scale. Therefore the present map is as accurate for the Seven Seas as the maps of our own countries used by sailors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;antarctica&quot;&gt;Antarctica&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to the lowest part of the map, often doubtlessly identified with Antarctica coastline, there are two inscriptions which say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And in this country it seems that there are white-haired monsters in this shape, and also six-horned oxen. The Portuguese infidels have written it in their maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This country is a waste. Everything is in ruin and it is said that large snakes are found here. For this reason the Portuguese infidels did not land on these shores and these are also said to be very hot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will leave to reader to decide how likely it is that these lands refer to Antarctica. In any case, Pîrî clearly credits these parts of the map to Portuguese, not to some lost ancient maps as it’s often claimed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that map actually depicts Antarctica coastline seems to originate with captain Arlington Humphrey Mallery in c. 1956.  In addition to being a captain, he was an amateur archaeologist who believed that North America had been extensively colonised by Celts, Vikings and other Old World peoples, who possessed accurate maps lost to later ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mallery’s accounts apparently inspired Charles Hapgood, famous mainly for his now discredited Polar shift theory, who argued that Pîrî’s map and others are a proof of a lost ancient civilization.  Hapgood’s book show his correspondence with USAF Lt. Colonel Harold Z. Ohlmeyer, who agreed with Hapgood that &lt;em&gt;“this is the most logical and in all probability the correct interpretation of the map”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“lower part of the map agrees very remarkably with the results of the seismic profile made across the top of the ice-cap by the Swedish-British Antarctic Expedition of 1949”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“we have no idea how the data on this map can be reconciled with the supposed state of geographical knowledge in 1513.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hapgood&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hapgood&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/hapgood.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hapgood's interpretation&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Hapgood's interpretation &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are several problems with Hapgood’s hypotheses.  The map does not show Drake’s Passage or the Pacific Ocean. Also, what Hapgood identifies as the Andes mountains are not located along a coast line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theory was later revived by Erich von Däniken in his &lt;em&gt;Chariots of the Gods?&lt;/em&gt;, where he basically just reiterated Hapgood’s claims within his own context of Ancient Aliens hypothesis.  He says that &lt;em&gt;“the only explanation is that it must have been made by extraterrestrials, either at an early date when Antarctica was indeed free from ice or because their technology revealed the underlying surface.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:daniken&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:daniken&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another proponent of this view is above mentioned Graham Hancock, who also adds that one the islands depicts the “Bimini Road”, which Hapgood identified as Cuba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/bimini_road.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An island which according to Hancock depicts Bimini Road&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;An island which according to Hancock depicts Bimini Road &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, serious scholarship holds that there is no reason to believe that the map is the product of genuine knowledge of the Antarctic coast.  General belief is that it actually depicts the South American coastline, just heavily distorted.  This distortion could be caused by an error, motivated by the weird shape of the parchment, or even for political reasons.  This well constructed argument is proposed by Diego Cuoghi on his website, where he doesn’t rely only on correlation of geography, but also on historical arguments and comparison with other historical maps.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cuoghi&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cuoghi&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/piri_brazil.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Correlation with SA coastline according to Diago Cuoghi&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Correlation with SA coastline according to Diago Cuoghi &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speculation alert:&lt;/strong&gt; Could this identification with Tierra del Fuego explain the “shores that are said to be very hot”?  Yes, Magellan officially coined the name in 1525, but maybe some relation with fire was already present before?  He apparently knew about the strait before he set out, as “he saw it, in the Treasury of the King of Portugal, on a map drawn by Martin de Bohemia” (Pigafetta).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, let’s not toss out the possibility that although the map does state the year of it’s creation, it some portions could be drawn later.  As Cuoghi states, we know that the chart of Pedro Reinel, kept in the same Library of Topkapı, was probably retouched after the discovery of the Strait of Magellan, so it wouldn’t be unprecedented.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cuoghi:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cuoghi&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cryptozoology&quot;&gt;Cryptozoology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting thing that is often overlooked are the illustrations of animals and fantastical creatures.  Apart from above-mentioned large snakes, white-haired monsters mentioned in the inscriptions, the map also features an unicorn, monkey dancing with what looks to be a dog-headed man, and a head-less creature reminiscent of &lt;em&gt;blemmyes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/dancing_beasts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/blemmye.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;“In the mountains of this territory were creatures like this and human beings came out on the seacoast. The gold mines are endless.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;“These monsters are seven spans long. The space between their eyes is one span, but they are harmless souls.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These fantastic creatures had already occasionally been depicted in medieval &lt;em&gt;mappae mundi&lt;/em&gt; and many of them were associated with either Africa or Asia.  De La Cosa’s map (1500) also shows &lt;em&gt;blemmye&lt;/em&gt; and a dog-headed man in the Far East, in the approximate location of China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Pîrî Reis they are also found on the chart of Guillaume Le Testu (1555) and associated with the New World on the map of Sebastian Cabot (1544) and that of Guiana by de Bry (1599).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:masseti&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:masseti&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hancock&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qt2GYyGTXTs&quot;&gt;Graham Hancock’s summary of the argument on &lt;em&gt;The Mysterious Origins of Man&lt;/em&gt; TV program.&lt;/a&gt; (youtube.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hancock&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:translation&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://turkeyinmaps.com/piri.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Piri Reis Map of 1513 (translations)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (turkeyinmaps.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:translation&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hapgood&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hapgood, Charles H. &lt;em&gt;Maps of the Ancient Sea Kings&lt;/em&gt;, 1966 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hapgood&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:daniken&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;von Däniken, Erich. &lt;em&gt;Chariots of the Gods?&lt;/em&gt;, 1968 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:daniken&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cuoghi&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diegocuoghi.com/Piri_Reis/PiriReis_eng.htm&quot;&gt;Cuoghi, Diego. &lt;em&gt;The Mysteries of the Piri Reis Map&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (diegocuoghi.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cuoghi&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cuoghi:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:masseti&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sciencepress.mnhn.fr/en/periodiques/anthropozoologica/51/1/les-representations-zoomorphiques-de-la-carte-de-piri-reis-1513&quot;&gt;Masseti, Marco &amp;amp; Veracini, Cecilia. &lt;em&gt;The zoomorphic representations of the Pîrî Reis map (1513)&lt;/em&gt;, 2016&lt;/a&gt; (mnhn.fr) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:masseti&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Atlantis - myths about the myth</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/atlantis"/>
   <updated>2021-01-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/articles/atlantis</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The myth of Atlantis probably doesn’t require much introduction.  The mythical lost civilization and its island has generated speculations in countless books since Plato first mentioned it in 5th century BC, even capturing attention of famous thinkers like Isaac Newton or Francis Bacon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It branched into many different beliefs about its true location, linking Atlantis with Crete, Sardinia, America, Antarctica, Iberian Peninsula, Mauritania and many, many other places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several years’ dormancy in imagination of the broader public, it has begun to make something of a comeback in recent years, partly driven by recent discoveries about Younger Dryas period and ancient settlements like Göbekli Tepe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most skeptical-minded articles focus on debunking of the idea itself or some specific claims, we’re just trying to trace the most repeated claims to their original source and show how the perception of the myth evolved through time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of building an argument, the goal is to gather &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; sources, make as little active claims as possible, and let the reader form his own opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;origin---platos-timaeus-and-critias&quot;&gt;Origin - Plato’s &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Critias&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a speaker in Plato’s &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, a character called Critias states that he heard the Atlantis tale from his grandfather Critias the elder, who heard it from Solon.  Solon, famous Greek statesman who lived two centuries before, allegedly acquired the story in Egypt and “brought it back with him” to Athens, with intentions to adapt it into an epic poem later, which he left unfinished. (&lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, p. 17)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:timaeus&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:timaeus&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;CRITIAS: [It’s a story that] Solon, the wisest of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seven_Sages_of_Greece&quot;&gt;wise seven&lt;/a&gt;, once declared. Solon, who, you must know, was, as he says in several places in his poems, a kinsman and a close friend of my great-grandfather Dropides, told my grandfather Critias (so the Critias in his turn, used to repeat the story to me in his old age), that there are great and splendid ancient exploits of our city which have been forgotten from lapse of time and decay of population, and, in particular, one, the greatest of all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right away, we have a problem.  There are several contradicting interpretations of the genealogy described by Plato.  However, it’s certain that in the time the dialogue was written, Solon must had been dead for at least 150 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Atlantis/proclus.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Atlantis/burnet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interpretation of Proclus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gen_proclus&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gen_proclus&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interpretation of classicist John Burnet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gen_burnet&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gen_burnet&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regard to Atlantis, here are some main takeaways from &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt; (p. 17 - 23):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Athens was inhabited 9,000 ago by Athenians, it was country “foremost both in war and all besides” before it’s destruction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Atlantis was an island with its own kings ruling over many other islands as well as mainland colonies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Located “before Pillars of Heracles” in Atlantic ocean, “larger than Libya and Asia together”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Atlanteans were wealthy and powerful, and set to subjugate all other nations. Athenians revolted and “vanquished the invaders”, even freeing some of their colonies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But layer, great earth-quakes and floods sunk the Atlantis (and drown all Athenian warriors as well).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Plato’s later work, &lt;em&gt;Critias&lt;/em&gt;, things get a bit more interesting (pages 116 - end):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Island of Atlantis was Poseidon’s “lot”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He carved the mountain into a palace and enclosed it with three circular moats.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Poseidon’s temple was in the inner ring and “forbidden to enter”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Poseidon took liking in an orphaned girl.  She gave him ten sons, who later ruled 10 parts of Atlantis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rich fauna and flora, including plentiful of elephants and many fruits and flowers (including ones exuding “gums”), which Atlanteans utilized for their sustenance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gold-red metal called Orichalcum was mined in many parts of Atlantis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apart from the capital city, “mountains contained numerous villages with a wealthy population”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First king of Altantis, Atlas, had a twin brother who ruled region now known as Gadeira (Cádiz). (Note: Later, Strabo and Diodoros attribute foundation of this city to Phoenicians, which even archaeology nowadays seem to confirm)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering that Plato invented Atlantis for the sake of a political allegory, it can seem quite intriguing that so much detail is provided regarding things like geography, natural resources, agricultural practices, etc. before turning focus to society itself.  Then again, we can’t simply ignore that the same amount of detail is provided also for Athens in the same period, which the archeology evidence doesn’t support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that’s pretty much it.  As you can see, there are absolutely no implications of advanced technology or superior esoteric knowledge.  From all descriptions (apart from the dating and mythology, of course), they seem like pretty believable, though remarkably wealthy and powerful, Bronze Age civilization.  They armed themselves with spears and shields, they conquered barbaric lands and they waged war against Athenians, which they lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, reading the whole dialog is highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bonus-solon-in-egypt&quot;&gt;BONUS: Solon in Egypt?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting all claims about Atlantis aside, even the claim that Solon actually travelled to Egypt in the first place is contested.  The first mention of this, apart from Plato’s story of course, comes from Herodotus’ &lt;em&gt;The Histories&lt;/em&gt; (c. 440 BC), some 200 years after Solon’s passing and &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; Platon’s &lt;em&gt;Timeas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Critias&lt;/em&gt; was already well known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there are many inconsistencies in Herodotus’ accounts on Solon’s travel and another story about his travel to Lydia is widely believed to be unhistorical.  However, the idea that Solon could visit Egypt roughly in the specified time is not really preposterous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interpretations-throughout-the-history&quot;&gt;Interpretations throughout the history&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, shouldn’t the story end here?  For many it does.  However, the debate about Atlantis is almost as old as the myth itself.  So how was the story perceived in the ancient times?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;strabo-and-aristotle&quot;&gt;Strabo (and Aristotle?)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantis&quot;&gt;wikipedia page on Atlantis&lt;/a&gt; claims, that Aristotle believed that Plato, his teacher, had invented the island to teach philosophy.  As a source, a 1967 article from &lt;em&gt;Galaxy Science Fiction&lt;/em&gt; magazine, is provided. Itself completely unsourced. (Note: Without taking any sides, it’s always important to be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; careful with accepting claims you read on Wikipedia and where they come from)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what’s the real story?  As always, it’s complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument comes from Strabo’s &lt;em&gt;Geography&lt;/em&gt;.  Strabo (c.60 BC- C.20 BC) endorses Poseidonius’ (c. 135 BC-c.50 BC) view that Atlantis might be more than mere fiction and dismisses argument that “Its inventor caused it to disappear, just as did the Poet the wall of the Acheans.” (Implying &lt;strong&gt;Solon&lt;/strong&gt; avoided the historical consequences of his fiction by sinking Atlantis, just as Homer did by making Poseidon and Apollo sweep away with a flood the wall built by the Achaeans. (Strabo 2.3.6&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:strabo&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:strabo&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does Aristotle come in?  Well, in chapter 13.1.36 in a passage completely unrelated to Atlantis, this quote is referenced again, this time attributed to Aristotle.  This lead some to conclude that first appearance of quote does indeed reflect Aristotle’s opinion on Atlantis.  This is disputed in generally well received book &lt;em&gt;Aristotle and Atlantis&lt;/em&gt; by T. C. Franke&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:franke&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:franke&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;commentary-on-platos-timaeus-by-proclus&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Commentary on Plato’s Timaeus&lt;/em&gt; by Proclus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosopher Crantor (c. 3rd century BC), a student of Plato’s student Xenocrates, is often cited as an example of a writer who thought the story to be historical fact.  His work, a commentary on &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, is however lost and all our information come from commentary on his work from 5th century by Neoplatonist Proclus (more than 600 years after life of Crantor) In regard to Atlantis story, he reports&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:proclus&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:proclus&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With respect for the whole of this narration about the Atlantics, some say, that it is a mere history, which was the opinion of Crantor, the first interpreter of Plato, who says, that Plato was derided by those of his time, as not being the inventor of the Republic, but transcribing what the Egyptians had written on this subject; and that he so far regards what is said by these deriders as to refer to the Egyptians this history about the Athenians and Atlantics, and to believe that the Athenians once lived conformably to this polity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[He] adds, that this is testified by the prophets of the Egyptians, who assert that these particulars [which are narrated by Plato] are written on pillars which are still preserved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re putting ‘He’ in brackets, because some translations say it was Crantor, who confirms the story (see 1820 English translation in Sources) but Greek original uses ambiguous ‘He’, which leaves room for speculations that it was Plato himself who verified the story with Egyptians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever you lean towards, all we can safely state is that according to 5th CE century Greek Neoplatonist philosopher, Plato, facing ridicule, made attempts to verify the story with Egyptians and either Plato or Crantor confirmed its veracity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, it’s evident that based on this text is absolutely no justification for conclusions such as Otto Muck’s “Crantor came to Sais and saw there in the temple of Neith the column, completely covered with hieroglyphs, on which the history of Atlantis was recorded. Scholars translated it for him, and he testified that their account fully agreed with Plato’s account of Atlantis”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:muck&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:muck&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;library-of-history-by-diodoros-of-sicily&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt; by Diodoros of Sicily&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diodoros’ &lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt; is remarkable for many reasons. This 40-volume book (of which only 15 books surive intact) is considered one of the earliest attempts at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_history&quot;&gt;Universal history&lt;/a&gt; and also it is notably more detached from ‘Hellenocentric’ world-view&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:usher&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:usher&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  It’s also a major source of our knowledge about Alexander the Great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we need to remember that Diodoros still relied on Greek tradition and historians and he was almost certainly familiar with Plato’s work.  What’s interesting though is that he doesn’t seem to even acknowledge Plato’s story and even disagrees on many details (notably mythical genealogy of Atlas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First mention is in volume in (III. 53)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:diodoros&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:diodoros&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Diodoros, many generations before the Trojan War, the Atlanteans, the most civilized people of their time, became subjected to the Libyan Amazons (author emphasises that this a different tribe, not the more famous one, living along river Thermodon).  He places these Amazons’ land to an island in Lake Tritonis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This island mentioned was of great size and full of fruit-bearing trees of every kind, from which the natives secured their food.  It also contained multitude of flocks, goats, sheeps, […]. But grain the nation used not at all because the use of this fruit of the earth had not yet been discovered among them.  The Amazons, then, the account continues, being a race superior in valour and eager for war, first of all subdued all the cities on the island except one called Menê, which was considered to be sacred[…] (III. 53. 3-6)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their city was called Cherronesus [Penninsula] after it’s shape.  Now, enter Atlantians:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…]the most civilized men among the inhabitants of those regions, who dwelt in a prosperous country and possessed great cities; it was among them, we are told, that mythology places the birth of the gods. (III. 54)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their first king had been Uranus, a god who had elevated them from the bestial state and had taught them agriculture (Book III, 56, 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, Amazons attacked and conquered major Atlantian city called Cernê and Atlantians became subjected and that’s the last time their history was mentioned.  This is what Diodoros said of Atlantians.  Not a word about its conquest neighboring nations or about the time and circumstances of the cataclysm that should have destroyed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, where does &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; version of the story come from?  Diodoros is very clear about that.  Before beginning the story of Amazons and Atlantians, he credits “Dionysius, who composed a narrative about Argonauts and Dionysus, and also about many other things which took place in the most ancient times.” (III. 52) (Note: Dionysus’ version of Argonauts is also quite different from the ‘classic’ version you probably know)  This Dionysius Scytobrachion, often identified with Dionysus of Miletus, is believed to live in 2nd century BC in Alexandria, Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;see-also-phoenicians-in-america&quot;&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/phoenicians-in-america&quot;&gt;Phoenicians in America&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-world&quot;&gt;New World&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some later christian scholars who seem to interpret Atlantis as real were Eusebius, Philo or Kosmas Indikopleustés (who by the way scorned the view of spherical Earth calling it “pagan lies”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big resurrection of the idea came with Age of Discovery.  The Spanish historian Fracisco López de Gómara (c. 1511-c. 1566) seems to be the first to believe that Plato’s Atlantis was referring to America.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gomara&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gomara&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exception to this sentiment provides Jesuit Father Athanasius Kircher (1601-1680), who pictures Atlantis as a separate landmass between Europe and America in an illustration to his book &lt;em&gt;Mundus Subterraneus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:kircher&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:kircher&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/i/Atlantis/Kircher.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Map of Atlantis from Mundus Subterraneus&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;Map of Atlantis from Mundus Subterraneus &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Francis Bacon (1561-1626)  his unfinished utopian novel &lt;em&gt;The New Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:bacon&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:bacon&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  He talks about an island called Bensalem, whose people, ancestors to bigger sialdn New Atlantis located even further west, were of a high moral character, modesty, christian faith and scientific inquiry.  Some then-futuristic technologies like flying machines, submarines, weather control, etc. are described.  However, this book is clearly a Christian utopian novel and nothing suggests it was ever intended to be taken literally, however it might play some role in cementing the idea of Atlantis as an utopian, advanced society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later theory was Mayanism, which connected Atlantis with Mayan and other indigenous American cultures.  Early proponents of this belief were Charles Étienne Brasseur de Bourbourg (1814-1874) and Augustus Le Plongeon (1825-1908) who seems to be the first to theorize that Atlantis was ancestral to ancient Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-age&quot;&gt;New Age&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During 19th century, the theory shifted into more fringe territory and it was molded to fit various Christian, New Age and even Nazi beliefs.  Also, only now does most of the supernatural claims start to appear.  Major figures were Ignatius L. Donnelly, Helena Blavatsky and Edgar Cayce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignatius L. Donnelly (1831-1901) is probably the reason why this myth became so widely known.  He was probably inspired by Mayanism, but he saw Atlantis as an actual lost continent in the Atlantic sea, which disappeared in a flood.  He also originated quite a few original claims, which are still perpetuated until today.  To name a few, Atlantis was the region where man first rose from barbarians [sic] to civilization.  From there the civilization was distributed to all ancient civilizations around the world.  Gods of Greeks, Phoenicians, Hindus, etc. were simply kings, queens and heroes of Atlantis.  From all colonies, religions of Egypt and Peru were the closest representations of the original religion of Atlanteans.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:donnelly&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:donnelly&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This video summarizes all 13 hypotheses that Donnelly is trying to prove: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aP9xOcZ9AN4&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Book Review: Atlantis: The Antediluvian World, by Ignatius L. Donnelly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (youtube.com)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helena Blavatsky (1831-1891), a Russian mystic and founder of the Theosophical Society.  Despite claiming that she was given access to “secret wisdom” in Tibet, she repeated many claims of Donelly, mainly concerning and further elaborating on the idea of “progenitor race” (first very briefly proposed in &lt;em&gt;Isis Unveiled&lt;/em&gt;).  In her next book, &lt;em&gt;The Secret Doctrine&lt;/em&gt;, she tells much more about Atlantis.  Tibetan masters revelaled to her that Atlantians were only the fourth of seven “root races”, following i.a. Hyperboreans and Lemurians.  Fifth “root race” is the “Aryan race” and sixth and seventh have yet to be.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:blavatsky&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:blavatsky&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  By the way, this unscientific race theory could be one of the contributing factors to forming of Nazi ideology.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:nazis&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:nazis&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  But, of course, Blavatsky was in no way responsible for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Blavatsky attributed her knowledge to “sacred wisdom” bestowed upon her by Ascended Masters, Edgar Cayce (1877-1945) wasn’t even trying to hide the fact that the knowledge of Atlantis came to him through his psychic abilities.  But it can be demonstrated that he must have been familiar with works of Donnelly, Blavatsky and probably other theosophists.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cayce&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cayce&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  In regard to Atlantis, he originates plethora of claims. Atlanteans migrated to Egypt after the disaster and that their &lt;em&gt;History of Records&lt;/em&gt; is still hidden under the Sphinx (likely inspired by Paul Chrisitan’s &lt;em&gt;Histoire De La Magie&lt;/em&gt;) and also “in another [place] in the Aryan or Yucatan land”.  He also made many claims concerning crystal technology, capability of flying and moving through water, telepathy, etc.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cayce2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cayce2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (probably inspired by Bacon)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;modern-times&quot;&gt;Modern times&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 20th century, the Continental drift hypothesis started to gain acceptance, which offered new possible explanations for Atlantis believers.  More recently, the myth was one again revived by new discoveries about catastrophic events during Younger Dryas period.  This is still fresh stuff, so it naturally captures minds of ancient history enthusiasts who often see it as a solution to all the flood myths of ancient cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of proponents of this “scientific stream” don’t seem to acknowledge the supposed esoteric and advanced technology proposed by New Age authors, some ideas persist.  Mainly connection to native Americans, Eyptians and other early civilizations - basically the idea of progenitor race, but stripped of all the Aryan connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there’s very little doubt, that catastrophic events like Mega floods and meteor strikes did happen in relatively short period and might greatly influence human population of that time, that itself doesn’t imply that some great civilization was destroyed by it.  Morever, archeological evidence of any bronze culture in neolothic is still lacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most prominent scientific hypothesies, which don’t mention anything in regard to Atlantis but somehow tie into the “progenitor civilization” theory, are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Younger_Dryas_impact_hypothesis&quot;&gt;YD impact hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;  and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sphinx_water_erosion_hypothesis&quot;&gt;Sphinx water erosion hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;.  Graham Hancock also mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orion_correlation_theory&quot;&gt;Orion correlation theory&lt;/a&gt; in BBC documentary &lt;em&gt;Atlantis Reborn Again&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest “canditate”, propagated mainly by youtube channel Bright Insight, is the Richat Structure in Mauretania.  Claims of this video are thoroughly analyzed by an actual historian in two videos from another youtube channel, World of Antiquity.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:woa1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:woa1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:woa2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:woa2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be also noted, that some academics propose that the destruction of Atlantis was inspired by explosion of volcano on Santorini (c. 1600 BC).  Louis Guillaume Figuier (1819-1984) was the first to suggest a link between the Theran explosion and Plato’s Atlantis.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:figuier&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:figuier&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Supporters of this theory note that Minoans were a significant naval power and they could be seen as ancestors of Greeks by Egyptians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many other locations were proposed: Bermuda Triangle (Charles Berlitz), Doñana National Park (Bruce Blackburn), Great Meteor Seamount, Azores, Black Sea, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reagard to these efforts, writer L. Sprague de Camp fittingly noted in his book “Lost Continents,” “You cannot change all the details of Plato’s story and still claim to have Plato’s story. That is like saying the legendary King Arthur is ‘really’ Cleopatra; all you have to do is to change Cleopatra’s sex, nationality, time period, temperament, moral character, and other details, and the resemblance becomes obvious.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:timaeus&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.499834/page/n31/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Plato, &lt;em&gt;Timaeus And Critias&lt;/em&gt;, 6th century BC, English translation, 1929&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:timaeus&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gen_proclus&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/timaeusofplato00platiala/page/64/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Archer-hind, R. D. &lt;em&gt;The Timaeus of Plato&lt;/em&gt;,  1888&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gen_proclus&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gen_burnet&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/burnetsgreekphil00burnuoft/page/350/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Burnet, John. &lt;em&gt;Greek Philosophy I&lt;/em&gt;, 1914&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gen_burnet&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:strabo&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/Strabo08Geography17AndIndex/Strabo%2001%20Geography%201-2/page/n425/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Strabo. &lt;em&gt;Geography&lt;/em&gt;, 1st century AD, English translation, 1917&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:strabo&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:franke&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Franke, Thorwald C. &lt;em&gt;Aristotle and Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;, English translation, 2012 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:franke&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:proclus&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/proclusontimaeus01procuoft/page/64&quot;&gt;Proclus, &lt;em&gt;Commentary on Plato’s Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, 4th century AD, English translation, 1820&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:proclus&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:muck&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Muck, Otto. &lt;em&gt;The Secret of Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;, English translation, 1981 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:muck&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:usher&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/historiansofgree00ushe/page/234/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Usher, Stephen. &lt;em&gt;The Historians of Greece and Rome&lt;/em&gt;, p. 235, 1970&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:usher&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:diodoros&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/DiodorosOfSicily034.598/Diodoros%20of%20Sicily%2002%20%282.35-4.58%29/page/n253/mode/1up&quot;&gt;Diodoros of Sicily, &lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt;, 1st century BC, English translation, 1933&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:diodoros&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gomara&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.cz/books?pg=PA337&amp;amp;ei=J5C_T4nHF6SN6QGGn_nOCg&amp;amp;id=VHoKAQAAIAAJ&quot;&gt;de Gómara, Francisco López. &lt;em&gt;Historia general de las Indias&lt;/em&gt;, 1552&lt;/a&gt; (Google Books) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gomara&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:kircher&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/mundussubterrane02kirc/page/n123/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Kircher, Athanasius. &lt;em&gt;Mundus Subterraneus&lt;/em&gt;, 1678&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:kircher&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:bacon&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bacon, Francis. &lt;em&gt;The New Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;, Francis Bacon, 1627. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:bacon&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:donnelly&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/atlantisantedilu00donnuoft/page/x/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Donnelly, Ingatius L. &lt;em&gt;Atlantis: the antediluvian world&lt;/em&gt;, 1882&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:donnelly&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:blavatsky&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/secretdoctrine01unkngoog/page/n10/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Blavatsky, Helena. &lt;em&gt;The Secret Doctrine&lt;/em&gt;, 1917&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:blavatsky&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:nazis&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.haaretz.com/jewish/holocaust-remembrance-day/.premium-the-dark-link-between-nazis-and-atlantis-1.6870036&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dark Link Between the Nazis and the Legend of Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (haaretz.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:nazis&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cayce&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Johnson, Paul K. &lt;em&gt;Edgar Cayce in Context: The Readings, Truth and Fiction&lt;/em&gt;, 1998 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cayce&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cayce2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bibliotecapleyades.net/esp_cayce_3.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edgar Cayce’s Atlantis Readings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (bibliotecapleyades.net) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cayce2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:woa1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BqhMGVLUSB0&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;THE LOST CITY OF ATLANTIS: What researchers get WRONG about Plato’s famous legend&lt;/em&gt;, World of Antiquity, 2019&lt;/a&gt; (youtube.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:woa1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:woa2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;ATLANTIS: The TRUTH about the Richat Hypothesis&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;ATLANTIS: The TRUTH about the Richat Hypothesis&lt;/em&gt;, World of Antiquity, 2019&lt;/a&gt; (youtube.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:woa2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:figuier&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k22526x&quot;&gt;Figuier, Louis. &lt;em&gt;La Terre et les Mers&lt;/em&gt;, 1872&lt;/a&gt; (bnf.fr) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:figuier&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
