<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Dubious History</title>
 <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2021-03-03T00:29:41+01:00</updated>
 <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Pîrî Reis Map of 1513</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/piri-reis-map-of-1513"/>
   <updated>2021-02-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/piri-reis-map-of-1513</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The map drawn by an admiral of Ottoman Empire Muhyi-iddin Pîrî &lt;em&gt;re‘is&lt;/em&gt; (a military rank) dated to 1513 CE is well known in the fringe literature, mainly for it’s alleged depiction of Antarctica coastline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was featured on the &lt;em&gt;Ancient Aliens&lt;/em&gt; and it’s often brought by Graham Hancock&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hancock&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hancock&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, among others, as a proof of ancient civilization or technology we’re not yet aware of, as the first modern mapping of Antarctica wasn’t done until 19th century.  The argument is that Pîrî himself must have drawn from older, more ancient maps, which ties it into the general notion of ancient civilization theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an undeniable fact, that the precision of this map is astounding for it’s time.  Made only 20 years after the Discovery, it is the most precise depiction of Brazilian coastline from this period.  Try to compare with other contemporary maps like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waldseem%C3%BCller_map&quot;&gt;Waldseemüller map&lt;/a&gt; from 1507 or even three decades older &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thedigitalgallery.org/images/255&quot;&gt;Sebastian Müster map&lt;/a&gt;.  However, there are numerous misconceptions about this map which I think need be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/overlay.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Overlay on a modern map&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite Pîrî being a well-known and studied figure in Turkish history, the discovery of the map came surprisingly late.  It was discovered by the Director of National Museums, Halil Etem Edhem only in 1929, when the Topkapı Palace in Istanbul was repurposed into a museum.  It seems to be just a fraction of a bigger map.  Apart from numerous illustrations of ships, animals and even mythical creatures, and more than a hundred of place-names (mostly corresponding with other contemporary portolan maps), it also features many inscriptions written mainly in Turkish.  There are about thirty of them and English translations are available online.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:translation&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:translation&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By far the largest inscription, placed over the South America inland, says following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These coasts are named the shores of Antilia. They were discovered in the year 896 of the Arab calendar [1491 CE]. But it is reported thus, that a Genoese infidel, his name was Colombo, who discovered these places. For instance, a book fell into the hands of the said Colombo, and he found it said in this book that at the end of the Western Sea [Atlantic] that is, on its western side, there were coasts and islands and all kinds of metals and also precious stones. Colombo, having studied this book thoroughly, explained these matters one by one to the greats of Genoa [Italy] and said: “Come, give me two ships, let me go and find these places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The above-mentioned Colombo saw that no help was forthcoming from the Genoese, he sped forth, went to the Bey of Spain [king], and told his tale in detail. They too answered like the Genoese. In brief Colombo petitioned these people for a long time, finally the Bey of Spain gave him two ships[…]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This passage is very interesting in context of our generally accepted notion that Colombo was simply trying to find an alternative route to Asia.  According to Pîrî, there was a book which taught Colombo about the undiscovered shores.  However, Colombo might still &lt;em&gt;interpret&lt;/em&gt; that as the east coast of Asia.  This could also refer to Pierre d’Ailly’s &lt;em&gt;Imago Mundi&lt;/em&gt;, which was in Colombo’s possession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lower part of the same text elaborates more on the source material:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No one now living has seen a map like this. I have composed and constructed it using about twenty maps and mappaemundi; these are the maps which were composed in the time of Alexander of the Two Horns, and which show the inhabited portion of the earth. The Arabs call these maps ja’fariya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have used eight ja’fariya maps, an Arab map of India and four recent Portuguese maps - these maps show the sea of Sind, India and China according to mathematical principles - and also a map of the western regions drawn by Colombo. The final farm was arrived at by reducing all these maps to the same scale. Therefore the present map is as accurate for the Seven Seas as the maps of our own countries used by sailors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;antarctica&quot;&gt;Antarctica&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to the lowest part of the map, often doubtlessly identified with Antarctica coastline, there are two inscriptions which say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And in this country it seems that there are white-haired monsters in this shape, and also six-horned oxen. The Portuguese infidels have written it in their maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This country is a waste. Everything is in ruin and it is said that large snakes are found here. For this reason the Portuguese infidels did not land on these shores and these are also said to be very hot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave that to reader to decide how likely it is that these lands refer to Antarctica. In any case, it’s clear that Pîrî was relying on Portuguese precedents for this part of the map, not from some lost ancient maps as it’s often claimed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that map actually depicts Antarctica coastline seems to originate with captain Arlington Humphrey Mallery in c. 1956.  In addition to being a captain, he was an amateur archaeologist who believed that North America had been extensively colonised by Celts, Vikings and other Old World peoples, who possessed accurate maps lost to later ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mallery’s accounts apparently inspired Charles Hapgood, famous mainly for his now discredited Polar shift theory, who argued that Pîrî’s map and others are a proof of a lost ancient civilization Hapgood’s book show his correspondence with USAF Lt. Colonel Harold Z. Ohlmeyer, who agreed with Hapgood that &lt;em&gt;“this is the most logical and in all probability the correct interpretation of the map”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“lower part of the map agrees very remarkably with the results of the seismic profile made across the top of the ice-cap by the Swedish-British Antarctic Expedition of 1949”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“we have no idea how the data on this map can be reconciled with the supposed state of geographical knowledge in 1513.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hapgood&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hapgood&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/hapgood.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hapgood’s interpretation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are several problems with Hapgood’s hypotheses.  The map does not show Drake’s Passage or the Pacific Ocean. Also, what Hapgood identifies as the Andes mountains are not located along a coast line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theory was later revived by Erich von Däniken in his &lt;em&gt;Chariots of the Gods?&lt;/em&gt;, where he basically just reiterated Hapgood’s claims within his own context of Ancient Aliens hypothesis.  He says that “the only explanation is that it must have been made by extraterrestrials, either at an early date when Antarctica was indeed free from ice or because their technology revealed the underlying surface.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:daniken&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:daniken&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another proponent of this view is above mentioned Graham Hancock, who also adds that one the islands depicts the “Bimini Road”, which Hapgood identified as Cuba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/bimini_road.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;An island which according to Hancock depicts Bimini Road&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, serious scholarship holds that there is no reason to believe that the map is the product of genuine knowledge of the Antarctic coast.  General belief is that it actually depicts the South American coastline, just heavily distorted.  This distortion could be caused by an error, motivated by the weird shape of the parchment, or even for political reasons.  This well constructed argument is proposed by Diego Cuoghi on his website, where he doesn’t rely only on correlation of geography, but also on historical arguments and comparison with other historical maps.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cuoghi&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cuoghi&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/piri_brazil.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Correlation with SA coastline according to Diego Cuoghi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speculation alert:&lt;/strong&gt; Could this identification with Tierra del Fuego explain the “shores that are said to be very hot”?  Yes, Magellan officially coined the name in 1525, but maybe some relation with fire was already present before?  He apparently knew about the strait before he set out, as “he saw it, in the Treasury of the King of Portugal, on a map drawn by Martin de Bohemia” (Pigafetta).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, let’s not toss out the possibility that although the map does state the year of it’s creation, it some portions could be drawn later.  As Cuoghi states, we know that the chart of Pedro Reinel, kept in the same Library of Topkapı, was probably retouched after the discovery of the Strait of Magellan, so it wouldn’t be unprecedented.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cuoghi:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cuoghi&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cryptozoology&quot;&gt;Cryptozoology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting thing that is often overlooked are the illustrations of animals and fantastical creatures.  Apart from above-mentioned large snakes, white-haired monsters mentioned in the inscriptions, the map also features an unicorn, monkey dancing with what looks to be a dog-headed man, and a head-less creature reminiscent of &lt;em&gt;blemmyes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/dancing_beasts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;“In the mountains of this territory were creatures like this and human beings came out on the seacoast. The gold mines are endless.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/blemmye.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;“These monsters are seven spans long. The space between their eyes is one span, but they are harmless souls.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These fantastic creatures had already occasionally been depicted in medieval &lt;em&gt;mappae mundi&lt;/em&gt; and many of them were associated with either Africa or Asia.  De La Cosa’s map (1500) also shows &lt;em&gt;blemmye&lt;/em&gt; and a dog-headed man in the Far East, in the approximate location of China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Pîrî Reis they are also found on the chart of Guillaume Le Testu (1555) and associated with the New World on the map of Sebastian Cabot (1544) and that of Guiana by de Bry (1599).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:masseti&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:masseti&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hancock&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qt2GYyGTXTs&quot;&gt;Graham Hancock’s summary of the argument on &lt;em&gt;The Mysterious Origins of Man&lt;/em&gt; TV program.&lt;/a&gt; (youtube.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hancock&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:translation&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://turkeyinmaps.com/piri.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Piri Reis Map of 1513 (translations)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (turkeyinmaps.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:translation&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hapgood&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maps of the Ancient Sea Kings&lt;/em&gt;, Charles H. Hapgood, 1966. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hapgood&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:daniken&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chariots of the Gods?&lt;/em&gt;, Erich von Däniken, 1968. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:daniken&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cuoghi&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diegocuoghi.com/Piri_Reis/PiriReis_eng.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Mysteries of the Piri Reis Map&lt;/em&gt;, Diego Cuoghi&lt;/a&gt; (diegocuoghi.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cuoghi&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cuoghi:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:masseti&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sciencepress.mnhn.fr/en/periodiques/anthropozoologica/51/1/les-representations-zoomorphiques-de-la-carte-de-piri-reis-1513&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The zoomorphic representations of the Pîrî Reis map (1513)&lt;/em&gt;, Marco Masseti &amp;amp; Cecilia Veracini, 2016&lt;/a&gt; (mnhn.fr) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:masseti&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Atlantis - myths about the myth</title>
   <link href="https://dubioushistory.github.io/atlantis"/>
   <updated>2021-01-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://dubioushistory.github.io/atlantis</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The myth of Atlantis probably doesn’t require much introduction.  The mythical lost civilization and its island has generated speculations in countless books since Plato first mentioned it in 5th century BC, even capturing attention of famous thinkers like Isaac Newton or Francis Bacon.  It branched into many different beliefs about its true location, linking Atlantis with Crete, Sardinia, America, Antarctica, Iberian Peninsula, Mauritania and many, many other places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several years’ dormancy in imagination of the broader public, it has begun to make something of a comeback in recent years, partly driven by recent discoveries about Younger Dryas period and ancient settlements like Göbekli Tepe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most skeptical-minded articles focus on debunking of the idea itself or some specific claims, I am trying to trace the most repeated claims to their original source and show how the perception of the myth evolved through time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of building an argument, my goal is to gather &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; sources, make as little active claims as possible, and let the reader form his own opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;origin---platos-timaeus-and-critias&quot;&gt;Origin - Plato’s &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Critias&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a speaker in Plato’s &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, a character called Critias states that he heard the Atlantis tale from his grandfather Critias the elder, who heard it from Solon.  Solon, famous Greek statesman who lived two centuries before, allegedly acquired the story in Egypt and “brought it back with him” to Athens, with intentions to adapt it into an epic poem later, which he left unfinished. (&lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, p. 17)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:timaeus&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:timaeus&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;CRITIAS: [It’s a story that] Solon, the wisest of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seven_Sages_of_Greece&quot;&gt;wise seven&lt;/a&gt;, once declared. Solon, who, you must know, was, as he says in several places in his poems, a kinsman and a close friend of my great-grandfather Dropides, told my grandfather Critias (so the Critias in his turn, used to repeat the story to me in his old age), that there are great and splendid ancient exploits of our city which have been forgotten from lapse of time and decay of population, and, in particular, one, the greatest of all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right away, we have a problem.  There are several contradicting interpretations of the genealogy described by Plato.  However, it’s certain that in the time the dialogue was written, Solon must had been dead for at least 150 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Atlantis/proclus.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Atlantis/birnet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interpretation of Proclus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gen_proclus&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gen_proclus&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interpretation of classicist John Burnet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gen_burnet&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gen_burnet&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regard to Atlantis, here are some main takeaways from &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt; (p. 17 - 23):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Athens was inhabited 9,000 ago by Athenians, it was country “foremost both in war and all besides” before it’s destruction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Atlantis was an island with its own kings ruling over many other islands as well as mainland colonies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Located “before Pillars of Heracles” in Atlantic ocean, “larger than Libya and Asia together”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Atlanteans were wealthy and powerful, and set to subjugate all other nations. Athenians revolted and “vanquished the invaders”, even freeing some of their colonies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But layer, great earth-quakes and floods sunk the Atlantis (and drown all Athenian warriors as well).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Plato’s later work, &lt;em&gt;Critias&lt;/em&gt;, things get a bit more interesting (pages 116 - end):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Island of Atlantis was Poseidon’s “lot”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He carved the mountain into a palace and enclosed it with three circular moats.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Poseidon’s temple was in the inner ring and “forbidden to enter”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Poseidon took liking in an orphaned girl.  She gave him ten sons, who later ruled 10 parts of Atlantis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rich fauna and flora, including plentiful of elephants and many fruits and flowers (including ones exuding “gums”), which Atlanteans utilized for their sustenance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gold-red metal called Orichalcum was mined in many parts of Atlantis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apart from the capital city, “mountains contained numerous villages with a wealthy population”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First king of Altantis, Atlas, had a twin brother who ruled region now known as Gadeira (Cádiz). (Note: Later, Strabo and Diodoros attribute foundation of this city to Phoenicians, which even archaeology nowadays seem to confirm)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering that Plato invented Atlantis for the sake of a political allegory, it can seem quite intriguing that so much detail is provided regarding things like geography, natural resources, agricultural practices, etc. before turning focus to society itself.  Then again, we can’t simply ignore that the same amount of detail is provided also for Athens in the same period, which the archeology evidence doesn’t support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that’s pretty much it.  As you can see, there are absolutely no implications of advanced technology or superior esoteric knowledge.  From all descriptions (apart from the dating and mythology, of course), they seem like pretty believable, though remarkably wealthy and powerful, Bronze Age civilization.  They armed themselves with spears and shields, they conquered barbaric lands and they waged war against Athenians, which they lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I highly recommend reading the whole book, though.  It’s is not that long and it really makes you realize, that the whole Atlantis story is only a small part of Plato’s great legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bonus-solon-in-egypt&quot;&gt;BONUS: Solon in Egypt?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting all claims about Atlantis aside, even the claim that Solon actually travelled to Egypt in the first place is contested.  The first mention of this, apart from Plato’s story of course, comes from Herodotus’ &lt;em&gt;The Histories&lt;/em&gt; (c. 440 BC), some 200 years after Solon’s passing and &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; Platon’s &lt;em&gt;Timeas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Critias&lt;/em&gt; was already well known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there are many inconsistencies in Herodotus’ accounts on Solon’s travel and another story about his travel to Lydia is widely believed to be unhistorical.  However, the idea that Solon could visit Egypt roughly in the specified time is not really preposterous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interpretations-throughout-the-history&quot;&gt;Interpretations throughout the history&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait. So, shouldn’t the story end here?  For many it does.  However, the debate about Atlantis is almost as old as the myth itself.  So how was the story perceived in the ancient times?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;strabo-and-aristotle&quot;&gt;Strabo (and Aristotle?)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantis&quot;&gt;wikipedia page on Atlantis&lt;/a&gt; claims, that Aristotle believed that Plato, his teacher, had invented the island to teach philosophy.  As a source, a 1967 article from &lt;em&gt;Galaxy Science Fiction&lt;/em&gt; magazine, is provided. Itself completely unsourced. (Note: Without taking any sides, it’s always important to be &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; careful with accepting claims you read on Wikipedia and where they come from)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what’s the real story?  As always, it’s complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument comes from Strabo’s &lt;em&gt;Geography&lt;/em&gt;.  Strabo (c.60 BC- C.20 BC) endorses Poseidonius’ (c. 135 BC-c.50 BC) view that Atlantis might be more than mere fiction and dismisses argument that “Its inventor caused it to disappear, just as did the Poet the wall of the Acheans.” (Implying &lt;strong&gt;Solon&lt;/strong&gt; avoided the historical consequences of his fiction by sinking Atlantis, just as Homer did by making Poseidon and Apollo sweep away with a flood the wall built by the Achaeans. (Strabo 2.3.6&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:strabo&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:strabo&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does Aristotle come in?  Well, in chapter 13.1.36 in a passage completely unrelated to Atlantis, this quote is referenced again, this time attributed to Aristotle.  This lead some to conclude that first appearance of quote does indeed reflect Aristotle’s opinion on Atlantis.  This is disputed in generally well received book &lt;em&gt;Aristotle and Atlantis&lt;/em&gt; by T. C. Franke&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:franke&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:franke&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;commentary-on-platos-timaeus-by-proclus&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Commentary on Plato’s Timaeus&lt;/em&gt; by Proclus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosopher Crantor (c. 3rd century BC), a student of Plato’s student Xenocrates, is often cited as an example of a writer who thought the story to be historical fact.  His work, a commentary on &lt;em&gt;Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, is however lost and all our information come from commentary on his work from 5th century by Neoplatonist Proclus (more than 600 years after life of Crantor) In regard to Atlantis story, he reports&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:proclus&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:proclus&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With respect for the whole of this narration about the Atlantics, some say, that it is a mere history, which was the opinion of Crantor, the first interpreter of Plato, who says, that Plato was derided by those of his time, as not being the inventor of the Republic, but transcribing what the Egyptians had written on this subject; and that he so far regards what is said by these deriders as to refer to the Egyptians this history about the Athenians and Atlantics, and to believe that the Athenians once lived conformably to this polity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[He] adds, that this is testified by the prophets of the Egyptians, who assert that these particulars [which are narrated by Plato] are written on pillars which are still preserved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve put ‘He’ in brackets, because some translations say it was Crantor, who confirms the story (see 1820 English translation in Sources) but Greek original uses ambiguous ‘He’, which leaves room for speculations that it was Plato himself who verified the story with Egyptians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever you lean towards, all we can safely state is that according to 5th CE century Greek Neoplatonist philosopher, Plato, facing ridicule, made attempts to verify the story with Egyptians and either Plato or Crantor confirmed its veracity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I hope it’s evident that based on this text is absolutely no justification for conclusions such as Otto Muck’s “Crantor came to Sais and saw there in the temple of Neith the column, completely covered with hieroglyphs, on which the history of Atlantis was recorded. Scholars translated it for him, and he testified that their account fully agreed with Plato’s account of Atlantis”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:muck&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:muck&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;library-of-history-by-diodoros-of-sicily&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt; by Diodoros of Sicily&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diodoros’ &lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt; is remarkable for many reasons. This 40-volume book (of which only 15 books surive intact) is considered one of the earliest attempts at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_history&quot;&gt;Universal history&lt;/a&gt; and also it is notably more detached from ‘Hellenocentric’ world-view&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:usher&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:usher&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  It’s also a major source of our knowledge about Alexander the Great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we need to remember that Diodoros still relied on Greek tradition and historians and he was almost certainly familiar with Plato’s work.  What’s interesting though is that he doesn’t seem to even acknowledge Plato’s story and even disagrees on many details (notably mythical genealogy of Atlas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First mention is in volume in (III. 53)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:diodoros&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:diodoros&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Diodoros, many generations before the Trojan War, the Atlanteans, the most civilized people of their time, became subjected to the Libyan Amazons (author emphasises that this a different tribe, not the more famous one, living along river Thermodon).  He places these Amazons’ land to an island in Lake Tritonis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This island mentioned was of great size and full of fruit-bearing trees of every kind, from which the natives secured their food.  It also contained multitude of flocks, goats, sheeps, […]. But grain the nation used not at all because the use of this fruit of the earth had not yet been discovered among them.  The Amazons, then, the account continues, being a race superior in valour and eager for war, first of all subdued all the cities on the island except one called Menê, which was considered to be sacred[…] (III. 53. 3-6)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their city was called Cherronesus [Penninsula] after it’s shape.  Now, enter Atlantians:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…]the most civilized men among the inhabitants of those regions, who dwelt in a prosperous country and possessed great cities; it was among them, we are told, that mythology places the birth of the gods. (III. 54)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their first king had been Uranus, a god who had elevated them from the bestial state and had taught them agriculture (Book III, 56, 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, Amazons attacked and conquered major Atlantian city called Cernê and Atlantians became subjected and that’s the last time their history was mentioned.  This is what Diodoros said of Atlantians.  Not a word about its conquest neighboring nations or about the time and circumstances of the cataclysm that should have destroyed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, where does &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; version of the story come from?  Diodoros is very clear about that.  Before beginning the story of Amazons and Atlantians, he credits “Dionysius, who composed a narrative about Argonauts and Dionysus, and also about many other things which took place in the most ancient times.” (III. 52) (Note: Dionysus’ version of Argonauts is also quite different from the ‘classic’ version you probably know)  This Dionysius Scytobrachion, often identified with Dionysus of Miletus, is believed to live in 2nd century BC in Alexandria, Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See also:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Phoenicians in America&lt;/strong&gt; (coming soon)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-world&quot;&gt;New World&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some later christian scholars who seem to interpret Atlantis as real were Eusebius, Philo or Kosmas Indikopleustés (who by the way scorned the view of spherical Earth calling it “pagan lies”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big resurrection of the idea came with Age of Discovery.  The Spanish historian Fracisco López de Gómara (c. 1511-c. 1566) seems to be the first to believe that Plato’s Atlantis was referring to America.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gomara&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gomara&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exception to this sentiment provides Jesuit Father Athanasius Kircher (1601-1680), who pictures Atlantis as a separate landmass between Europe and America in an illustration to his book &lt;em&gt;Mundus Subterraneus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:kircher&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:kircher&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/Atlantis/Kircher.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Map of Atlantis from Mundus Subterraneus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sir Francis Bacon (1561-1626)  his unfinished utopian novel &lt;em&gt;The New Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:bacon&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:bacon&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  He talks about an island called Bensalem, whose people, ancestors to bigger sialdn New Atlantis located even further west, were of a high moral character, modesty, christian faith and scientific inquiry.  Some then-futuristic technologies like flying machines, submarines, weather control, etc. are described.  However, this book is clearly a Christian utopian novel and nothing suggests it was ever intended to be taken literally - and I’m not aware of anyone who actually does, however it might play some role in cementing the idea of Atlantis as an utopian, advanced society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later theory was Mayanism, which connected Atlantis with Mayan and other indigenous American cultures.  Early proponents of this belief were Charles Étienne Brasseur de Bourbourg (1814-1874) and Augustus Le Plongeon (1825-1908) who seems to be the first to theorize that Atlantis was ancestral to ancient Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-age&quot;&gt;New Age&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During 19th century, the theory shifted into more fringe territory and it was molded to fit various Christian, New Age and even Nazi beliefs.  Also, only now does most of the supernatural claims start to appear.  Major figures were Ignatius L. Donnelly, Helena Blavatsky and Edgar Cayce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignatius L. Donnelly (1831-1901) is probably the reason why this myth became so widely known.  He was probably inspired by Mayanism, but he saw Atlantis as an actual lost continent in the Atlantic sea, which disappeared in a flood.  He also originated quite a few original claims, which are still perpetuated until today.  To name a few, Atlantis was the region where man first rose from barbarians [sic] to civilization.  From there the civilization was distributed to all ancient civilizations around the world.  Gods of Greeks, Phoenicians, Hindus, etc. were simply kings, queens and heroes of Atlantis.  From all colonies, religions of Egypt and Peru were the closest representations of the original religion of Atlanteans.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:donnelly&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:donnelly&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helena Blavatsky (1831-1891), a Russian mystic and founder of the Theosophical Society.  Despite claiming that she was given access to “secret wisdom” in Tibet, she repeated many claims of Donelly, mainly concerning and further elaborating on the idea of “progenitor race” (first very briefly proposed in &lt;em&gt;Isis Unveiled&lt;/em&gt;).  In her next book, &lt;em&gt;The Secret Doctrine&lt;/em&gt;, she tells much more about Atlantis.  Tibetan masters revelaled to her that Atlantians were only the fourth of seven “root races”, following i.a. Hyperboreans and Lemurians.  Fifth “root race” is the “Aryan race” and sixth and seventh have yet to be.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:blavatsky&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:blavatsky&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  By the way, this unscientific race theory could be one of the contributing factors to forming of Nazi ideology.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:nazis&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:nazis&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  But, of course, I’m not implying that Blavatsky was in any way responsible for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Blavatsky attributed her knowledge to “sacred wisdom” bestowed upon her by Ascended Masters, Edgar Cayce (1877-1945) wasn’t even trying to hide the fact that the knowledge of Atlantis came to him through his psychic abilities.  But it can be demonstrated that he must have been familiar with works of Donnelly, Blavatsky and probably other theosophists.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cayce&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cayce&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  In regard to Atlantis, he originates plethora of claims. Atlanteans migrated to Egypt after the disaster and that their &lt;em&gt;History of Records&lt;/em&gt; is still hidden under the Sphinx (likely inspired by Paul Chrisitan’s &lt;em&gt;Histoire De La Magie&lt;/em&gt;) and also “in another [place] in the Aryan or Yucatan land”.  He also made many claims concerning crystal technology, capability of flying and moving through water, telepathy, etc.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cayce2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cayce2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (probably inspired by Bacon)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;modern-times&quot;&gt;Modern times&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 20th century, the Continental drift hypothesis started to gain acceptance, which offered new possible explanations for Atlantis believers.  More recently, the myth was one again revived by new discoveries about catastrophic events during Younger Dryas period.  This is still fresh stuff, so it naturally captures minds of ancient history enthusiasts who often see it as a solution to all the flood myths of ancient cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of proponents of this “scientific stream” don’t seem to acknowledge the supposed esoteric and advanced technology proposed by New Age authors, some ideas persist.  Mainly connection to native Americans, Eyptians and other early civilizations - basically the idea of progenitor race, but stripped of all the Aryan connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there’s very little doubt, that catastrophic events like Mega floods and meteor strikes did happen in relatively short period and might greatly influence human population of that time, that itself doesn’t imply that some great civilization was destroyed by it.  Morever, archeological evidence of any bronze culture in neolothic is still lacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most prominent scientific hypothesies, which don’t mention anything in regard to Atlantis but somehow tie into the “progenitor civilization” theory, are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Younger_Dryas_impact_hypothesis&quot;&gt;YD impact hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;  and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sphinx_water_erosion_hypothesis&quot;&gt;Sphinx water erosion hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;.  Graham Hancock also mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orion_correlation_theory&quot;&gt;Orion correlation theory&lt;/a&gt; in BBC documentary &lt;em&gt;Atlantis Reborn Again&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latest “canditate”, propagated mainly by youtube channel Bright Insight, is the Richat Structure in Mauretania.  Claims of this video are thoroughly analyzed by an actual historian in two videos from another youtube channel, World of Antiquity.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:woa1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:woa1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:woa2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:woa2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be also noted, that some academics propose that the destruction of Atlantis was inspired by explosion of volcano on Santorini (c. 1600 BC).  Louis Guillaume Figuier (1819-1984) was the first to suggest a link between the Theran explosion and Plato’s Atlantis.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:figuier&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:figuier&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;  Supporters of this theory note that Minoans were a significant naval power and they could be seen as ancestors of Greeks by Egyptians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many other locations were proposed: Bermuda Triangle (Charles Berlitz), Doñana National Park (Bruce Blackburn), Great Meteor Seamount, Azores, Black Sea, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reagard to these efforts, writer L. Sprague de Camp fittingly noted in his book “Lost Continents,” “You cannot change all the details of Plato’s story and still claim to have Plato’s story. That is like saying the legendary King Arthur is ‘really’ Cleopatra; all you have to do is to change Cleopatra’s sex, nationality, time period, temperament, moral character, and other details, and the resemblance becomes obvious.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:timaeus&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.499834/page/n31/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Timaeus And Critias&lt;/em&gt;, Plato, English translation (1929)&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:timaeus&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gen_proclus&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/timaeusofplato00platiala/page/64/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Timaeus of Plato&lt;/em&gt;,  R.D. Archer-Hind, 1888&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gen_proclus&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gen_burnet&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/burnetsgreekphil00burnuoft/page/350/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Greek Philosophy I&lt;/em&gt;, John Burnet, 1914&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gen_burnet&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:strabo&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/Strabo08Geography17AndIndex/Strabo%2001%20Geography%201-2/page/n425/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Geography&lt;/em&gt;, Strabo, English translation (1917)&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:strabo&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:franke&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aristotle and Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;, Thorwald C. Franke, English translation (2012) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:franke&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:proclus&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/proclusontimaeus01procuoft/page/64&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Commentary on Plato’s Timaeus&lt;/em&gt;, Proclus, english translation (1820)&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:proclus&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:muck&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Secret of Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;, Otto Muck, English translation (1981) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:muck&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:usher&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/historiansofgree00ushe/page/234/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Historians of Greece and Rome&lt;/em&gt;, Stephen Usher, p. 235 (1970)&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:usher&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:diodoros&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/DiodorosOfSicily034.598/Diodoros%20of%20Sicily%2002%20%282.35-4.58%29/page/n253/mode/1up&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Library of History&lt;/em&gt;, Diodoros of Sicily, English translation (1933)&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:diodoros&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gomara&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.cz/books?pg=PA337&amp;amp;ei=J5C_T4nHF6SN6QGGn_nOCg&amp;amp;id=VHoKAQAAIAAJ&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Historia general de las Indias&lt;/em&gt;, Francisco López de Gómara (1552)&lt;/a&gt; (Google Books) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gomara&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:kircher&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/mundussubterrane02kirc/page/n123/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mundus Subterraneus&lt;/em&gt;, Athanasius Kircher (1678)&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:kircher&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:bacon&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The New Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;, Francis Bacon (1627). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:bacon&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:donnelly&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/atlantisantedilu00donnuoft/page/x/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atlantis: the antediluvian world&lt;/em&gt;, Ignatius L. Donnelly (1882)&lt;/a&gt; (archive.org) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:donnelly&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:blavatsky&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/secretdoctrine01unkngoog/page/n10/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Secret Doctrine&lt;/em&gt;, Helena Blavatsky (1917)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:blavatsky&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:nazis&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.haaretz.com/jewish/holocaust-remembrance-day/.premium-the-dark-link-between-nazis-and-atlantis-1.6870036&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Dark Link Between the Nazis and the Legend of Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (haaretz.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:nazis&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cayce&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edgar Cayce in Context: The Readings, Truth and Fiction&lt;/em&gt;, Paul K. Johnson (1998) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cayce&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cayce2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bibliotecapleyades.net/esp_cayce_3.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edgar Cayce’s Atlantis Readings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (online) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cayce2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:woa1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BqhMGVLUSB0&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;THE LOST CITY OF ATLANTIS: What researchers get WRONG about Plato’s famous legend&lt;/em&gt;, World of Antiquity (2019)&lt;/a&gt; (youtube.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:woa1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:woa2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;ATLANTIS: The TRUTH about the Richat Hypothesis&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;ATLANTIS: The TRUTH about the Richat Hypothesis&lt;/em&gt;, World of Antiquity (2019)&lt;/a&gt; (youtube.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:woa2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:figuier&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k22526x&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;La Terre et les Mers&lt;/em&gt;, Louis Figuier (1872)&lt;/a&gt; (bnf.fr) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:figuier&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
