<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-02T22:39:09+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Dubious History</title><subtitle>Alternative History under scrutiny</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Piri Reis Map of 1513</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/piri-reis-map-of-1513" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Piri Reis Map of 1513" /><published>2021-02-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/piri-reis-map-of-1513</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/piri-reis-map-of-1513">&lt;p&gt;The map drawn by an admiral of Ottoman Empire Muhyi-iddin Pîrî &lt;em&gt;re‘is&lt;/em&gt; (a military rank) dated to 1513 CE is well known in the fringe literature, mainly for it’s alleged depiction of Antarctica coastline.  It was featured on the &lt;em&gt;Ancient Aliens&lt;/em&gt; and it’s often brought by Graham Hancock&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hancock&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hancock&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, among others, as a proof of ancient civilization or technology we’re not yet aware of, as the first modern mapping of Antarctica wasn’t done until 19th century.  The argument is that Pîrî himself must have been drawn from older, more ancient maps, which ties it into the general notion of ancient civilization theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an undeniable fact, that the precision of this map is astounding for it’s time.  Made only 20 years after the Discovery, it is the most precise depiction of South American coastline from this period.  Try to compare them with other contemporary maps like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waldseem%C3%BCller_map&quot;&gt;Waldseemüller map&lt;/a&gt; from 1507 or even three decades older &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thedigitalgallery.org/images/255&quot;&gt;Sebastian Müster map&lt;/a&gt;.  However, there are numerous misconceptions about this map which I think should be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/overlay.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Overlay on a modern map&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite Pîrî being a well-known and studied figure in Turkish history, the discovery of the map came surprisingly late.  It was discovered by the Director of National Museums, Halil Etem Edhem only in 1929, when the Topkapı Palace in Istanbul was repurposed into a museum.  It seems to be just a fraction of a bigger map.  Apart from numerous illustrations of ships, animals and even mythical creatures, and more than a hundred of place-names (mostly corresponding with other contemporary portolan maps), it also features many inscriptions written mainly in Turkish.  There are about thirty of them and English translations are available online.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:translation&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:translation&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By far the largest inscription, placed over the South America inland, says following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These coasts are named the shores of Antilia. They were discovered in the year 896 of the Arab calendar [1491 CE]. But it is reported thus, that a Genoese infidel, his name was Colombo, who discovered these places. For instance, a book fell into the hands of the said Colombo, and he found it said in this book that at the end of the Western Sea [Atlantic] that is, on its western side, there were coasts and islands and all kinds of metals and also precious stones. Colombo, having studied this book thoroughly, explained these matters one by one to the greats of Genoa [Italy] and said: “Come, give me two ships, let me go and find these places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The above-mentioned Colombo saw that no help was forthcoming from the Genoese, he sped forth, went to the Bey of Spain [king], and told his tale in detail. They too answered like the Genoese. In brief Colombo petitioned these people for a long time, finally the Bey of Spain gave him two ships[…]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This passage is very interesting in context of our generally accepted notion that Colombo was simply trying to find an alternative route to Asia.  According to Pîrî, there was a book which taught Colombo about the undiscovered shores.  However, Colombo might still &lt;em&gt;interpret&lt;/em&gt; that as the east coast of Asia.  This could also refer to Pierre d’Ailly’s &lt;em&gt;Imago Mundi&lt;/em&gt;, which was in Colombo’s possession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lower part of the same text elaborates more on the source material:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No one now living has seen a map like this. I have composed and constructed it using about twenty maps and mappaemundi; these are the maps which were composed in the time of Alexander of the Two Horns, and which show the inhabited portion of the earth. The Arabs call these maps ja’fariya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have used eight ja’fariya maps, an Arab map of India and four recent Portuguese maps - these maps show the sea of Sind, India and China according to mathematical principles - and also a map of the western regions drawn by Colombo. The final farm was arrived at by reducing all these maps to the same scale. Therefore the present map is as accurate for the Seven Seas as the maps of our own countries used by sailors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Kahle, the first scholar to write about the map, suggested that the Caribbean portion of it was based on a map drawn by Columbus himself, just as Pîrî Reis states. If so, this Turkish map is the only evidence we possess for how Columbus visualized his discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;antarctica&quot;&gt;Antarctica&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to the lowest part of the map, often doubtlessly identified with Antarctica coastline, there are two inscriptions which say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And in this country it seems that there are white-haired monsters in this shape, and also six-horned oxen. The Portuguese infidels have written it in their maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This country is a waste. Everything is in ruin and it is said that large snakes are found here. For this reason the Portuguese infidels did not land on these shores and these are also said to be very hot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave that to reader to decide how likely it is that these lands refer to Antarctica. In any case, it’s clear that Pîrî was relying on Portuguese precedents for this part of the map, not from some lost ancient maps as it’s often claimed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that map actually depicts Antarctica coastline seems to originate with captain Arlington Humphrey Mallery in c. 1956.  In addition to being a captain, he was an amateur archaeologist who believed that North America had been extensively colonised by Celts, Vikings and other Old World peoples, who possessed accurate maps lost to later ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mallery’s accounts apparently inspired Charles Hapgood, famous mainly for his now discredited Polar shift theory, who argued that Pîrî’s map and others are a proof of a lost ancient civilization Hapgood’s book show his correspondence with USAF Lt. Colonel Harold Z. Ohlmeyer, who agreed with Hapgood that &lt;em&gt;“this is the most logical and in all probability the correct interpretation of the map”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“lower part of the map agrees very remarkably with the results of the seismic profile made across the top of the ice-cap by the Swedish-British Antarctic Expedition of 1949”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“we have no idea how the data on this map can be reconciled with the supposed state of geographical knowledge in 1513.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:hapgood&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:hapgood&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/hapgood.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hapgood’s interpretation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are several problems with Hapgood’s hypotheses.  The map does not show Drake’s Passage or the Pacific Ocean. Also, what Hapgood identifies as the Andes mountains are not located along a coast line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theory was later revived by Erich von Däniken in his &lt;em&gt;Chariots of the Gods?&lt;/em&gt;, where he basically just reiterated Hapgood’s claims within his own context of Ancient Aliens hypothesis.  He says that “the only explanation is that it must have been made by extraterrestrials, either at an early date when Antarctica was indeed free from ice or because their technology revealed the underlying surface.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:daniken&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:daniken&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another proponent of this view is above mentioned Graham Hancock, who also adds that one the islands depicts the “Bimini Road”, which Hapgood identified as Cuba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/bimini_road.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;An island which according to Hancock depicts Bimini Road&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, serious scholarship holds that there is no reason to believe that the map is the product of genuine knowledge of the Antarctic coast.  General belief is that it actually depicts the South American coastline, just heavily distorted.  This distortion could be caused by an error, motivated by the weird shape of the parchment, or even for political reasons.  Very well constructed argument is proposed by Diego Cuoghi on his website, where he doesn’t rely only on correlation of geography, but also on historical arguments and comparison with other historical maps.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cuoghi&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cuoghi&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/piri_brazil.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Correlation with SA coastline according to Diego Cuoghi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speculation alert:&lt;/strong&gt; Could this identification with Tierra del Fuego explain the “shores that are said to be very hot”?  Yes, Magellan officially coined the name in 1525, but maybe some relation with fire was already present before?  He apparently knew about the strait before he set out, as “he saw it, in the Treasury of the King of Portugal, on a map drawn by Martin de Bohemia” (Pigafetta).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, let’s not toss out the possibility that although the map does state the year of it’s creation, it some portions could be drawn later.  As Cuoghi states, we know that the chart of Pedro Reinel, kept in the same Library of Topkapı, was probably retouched after the discovery of the Strait of Magellan, so it wouldn’t be unprecedented.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cuoghi:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cuoghi&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cryptozoology&quot;&gt;Cryptozoology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting thing that is often overlooked are the illustrations of animals and fantastical creatures.  Apart from above-mentioned large snakes, white-haired monsters mentioned in the inscriptions, the map also features an unicorn, monkey dancing with what looks to be a dog-headed man, and a head-less creature reminiscent of &lt;em&gt;blemmyes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/dancing_beasts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;“In the mountains of this territory were creatures like this and human beings came out on the seacoast. The gold mines are endless.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/i/PiriReis/blemmye.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; /&gt; &lt;em&gt;“These monsters are seven spans long. The space between their eyes is one span, but they are harmless souls.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These fantastic creatures had already occasionally been depicted in medieval &lt;em&gt;mappae mundi&lt;/em&gt; and many of them were associated with either Africa or Asia.  De La Cosa’s map (1500) also shows &lt;em&gt;blemmye&lt;/em&gt; and a dog-headed man in the Far East, in the approximate location of China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Pîrî Reis they are also found on the chart of Guillaume Le Testu (1555) and associated with the New World on the map of Sebastian Cabot (1544) and that of Guiana by de Bry (1599).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:masseti&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:masseti&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hancock&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qt2GYyGTXTs&quot;&gt;Graham Hancock’s summary of the argument on &lt;em&gt;The Mysterious Origins of Man&lt;/em&gt; TV program.&lt;/a&gt; (youtube.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hancock&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:translation&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://turkeyinmaps.com/piri.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Piri Reis Map of 1513 (translations)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (turkeyinmaps.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:translation&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:hapgood&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maps of the Ancient Sea Kings&lt;/em&gt;, Charles H. Hapgood, 1966. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:hapgood&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:daniken&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chariots of the Gods?&lt;/em&gt;, Erich von Däniken, 1968. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:daniken&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cuoghi&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diegocuoghi.com/Piri_Reis/PiriReis_eng.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Mysteries of the Piri Reis Map&lt;/em&gt;, Diego Cuoghi&lt;/a&gt; (diegocuoghi.com) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cuoghi&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cuoghi:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:masseti&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sciencepress.mnhn.fr/en/periodiques/anthropozoologica/51/1/les-representations-zoomorphiques-de-la-carte-de-piri-reis-1513&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The zoomorphic representations of the Pîrî Reis map (1513)&lt;/em&gt;, Marco Masseti &amp;amp; Cecilia Veracini, 2016&lt;/a&gt; (mnhn.fr) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:masseti&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="maps" /><category term="cryptids" /><category term="lost-technology" /><category term="lost-civilization" /><summary type="html">The map drawn by an admiral of Ottoman Empire Muhyi-iddin Pîrî re‘is (a military rank) dated to 1513 CE is well known in the fringe literature, mainly for it’s alleged depiction of Antarctica coastline. It was featured on the Ancient Aliens and it’s often brought by Graham Hancock1, among others, as a proof of ancient civilization or technology we’re not yet aware of, as the first modern mapping of Antarctica wasn’t done until 19th century. The argument is that Pîrî himself must have been drawn from older, more ancient maps, which ties it into the general notion of ancient civilization theory. Graham Hancock’s summary of the argument on The Mysterious Origins of Man TV program. (youtube.com) &amp;#8617;</summary></entry></feed>